<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Fortune in her wits, or, The hour of all men written in Spanish by the most ingenious Don Francisco de Quivedo Villegas ... ; translated into English by Capt. John Stevens.</title>
            <title>Fortuna con seso. English</title>
            <author>Quevedo, Francisco de, 1580-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 231 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 75 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56890</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R5377</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13206290</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13206290</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98488</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56890)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98488)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 435:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Fortune in her wits, or, The hour of all men written in Spanish by the most ingenious Don Francisco de Quivedo Villegas ... ; translated into English by Capt. John Stevens.</title>
                  <title>Fortuna con seso. English</title>
                  <author>Quevedo, Francisco de, 1580-1645.</author>
                  <author>Stevens, John, d. 1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 131 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Sare ... F. Saunders ... and Tho. Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Fortuna con seso.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98488:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98488:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FORTUNE IN HER WITS, OR, <hi>The Hour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>TEN In <hi>Spaniſh</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the moſt Ingenious Don <hi>Franciſco
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Quivedo Villegas,</hi> Author of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Viſions of Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh BY CAPT. JOHN STEVENS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Sare</hi> at <hi>Gray's-Inn-Gate, F. Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> in the
<hi>New-Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Tho. Bennet</hi> in <hi>St. Paul's</hi> Church-Yard. 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98488:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98488:2"/>
            <head>TO <hi>Mark Arundell</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THere are three Faults, which I have obſerved in many Dedications, and which I have reſolved care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to avoid. The firſt is, the Choice of an Unworthy Perſon to Dedicate to. The ſecond, the ſervile Flattery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on him. And the laſt, the Tediouſneſs of the Epiſtle. The two laſt ſeem to be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Conſequences to the firſt; for when an Author has made
<pb facs="tcp:98488:3"/>choice of a Vile Patron, he is obliged to turn Paraſite in his own defence, and to defile much Paper, as well as nauſeate the Reader with a multitude of Fawning Sentences, ſtolen out of ancient Panegyricks ſpoken to Wicked Heathens, who yet were better Men than thoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Chriſtians to whom the ſame Praiſes are now applied.</p>
            <p>I believe Envy it ſelf cannot find place to cenſure the Choice I have made, and only Envy is capable of attempting it, which if it ſhould, there is yet this Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, that we know this Vice, tho aiming to devour and tear others, only gnaws and wounds it ſelf. Good Men, who are the true Judges of Merit, know yours to be far above all I can offer; and yet I make no doubt but
<pb facs="tcp:98488:3"/>you will look upon this as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy your Acceptance; for Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity regards not the Gift, but the intention of the Giver. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> not only accepted of the Water brought him by the Three Worthies from the Ciſtern in <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> but alſo offered it to our Lord, becauſe thoſe Men had brought it with the hazard of their Lives. It was not the Water that was of ſuch value, but the Zeal of thoſe Men to ſerve him that made it precious. Accept,
<hi>Sir,</hi> in like manner here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and regard not the value of the Offering, but the Will of him that offers.</p>
            <p>Where Merit is, there can be no Flattery, and therefore ſhould a better Pen than mine under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to make your Character publick, it might find Subject
<pb facs="tcp:98488:4"/>enough to employ it ſelf with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out falling into that Vice. It is peculiar to the Unworthy, only they delight in it, and yet it is that which moſt expoſes them to ſcorn. To commend Wicked Perſons, by attributing to them Virtues they are wholly void of, is no other than to extol the Whiteneſs of an <hi>Ethiopian;</hi> for the Vices of the former are no leſs viſible than the Blackneſs of the latter, and to commend them, for what is not in them is rather a reproach than a commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But thoſe who like you are truly Virtuous, are alſo free from the vanity of taking delight in publick Praiſes, becauſe no emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Virtue can be long conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, its own luſtre will attract the Eyes of all Men, and therefore it needs no foreign helps to make
<pb facs="tcp:98488:4"/>it publickly known. Virtue car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries its Reward and its Honour with it. It is better to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, than to fall ſhort in a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Character. Yours, <hi>Sir,</hi> is above all Flattery, and ſince it can receive no acceſſion by a juſt Praiſe, ought to receive no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution through the fault of my Pen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sir,</hi> I am obliged to draw to a concluſion, leſt I ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for incurring the ſame Fault I blame in others, which is Tediouſneſs. It will be needleſs to give you an account of my Author; he is well known to the World, and, I doubt not, but to you in particular. As for the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, it is expoſed to every Mans Cenſure, yet if you approve of it, I ſhall not queſtion but it may pleaſe; and if it pleaſe ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:98488:5"/>as are Competent Judges, it is no matter for the reſt. I think, <hi>Sir,</hi> I have avoided thoſe three Faults I mentioned at firſt, by chooſing you to Dedicate to, by forbearing your juſt Commendations, leſt Malice ſhould call them Flattery, and by reducing all I had to ſay to this ſmall compaſs. All that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains is once more to beg a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Reception and kind Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance for this ſmall Offering, which comes not alone, being well attended by the good Wiſhes for your Proſperity and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR, </salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Obedient, and moſt Humble Servant, <hi>JOHN STEVENS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:98488:5"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>DON <hi>Franciſco de Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedo Villegas,</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this ſmall Work, has been a Perſon ſo famous in this Age, among all thoſe who underſtand the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue, that it is much to be admired that <hi>England</hi> ſhould ſtill be ſo great a ſtranger to his Talent. Nothing of his has hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto appeared in <hi>Engliſh</hi> but his <hi>Viſions,</hi> and how general an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptation they have met with every Man is ſenſible. Being Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged thereby, I take the Liberty to preſent the Publick with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall Piece of the ſame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, nothing inferior in it ſelf to
<pb facs="tcp:98488:6"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:98488:6"/> 
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:98488:7"/>any of the <hi>Viſions,</hi> unleſs it has ſuſtained loſs in the Tranſlation, which muſt be left to the Judgment of Judicious, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbiaſſed Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</p>
            <p>I cannot but lay hold of this Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of undeceiving thoſe who look upon my Author as only a Faceti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſort of inconſiderable Satyriſt. As to his Birth he was a Man of good Quality, and Born to a good Eſtate being as he is Stiled in the Title of his Works, Knight of the Order of <hi>Santjago,</hi> or <hi>St. James,</hi> and Lord of the Town called <hi>Villa de la Torre de Juan Abad,</hi> which is ſomewhat more than a Lord of a Mannor with us in regard that in
<hi>Spain</hi> ſuch Lords have the power of Life and Death wihin their Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, and are therefore called <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nores de Horca y Cuchillo,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:98488:7"/>is, Lords with power of Hanging and Beheading. His Parts are too great a Subject for my intended brevity, only this muſt not be paſſed in ſilence, that he was the <hi>Spaniſh Ovid,</hi> for Wit flowed naturally from him without Study, and it was as eaſie to him to write Verſe as Proſe Beſides he was well Verſed in the <hi>Latin, Greek, Hebrew,</hi> and
<hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> Languages, and had imbibed the Marrow of the beſt Authors in them. But his Works will be a laſting Monument of his great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities. All of theſe, that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, is contained in Three large Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes in Quarto, two whereof, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain his Works in Proſe, and the third his Poems. Theſe are all the Poems of his that have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to been committed to the Preſs, but a Friend of his, who was fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarly acquainted with him, affirms
<pb facs="tcp:98488:8"/>in the Preface to that Book, that they are not the twentieth part of what he writ. We have alſo ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proof that more might have been expected, which is, that this Volume is divided into Six Muſes, the other Three being deſigned to compoſe another. Thus much may ſuffice as to the Author and his Works in general.</p>
            <p>Now as to this in particular, I will not give any Character of it, leſt it ſhould ſeem deſigned to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſs the Reader, and I hope it will appear beautiful enough of it ſelf without the help of any bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed Ornaments. It was writ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Fifty years ago, as may appear by ſeveral Paſſages in it, as parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly where ſpeaking of the <hi>French</hi> he mentions Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> as Prime Miniſter; Treating of the
<pb facs="tcp:98488:8"/>
               <hi>Dutch,</hi> he urges their incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and
<hi>Weſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies;</hi> and in his Diſcourſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>England,</hi> he hints at the Rebellion then about breaking out.</p>
            <p>As I have ſaid nothing in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of the Original, ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will I ſay any thing in Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Tranſlation. If good, it needs none, and if otherwiſe, it deſerves none. Only the Reader may obſerve, I have followed the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> as cloſe as the difference of the two Languages could bear, which I did to preſerve as near as poſſible the Authors Senſe entire, without intruding any Notions of my own.</p>
            <p>My Deſign is not to make up this ſmall Volume with a long Preface, for this has already extended far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than I had propoſed to my ſelf.
<pb facs="tcp:98488:9"/>I will therefore conclude, advertiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reader, that according to the Acceptance. I ſhall ſind this meets withall, I will proceed to give the Publick a farther Taſte of the Works of Don <hi>Franciſco de Quevedo.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98488:9"/>
            <head>FORTUNE IN HER WITS, AND THE Hour of all Men.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>JOVE</hi> in a Splenetick Rage rent his very Throat, and pierced the Earth with his Bawling; for to ſay it only pierced the Heaven, where he reſided, had not been an Expreſſion emphatical enough. He ſummon'd all the Gods in great haſte to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble before him in Council. The firſt that appeared was <hi>Mars,</hi> that Celeſtial Don <hi>Quixot,</hi> armed Cap-a pee, with his Spear advanced, and making Paſſes in the Air. Next to him came the Platter-faced Deity <hi>Bacchus,</hi> with a Periwig made of Vine-Branches, his Eyes overflowing, his Mouth like a Wine-Preſs belching out Liquor at ſecond-hand, his Speech Stammering, his Steps Reeling, an his Brain
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98488:10"/>entoxicated with the Juice of the Grape. On the other ſide appeared Hobling
<hi>Saturn,</hi> that Bugbear, Child-eating Deity, gorging himſelf with his own Sons. With him came Drip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping <hi>Neptune,</hi> the Watery God, that bears an old Woman's Jaw-bone inſtead of a Scepter; for that is the Engliſh of a Trident; about him hung the Sea-weeds like Rags, clung to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the Spawn of Fiſh, ſmelling ſtrong as of a <hi>Friday</hi> Dinner, and with the Water that ran from him laying the Duſt of the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coal raiſed by his Follower
<hi>Pluto,</hi> a God of Devils, with his Head and Face powder'd with Soot, perfum'd with Brimſtone and Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, and Cloathed in ſuch profound Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that he was ſcarce diſcernable, tho cloſe followed by the Glaring Sun, with his Brazen Face and Tinſel Beard: That Fox-coloured rambling Planet, that winds up the Threads of all Lives, affects being cloſe Trimm'd, doats on the Guitars and the Lute, and yet is employed in tacking of Days one upon the back of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and heaping of Years and Ages, having conſpir'd with Cares and Apoplexies for the Peopling, of Church-yards. <hi>Venus,</hi> as ſhe came, filled the Heavens with the vaſt Circumference of her Fardingale, hiding the Five <hi>Zones</hi> under her Petticoats, her Face but half lick'd, and the Tower that was to cover her bald Skull hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all awry for haſte. After her came the <hi>Moon</hi> with her Face cut into Quarters, the Night-walking Lady that only ſerves to ſave Candle and Lanthorn. The God <hi>Pan</hi> ruſhed in with a great noiſe, being followed by two
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98488:10"/>vaſt Herds of <hi>Sylvans, Faunes,</hi> and other Hairy and Cloven-footed Gods of the Woods. All Heaven ſwarm'd with <hi>Manes, Lemures, Lares,</hi> and other little Deities, who all took their Chairs, the Goddeſſes<note n="*" place="margin">In <hi>Spain</hi> the Women do not ſit on Chairs, but on Cuſhions upon the Ground.</note> ſquatting down like Taylors upon their Legs, the whole Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly attentively fixing their Eyes upon <hi>Jove. Mans</hi> ratling his Armour like the Harmony of a Tinkers Kettle, ſtarted up, and looking ſtern as a Bully after a Beating, thundred out theſe Words: <hi>Open thy Mouth with a Vengeance, thou mighty Hector of this upper Region, open thy Mouth, I ſay, and prate, for you ſeem to be in a Dream. Jove</hi> thus accoſted in ſo rough a Dialect, whilſt, tho it was Summer, he held the ſparkling Thunderbolt, (when it had been much properer to have cooled himſelf with a Fan) raiſing his Voice, that it might ſound the greater, anſwered: <hi>Keep your Prating Tongue betwixt your Teeth, and let us call</hi> Mercury. In the twinkling of an Eye <hi>Mercury</hi> dropt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, holding his little Wand like a Juggler; his Heel fledged, and his little Hat in the ſhape of a Muſhroom on his Head. Then <hi>Jove</hi> ſaid, <hi>Thou Ubiquitary God, ſhoot thy ſelf into the World, and in a trice drag</hi> Fortune <hi>hither by the Ears.</hi> In an inſtant the Spright of <hi>Olympus,</hi> clapping Wings inſtead of Spurs, to his Heels, vaniſhed with ſuch ſwiftneſs, that the ſight could not diſtinguiſh between his departure and return. He returned like <hi>Lazarillo</hi> leading Blind <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,</hi> who with a Staff in one Hand felt out her Way, and in the other held a String, which was a Bridle to a little Dog. She ſtood a tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toe
<pb facs="tcp:98488:11"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:98488:11"/>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98488:12"/>upon a Globe, in the midſt of a Wheel wound with Threads, Breads, Ribbans, Cords, and Ropes, all which, as it moved, knit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together, and unknit again. Behind, as her Maid, came <hi>Opportunity,</hi> a Broad-faced, Flat-noſed, Bald-pated Wench, only on the top of her Forehead was one ſingle Lock ſcarce big enough to make one good Whisker. This Lock was as ſlippery as an Eell, and played in the Air, being moved at the breath of every Word. By her Hands it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared that <hi>Opportunity</hi> lived upon hard labour, and doing all the Drudgery of
<hi>Fortune.</hi> All the Gods appeared diſguſted at the ſight of <hi>Fortune,</hi> and ſome of them made ſigns as if ſhe had turned their Stomachs, when ſhe in a ſqueeking Tone, and ſpeaking at a venture, ſaid; <hi>My Eyes being in their Swadling Clouts, and my Sight in the dark, I cannot diſcover who you are that make up this Aſſembly; but be you who you will, my diſcourſe is directed to you all, and particularly to thee,</hi> O Jove, <hi>who ſpitteſt thy Thunderbolts after the drippings of the Clouds; tell me what Whimſey came into thy Head to ſend for me, whereas for ſo many Ages paſt thou haſt never ſo much as thought on me: Perhaps thou and the reſt of thy Mob of Godlings have forgot how great the extent of my power is, and that I have toſſed about both thee and them no leſs than I do poor Mortals. Jove</hi> ſwelling, and looking ſtern, replied; <hi>Thou Sot, thy Extravagancies, thy Follies, and thy Wickedneſs, are ſo great, that Mortals believe, ſince we do not curb thee, there are no Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that Heaven lies waſte, and that I am a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98488:12"/>poor inſignificant God: They complain, that thou giveſt to Villanies thoſe Rewards which are due to Merit; that Virtue is unregarded, and Vice encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged; that thou placeſt thoſe in the Judgment-Seats, who ought to be preferred to the Gallows; that thou beſtow'ſt Dignities on thoſe whoſe Ears ſhould be Nail'd to the Pillory; and that thou oppreſſeſt and impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheſt thoſe thou oughteſt to raiſe and enrich. Fortune</hi> looking pale with anger, and chafing, ſaid; <hi>I am no Fool, I know what I do, and all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are guided by Prudence: You who call me raſh Sot, remember you Kackled like a Gooſe to</hi> Leda, <hi>that you played the falſe Coiner with</hi> Danae, <hi>that you Bellowed and acted the Bull for</hi> Europa, <hi>and have been guilty of a thouſand other Roguiſh mad Pranks, and that all thoſe who attend you have been only Crows and Magpies; None of which Fopperies can be laid to my charge. If Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Merit are laid aſide, and Vertuous Men paſs unrewarded, the fault is not altogether mine; many deſpiſe what I offer them, and their Modeſty is laid at my door as a Crime; Others rather than ſtretch out their hands, let ſlip what I tender them; Others ſnatch it from me without my conſent; More Men are enriched by forcing it from me, than by my free gift. There are more that ſteal what I refuſe, than that keep what I give them; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny receive of me that they know not how to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, they loſe it and pretend I take it from them; Many accuſe me for miſplacing Gifts on others, which would be much worſe employed on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; There is no Man happy without being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied by many, and no Man is miſerable without being contemned by all; This Maid has always
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98488:13"/>ſerved me, without her I have never done any thing; her Name is</hi> Opportunity, <hi>hear her, and learn of a Drudging Wench how to judge of things.</hi> Then
<hi>Opportunity</hi> letting her Tongue run for fear of letting her ſelf ſlip ſaid; <hi>I am that ſort of good natured Female that offer my ſelf to all Men, many find but few enjoy me: I am a Female</hi> Sampſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>for all my ſtrength lies in my Hair, he that can hold faſt by my Lock need not fear to be thrown by my Miſtreſs: It is I that manage, I that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute her, and when Men know not how to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue their own intereſts, and make their advantages, they lay all the blame upon me: Folly and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance have furniſhed Men with theſe Helliſh Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences,</hi> Who would have believed? I did not think. I did not reflect on it. I did not know. It is well enough yet. What matter's it. It is neither here nor there. To morrow will do. There's time enough. There is no wanting an Opportunity. I ſlipt my time. I know my own buſineſs. I am no Fool. Let not that trouble you. I am bound to ſee it. That's a Jeſt. Never believe it. I'le do my own bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. I ſhall not want. God will provide. All days are not alike. If one thing fails, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hits. 'Tis well enough. What is that to him? It is my Opinion. It cannot be. Do not tell me. I can ſee into it. Time will ſhew it. Let the World run. It is I that am to anſwer for it. I am no ſuch Man. Very lively. Let them talk as they pleaſe. Over Shooes over Boots. I underſtand Trap. Time will ſhew, <hi>they ſay, and</hi> But, <hi>and</hi> Perhaps, <hi>and the Conlcuſion of all poſitive Blockheads,</hi> Come
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98488:13"/>what will. <hi>Theſe Follies make Men Conceited, Sloathful and Careleſs; Theſe are the Gaps that I ſlip out at; Theſe are the Rubs that overſet my Miſtreſs's Wheel; and theſe the Guſts that ſplit her Sail. Then if the Fools let me ſlip by them, what fault is it in me to be gone? If they lay the Rubs in the way of my Miſtreſſes Wheel, why do they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of its jolting. If they know it is a Wheel whereof every part is ſometimes up and ſometimes down, and that each part deſcends in order to riſe, and riſes in order to fall again, why do they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle themſelves in it? The Sun has ſtood ſtill, the Wheel of Fortune never did. Whoſoever has thought to fix it, only gave it a check that it might whirl again with the greater fury. Its motion like that of Time puts a period to all Worldly Felicities and Calamities, to all the Lives in the World, and by degrees to the World it ſelf. This,</hi> O Jove, <hi>is matter of fact, let who will oppoſe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fortune</hi> encouraged at theſe Words, and turning on all hands like a Weathercock, ſaid; Opportunity <hi>has diſcovered how unjuſtly I am accuſed; however, I am reſolved my ſelf to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince thee, thou Supream Thunderer, and all thy Company, carrouſing in</hi> Nectar
<hi>and</hi> Ambroſia, <hi>notwithſtanding that I always had, now have, and ſhall ever continue to have as much power over you, as over the meaneſt Rabble in the World. I hope to ſee your Divinities ſtarving with Hunger and Cold for want of Victims, and that not ſo much as a black Pudding ſhall be ſacrificed to you, but you ſhall only ſerve to fill up Ballads, and be brought in for Rhime ſake in Love Songs for the Diverſion of the Mob, and Encouragement of Hawkers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:98488:14"/>
               <hi>A Curſe light on all thy Deſigns</hi> (quoth the <hi>Sun</hi>) <hi>for ſo impudently blaſpheming againſt our Power. Were it permitted me, as I am the</hi> Sun,
<hi>I would ſwelter thee with Heat, ſcorch thee with my Rays, and make thee run mad with the Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach. Go dry up the Dirt</hi> (<hi>ſaid</hi> Fortune) <hi>ripen Cucumbers, furniſh Plagues for the good of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, and aſſiſt thoſe that louſe themſelves at thy light; for know I have ſeen you keep Cows, and run after a Wench, who, tho you was the</hi> Sun, <hi>left you in the dark. Remember your Son was burnt to death like a Heretick, therefore be ſilent hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let thoſe ſpeak to whom it belongs.</hi> Then <hi>Jove</hi> with all his gravity utter'd theſe Words; Fortune; <hi>both you, and that impudent Wench thy Servant, are much in the right, in many things you have ſaid; however, for the general ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all People, it is irrevocably decreed, that on the ſame day and hour throughout the whole World every Man be put into thoſe Circumſtances he juſtly deſerves. This muſt be, therefore appoint the day <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd the hour. Fortune</hi> replied,
<hi>To what purpoſe is it to delay what muſt be, let it be to day, let us know what time of the day it is.</hi> The <hi>Sun,</hi> who is the Standard of Clockmakers, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd; <hi>This is the</hi> 20th <hi>of</hi> June, <hi>as to the time of the day, it is Three and three quarters and ſix minutes after Noon. Mind then</hi> (quoth <hi>Fortune</hi>) <hi>and as ſoon as it ſtrikes Four, you ſhall ſee how affairs go upon Earth.</hi> Then falling to work, ſhe began to greaze the Axletree of her Wheel, to ſettle the Spokes, remove the Nails, and entangle ſeveral Cords, ſlackning ſome, and ſtraining others, till the <hi>Sun</hi> cried out, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98488:14"/>ſaid; <hi>It is juſt Four, neither over nor under, for this very inſtant I have brought the ſhade of the Gnomons of all Clocks upon the fourth</hi> Poſtmeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian
<hi>Line.</hi> No ſooner had he uttered theſe Words than <hi>Fortune,</hi> as if ſhe had been play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a Cymbal, began to unwind her Wheel, which whirling about like a Hurrican, hudled all the World into an unparallelled confuſion. <hi>Fortune</hi> gave a mighty Squeek, ſaying,
<hi>Fly Wheel, and the Devil drive thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</note>That very moment, a Phyſician riding along on his Mule, a Snails Gallop, in purſuit of Diſeaſes, was ſurprized by the wonderful in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of that Hour which was to give all Men their due, and on a ſudden he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the poſture of a Hangman, with his Legs a-croſs the Shoulders of his Patient, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<hi>Credo</hi> inſtead of <hi>Recipe,</hi> as if he had been going to turn him off the Ladder.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guazil.</note>At a ſmall diſtance followed in the ſame Street a Criminal that was Whipt, the Cryer before proclaiming his Miſdemeanours, the Hangman behind laſhing him, he riding upon an Aſs, and naked from the Waſte upward like a Galley Slave. This was his poſture at the Striking of the Clock, which was no ſooner over, but the Horſe the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Alguazil</hi> is an Officer in <hi>Spain</hi> that apprehends Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, and attends the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of Juſtice. Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals in <hi>Spain</hi> are carried to the Gallows, and Whipt upon an Aſs.</note> 
               <hi>Alguazil</hi> rid on threw him, and the † Aſs the Criminal; The Horſe took up the Criminal, and having changed Stations, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be laſhed who before at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the Execution, and he to attend who
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98488:15"/>before was laſhed. The<note n="*" place="margin">The Scribe, in Spaniſh
<hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crivano,</hi> is a ſort of Clerk al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable from the
<hi>Alguazil.</hi>
               </note> Scribe alighted to ſet all again to rights, and taking out his Pen it grew out into a Galley Oar, and inſtead of Writing, he began to Row.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="†" place="margin">The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary.</note>The Scavengers Carts paſſing through another Street at the firſt moment of the Hour, ſtopped before an Apothecary's Shop, and on a ſudden all the Dirt began to fly out of the Cart into the Shop, whence the Pots and Glaſſes leaped out into the Carts with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful noiſe and confuſion. But the Dirt and the Pots meeting, as the one went in and the other out, it was obſerved, that the Dirt very ſqueamiſhly cried out, Keep off. Mean while the Duſt men were not idle, but with their Brooms and Shovels ſwept together and threw up into the Carts heaps of Painted Whores, Pocky Beaus, and Powdred Fops.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cheat.</note>A certain notorious Knave had built a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous Houſe, not much inferior to a Palace, with a ſtately Porch, and over it a Noble Coat of Arms cut in Stone, and an Inſcription as if he had been of ſome conſiderable Family. The Owner was an errant Thief, who under the ſhadow of his Employ had ſtole the whole Coſt of the Fabrick. He was then in the Houſe, and at the Door was a Bill ſignifying three Apartments were there to be let. The Hour came, O good God, who can expreſs ſuch a Prodigy? Every Stone, every Brick in the whole Structure, fell aſunder, the Tiles flew ſome to the top of one Houſe, and ſome to another, the Rafters, Doors and Windows hurried into ſeveral Houſes, to the terrour of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98488:15"/>the Owners who looked upon this Reſtitution as the effects of an Earthquake, and thought it was the end of the World. The Iron Bars and Grates walked about the ſtreets ſeeking whom they belonged to. The Armes that ſtood over the Doores poſted away to a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Gentleman's ſeat, whence this Curſed Villain pretended himſelf to be deſcended, The Rogue himſelf ſtripped of his Fabrick, was left alone at the corner of a Street, with only the Bill upon him which had been at the Door, but that ſo changed, that whereas before the purport of it was, This Houſe is to be Lett unfurniſhed, inquire within of the Landlord: Now it was, This Thief is to be Lett unfurniſhed, whoſoever will hire him may come in without knocking,
<hi>ſince the Houſe does not hinder it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oppoſite to this Man lived a Pawnbroker,<note place="margin">Pawn-Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</note> who ſeeing his Neighbour's Houſe vaniſh, thought to ſecure himſelf, ſaying, the Houſes remove from their Landlords, this is a baſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention. But tho' he uſed the utmoſt diligence to ſecure himſelf, the hour was come, and on a ſudden an Eſcritore, a Silver Table and, a rich Hanging which he kept in Captivity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pawned to him, flew from the Walls with ſuch violence, that a piece of the hanging in its way to the Window wound it ſelf about him, and carried him through the Air above an hundred paces, where he dropt on the top of a Houſe, not without ſome bruiſes. From thence to his unſpeakable Grief, he ſaw all he had hurried away to the right owners. After all
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98488:16"/>the reſt came out the Letters of Nobility,<note place="margin">In
<hi>Spain</hi> Gentlemen take out their Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, which who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can ſhow, is free from Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts.</note> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he had lent a Sum of Mony to the Gentleman they belonged to for two Months, on condition to receive five and Twenty <hi>per Cent.</hi> Intereſt for that ſhort time. Theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to his aſtoniſhment, as they paſſed by him, ſaid, Thou Barbarous Tyrant over Pawns, if our Maſter for our ſake cannot be arreſted for Debt, what reaſon can you ſhow, to keep us in Priſon? This ſaid, they leaped into a Cooks ſhop, where the Gentleman that owned them ſate with a hungry Belly envying every bit he ſaw another put into his Mouth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Talker.</note>An Eternal Talker, who laviſhed as many words, as would have furniſhed half a ſcore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tolerable Bablers, and whoſe Tongue ſeemed to be the perpetual motion ſo long ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, was buſy confounding his whole Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood with the overflowing of his clack; when, on a ſudden, the hour being come, his Tongue was tied up, and he ſtrugling to run on, only ſtutter'd and ſtammer'd the ſame ſyllables over without end; and finding his mouth ſtopped, his very Eyes and Ears ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to forget their own Office, and burſt out into talk.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Judges</note>Five Judges were ſitting on the Bench upon a Tryal; one of them meerly out of ill nature was projecting how he might caſt both parties. Another being a meer Ignoramus, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding nothing of the matter, was reſolved to give his opinion, as all Blockheads do, at a venture. The Third a doating old Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low who had ſlept moſt part of the Tryal, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98488:16"/>Judgment like? <hi>Pilate</hi>'s Wife, by Dreams, was conſidering with which of his Fellows he ſhould cloſe in opinion at random. The Fourth who was a Learned and Upright Judge, ſate like a Cypher next to the laſt, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing corrupted with Bribes, ſtrained the ſenſe of the Law, and drew over to his Party the other three; but at the very inſtant of giving Judgment the hour commenced, and inſtead of ſaying, The Court is of opinion, that ſuch a one is Caſt and Condemned, he ſaid, The Court does award, that we be Damned, and accordingly we are Damned. Be the ſentence fulfilled ſaid an unknown Voice. In a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their Gowns were converted into Snake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skins, and they falling together by the Ears, ſoon ſtripped one anothers Faces, every one carrying away his Neighbours Beard, to ſhow that their Judgment lay in their Fingers, and not in their Heads.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Match-maker.</note>A Match maker was buſie intoxicating an Honeſt Man's Brain, who being weary of a quiet Life and a good Eſtate, was thinking of Marrying; he propoſed to him a conſummated Jilt, and ſet her off in this manner. Sir, I will not commend her Birth, becauſe, God be praiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, you have quality enough to beſtow on her; as for Riches, you are plentifully provided; Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in a Wife is a thing of dangerous conſequence; as for matter of Judgment it is you that are to govern her, and you do not take her for a Councellor; ill humours ſhe is not troubled with, her Years are but few, (yet he meant ſhe had but few to Live) ſhe has all the other
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98488:17"/>good qualities you could wiſh. The poor Man in a paſſion cried out, Thou accurſed Divel, what other good qualities can ſhe have, ſince you own ſhe is neither well Born, Rich, Beautiful nor Diſcreet; and all you can ſay for her is, that ſhe is not ill-natur'd. Scarce had he done when the Hour began, and the Curſed Match-maker, who acts the Taylor at Weddings, Stealing, Lying, Cheating, Patching and Piecing, found himſelf Married to the Monſter, he would have vamp'd upon the other Man; and the new Couple falling upon one another, went off Kicking and Scratching, and Crying by turnes, Who are you? What Fortune did you bring, you are not worthy to wipe my Shoes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Poet.</note>A Poet having ſeated himſelf among an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Wits, was rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to them a Pedantick obſcure Poem of his own compoſing, ſo ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed with Latiniſms, ſo cramp'd with Syncopa's, ſo entangled with Parentheſes, and ſo perplexed with Similies and Alluſions, that none of the Company could find either head or tail to it. Upon the turn of the Hour he had gone halfway through his <hi>Jargon,</hi> or Confuſion of Langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and all the hearers preſſing upon him, to pick out, if poſſible, ſome meaning from that Chaos of hard Words, one of them who held a Candle in his hand to inform himſelf the better by over-looking the Paper, put it ſo cloſe that the unfortunate Poem took Fire. The Poet ſtamp'd and tore his hair ſeeing all his labour condemned to the Flames; but he that had fired it pacified him, ſaying, Theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98488:17"/>Verſes are like old tarniſhed Silver Lace, they muſt be firſt burnt, and then perhaps you may ſeparate the pure Metal from the Droſs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Whore.</note>A Topping Whore ſailing out of her Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a mighty Fardingal, ſo large ſhe could ſcarce crowd through her narrow En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and filled both ſides of the Street with the vaſt compaſs of her Coats, was overtaken by the firſt minute of the all-ruling Hour, and on a ſudden being ſet upon her Head, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared like a Bell inverted. Here was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered a vaſt Fardel of Rags that compoſed a Rumprowl, with a Piece of Tapeſtry Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rowled up to ſet out her Hips, which in the turn looſening, and falling over her Belly, there appeared at the bottom of it an <hi>Holo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernes</hi>'s his Head. The whole Street was alarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Shouts of the Rabble that beheld her. She Skreiked, but her Voice being drowned in the labyrinth of her Petticoats fallen about her Head, the noiſe ſounded as if it came out from a deep Cavern. She had certainly been ſtifled in the Crouch, but that at the ſame time a Beau ſtrutting along the Street with falſe Calves, and three falſe Teeth; and two Dotards with their grey Hair, and Beard coloured black; and 3 old Bald pated Fellows that wore Periwigs; They were all ſurpriſed by the Influence of that Hour. The Beau feeling his Calves ſlink away, thought to cry for help, believing his Legs would be ſtolen; but at the firſt motion of his Tongue, out drops his Teeth. The Dotards Beards and Hair became as grey as a Badger, ſo that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98488:18"/>they ſcarce knew one another; and the Bald Fellows Periwigs flew away with their Hats, leaving them nothing differing from bare Skuls, but that they wore Whiskers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</note>A certain Nobleman had a Favourite Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick who devoured his Subſtance, this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick was cheated by his Servant, the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant by his Man, the Man by his Friend, the Friend by his Wench, and the Wench was deluded by the Devil. Now the Hour being come, the Devil who ſeemed to be at ſuch a diſtance from the Lord, ſeizes upon the Whore, the Whore on her Spark, the Spark on the Man, the Man on the Servant, the Servant on his Maſter, and the Maſter on his Lord, and the Devil poſſeſſing him, after run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Gantlet through the Whore, the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the Man, the Servant and Domeſtick, in a Helliſh Rage he falls upon his Domeſtick, the Domeſtick on his Servant, the Servant on his Man, the Man on his Friend, the Friend on his Whore, and ſhe layed about upon them all; and thus exagitated by Furies, they tore one another to pieces, all their Frauds and Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were laid open, and the Devil who had managed the whole Contrivance without diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, ſwept them away all in a Cluſter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Rich Wife.</note>A Rich Married Woman ſat at her Dreſſing Table, plaiſtering up her Wrinkled freckly Skin, ſleeking her Weatherbeaten Forehead, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eyebrows with a Pencil, colouring her decayed Cheeks with Spaniſh Wooll, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her pale Lips of a lively Cherry colour. By her, as an Aſſiſtant, kneel'd a Decrepid
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98488:18"/>old Governant like a Skeleton, Dreſt up, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Tour of an extraordinary magnitude. Next to her ſtood a young Chambermaid, yet a Novice at the Trade of Daubing, and in her Hands a pair of Iron Bolſter'd Bodies, contriv'd to rectifie two mighty Excreſcencies that diſcompoſed the figure of the Body. In this poſture ſate the Lady confounding and ſhaming her very Looking-glaſs, when the Hour commenced, and ſhe led by the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful influence thereof, began to lay about her, applying the White-waſh to her Hair, the Black Lead to her Teeth, the Red to her Eyebrows and Forehead, clapping the Tower on her Jaws, and lacing on the Bolſtered Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies the wrong way. Thus in a moment ſhe was converted into a Skarecrow, with a curled Beard, and four Hunches more gaſtly and frightful than an Hobgoblin. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernant thinking ſhe was diſtracted, ſtarted up, and fled with might and main; the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bermaid ſounded away as if ſhe had ſeen the Devil, and the Lady enraged in that horrible poſture ſcoured after the Governant. The noiſe brought the Husband, who ſeeing his Wife, thought ſhe was poſſeſs'd by ſome Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Spirit, and ran with ſpeed to call a Prieſt to apply Exorciſms to her.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Abuſes in Goals.</note>A Sovereign Prince reſolved to be preſent himſelf at a Goal Delivery, being informed that his Officers made the Priſon their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, where they bought and ſold Crimes and Criminals at all ſorts of Rates and Prizes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing Robbers for Gold, and Murderers
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98488:19"/>for ready Money. He ordered the Priſoners to be brought before him, and found they had been apprehended for the Crimes they had committed, but were detained through the Avarice of their Keepers, who computed what ſome had and might have ſtolen, and what others had or might have of their own: ſo that their Cauſe was depending as long as their Stock laſted, and the day it expired was the day they were puniſhed; it being plain they were apprehended for the ill they had done, and executed for what they had not. Among the reſt were two condemned to be Hanged the next day. One of theſe having compounded with his Adverſary, was kept as a Priſoner at large. The other they deſigned to Hang for Robbing, after having been three years a Priſoner, during which time they had devoured all he ſtole, and all he, his Father, and Wife, by whom he had two Children, were worth. Thus far had this Prince pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded when the Hour commenced, and he turning pale with anger, ſaid; <hi>This Man you diſigned to diſcharge becauſe he has compounded with his Adverſary, ſhall be hanged to morrow; for the contrary would be expoſing of Lives to Sale, and the Price of buying off an Appeal would prove the purchaſe of a Husband's Blood from the Wife, of the Father's from a Son, and of a Son's from the Father; ſo that Pardons for Murder being to be bought, a Rate would be ſet upon every Man's Life, and thus all Examples of Juſtice would ceaſe, it being an eaſie matter to perſwade the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellant, that a Thouſand or Five hundred Crowns
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98488:19"/>will do him more good, than the Hanging of his Enemy. There are two Parties concerned in all publick Offences,</hi> viz. <hi>Juſtice and the Perſon Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, and it is no leſs neceſſary that the former ſhould puniſh, than that the latter ſhould forgive. This Thief, whom after three years impriſonment you intended to Hang, ſhall be ſent to the Galleys; for as it had been juſtice to Hang him three years ago, ſo now it would be a Barbarous Wrong, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in him you would hang his Father, Wife, and Children, who are innocent, and whoſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance by theſe delays you have devoured. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member a Story of a Man, who enraged that the Mice gnawed his Papers, Cruſts of Bread, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Cheeſe, and old Shooes, took in Cats to deſtroy the Mice; but perceiving the Cats not only eat the Mice, but ſtole his Meat out of the Pot, and tore it off the Spit, that one day they ſpoiled a Fowl, and another a whole Joint of Meat, he kill'd the Cats, and ſaid,</hi> The Mice for my Money. <hi>Do you apply ſhe Moral to this Fable, ſince you like Devouring Cats, inſtead of cleanſing the State from Vermin, do catch and eat the Thieves, who are little Mice, that Pick a Pocket, Cut a Purſe, Snatch a Hat, or Steal a Cloak, and at the ſame time you waſte the Country, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume Eſtates, and deſtroy whole Families. Infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Wretches, I will rather endure Mice than maintain Cats.</hi> This ſaid, he ordered all the Priſoners to be diſcharged, and the Officers to be apprehended. There was a wonderful Noiſe and Confuſion, thoſe lamented who before were inexorable; and the Priſoners loaded thoſe with Fetters and Chains, who before had Fetter'd them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98488:20"/>
               <note place="margin">Old Women hiding their Age.</note>Several Women appeared in a Street, ſome of them a-foot, and tho many were well ſtricken in years, they tript it along like young Girls, proud of their little Feet and white Petticoats. Others were pack'd up in a Coach, diſſembling their Age with their Coy Looks, and playing with their white Hands. Others Dreſs'd like <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Babies, and afraid the Air ſhould diſcompoſe them, were ſet up in Glaſs Cupboards or Sedans, carried by greaſy Fellows, the fartheſt proſpect of the Lady's Eyes being the neighbouring Haunches of the foremoſt, and the next Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume to their Noſes proceeding from his ſweaty Feet, which being free from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrance of Socks ſent it up the freſher. All of them were as gay as young Girls, ſtriving to be taken for ſuch, concealing their Age as they would their Shame, and Ogle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with thoſe Eyes that were ready to ſink into their Heads. Upon the very entrance of the Hour they were met by <hi>Maximus, Origa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Argolius,</hi> and a pack of other ancient Aſtrologers, with their Ephemerides in their Hands, who preſently attack'd them, to fix upon every one the date of her Life to the very year, day, hour, minute, and ſecond of their Nativity. Theſe Conjurers ſet up a Cry, <hi>Own your Age, ye Wretches, ſince it is your Doom, you are Forty two years old,</hi> 2 <hi>months, days,</hi> 2 <hi>hours,</hi> 9 <hi>minutes, and</hi> 20 <hi>ſeconds,</hi> ſays one of the Aſtrologers to one of the Ladies. Good God! who can expreſs the terrible Shreiks ſhe rais'd; all that could be underſtood
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98488:20"/>was, <hi>you Lye, it is falſe, I am not Fifteen; Lord, what a Rogue this is to ſay ſuch a thing!</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cryed, <hi>I am not Eighteen;</hi> a Third, <hi>I am but Thirteen; I am a mere Child, an Infant,</hi> crys another. <hi>Origanus</hi> was writing her Age upon the Back of one, as if it had been a Bill up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Door, and it was to this effect; <hi>This Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was deliver'd into the World in the Year</hi> 1629. She perceiving by this means, it would appear ſhe was 67 Years of Age, all in a rage cryed out, <hi>Thou Old doating Emblem of Death, I am but juſt come into the World, my Teeth are not all cut<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Thou decayed piece of Antiquity,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Origanus, Teeth will never ſpring under old Stumps, look upon your Date: I'll own no Date,</hi> quoth ſhe, and thus falling together by the Ears, the controverſie ended in a wonderful confuſion.</p>
            <p>After a ſumptuous Dinner a mighty Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſate ſate lulling his Pride with the falſe Flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that fell from the mouths of his Servants.<note place="margin">Sycophants.</note> A grumbling noiſe reſounded from his cram'd gutts, which could not agree in the Cooks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of his Belly, with the ſtrange medly of varieties he had devoured. He foam'd at the Mouth, the Wine boiling over, and his whole Face was inflamed and bloated with the exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of his Stomach. At each word he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, tho' never ſo ſtupid, the ſtanders by like Men in a Frenzie poured out Superlative Encomiums: An admirable ſentence crys one, nothing could be expreſt finer ſays another, moſt incomparable words ſays a Third; and laſtly, a Paraſite who laboured to out-flatter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98488:21"/>all the reſt, ſtraining a lye to the utmoſt pitch exclaimes, Learning it ſelf ſtands ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to hear you, and even admiration is out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done. The great Man ſtrutting, and fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up two or three Gulps, the fore-runners of a Vomit drivelled out theſe words, <hi>I am much concerned for the loſs of my two Ships.</hi> Immediately the Paraſites renewed their Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries, and Romancing without meaſure, one of them replyed, <hi>That that loſs redounded to his Honour, that it fell out as could have been wiſhed, and nothing could have happened more opportunely, ſince it adminiſtred an opportunity of falling out with his Neighbours, from whom he might take Two Hundred in lieu of theſe two, which might eaſily be compaſſed.</hi> To prove this, the, falſe Flatterer produced many examples. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid, <hi>That loſs was the greateſt teſtimony of his Grandeur, for only he was a great Prince who had much to loſe, that loſing was a better demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Power, than gaining and acquiring, which were the Practice of Pyrates and Robbers. That damage ſuſtained,</hi> he added, <hi>would be the enriching of him;</hi> and then began to fill his Ears with ſentences out of <hi>Tacitus, Saluſt, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libius, Thucidides,</hi> and other Authors; repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſencing the vaſt loſſes of the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and a Thouſand other extravagancies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The mighty Glutton who only ſtuddied how to excuſe his ſloath, took theſe falſhoods as full ſatisfaction for his loſs. The Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf could not have contrived a better way to infatuate him. At this time the crudity of his Stomach for want of digeſtion caſt up a Belch,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98488:21"/>which made the room to Eccho No ſooner had the Curſed Paraſites heard it, than kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to make him believe he had ſneez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they unanimouſly ſaid, <hi>God bleſs you.</hi> That very minute began the Hour, and the great Man raving as if exagicated by furies cryed out, <hi>Villains, ſince you would impoſe upon me ſo far as to make a Belch paſs for a Sneeze, tho my Mouth and my Noſe are ſo cloſe together, what can I expect you would do in thoſe things I neither ſee nor ſmell.</hi> Then ſhaking his Hands about his Ears as if he were driving away their Lyes, he ran at them and kick'd them out of the Palace, ſaying. <hi>Had theſe Fellows come upon me when I had a Cold, they had utterly undone me; one ſenſe that was left me proved their ruin, their is no greater happineſs than Smelling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Cheats.</note>The Miſers warned by coſtly experience ſeparated themſelves from the Cheats, and theſe rather than loſe their Trade attacked one another, diſguiſing their Words and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting Plain Dealing. Says one Cheat to another, <hi>Sir, having paid dear for dealing with Sharpers who have been my ruin, I come to you who are no ſtranger to my Honeſty, to deſire you will lend me</hi> 3000 <hi>Royals</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">There are ſuch quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities of Coper-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in <hi>Spain,</hi> that great Sums are often paid in it, and great Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration is allowed for Payments in Gold or Silver.</note>
               <hi>in Braſs, upon a Bill which is accepted and payable in Silver within two Months; the party the Bill is drawn upon is ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſible, the Money is as good as if you had it in your Pocket, and you will have no further trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than telling of it.</hi> But the Man upon whom he gave the Bill was the very ſink of Fraud and Deceit. The Sharper who hear'd the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sharper commending the Third, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98488:22"/>not to be acquainted with the qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of either, and arming himſelf with his own Weapons, with a doleful deliberation anſwered, <hi>That he was juſt then come abroad to borrow</hi> 4000 <hi>Royals upon A Pawn that was worth Eight.</hi> They all accoſted one another with gilt Chains that were to paſt for Gold, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Bills that were accepted, ſham Securi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, falſe Notes, Plate they had borrowed for a Feaſt, and bits of Glaſs and
<hi>Bristol</hi> ſtones under the title of <hi>Diamonds.</hi> It was wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to hear the diſcourſe that paſſed betwixt them. One ſaid, <hi>Honesty is the beſt Policy, and plain dealing is a Jewel. I had rather die in a Ditch than do a baſe thing. I stand upon my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, 'tis a great bleſſing to be afraid to ſhow ones Face; this has been my Education from my Cradle.</hi> Another of the Cheats anſwered. <hi>There is nothing like keeping touch, an honest Man's Word is as good as his Bond, I never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired ill-gotten Riches, I will have nothing that way require reſtitution, my Soul is more precious to me than all the World, I would not be guilty of one Cheat for all the Riches in the Earthy, I value my conſcience above all the Univerſe contains.</hi> Thus were theſe Diſſemblers diſguiſing their fly deſigns with fair Speeches, when the Hour came upon them, and every Sharper believing his companion, they all ruined one another. He that had the falſe Chain gave it for the counterfeit Bill, he that ſhowed the Glaſs Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amonds exchanged them for the borrowed Plate. The Three ran to the Goldſmith, the other with his Bill to the Banker to compound
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98488:22"/>for half in ready Money before the Cheat of the Chain was diſcovered. The Banker told him the Bill was not his, neither did he know any ſuch Man, and ſeat him away with a Flea in his Ear. Away ſlunk the Sharper with-his Bill inſtead of his Tail betwixt bis Legs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>O Dog, what a trick had he ſerved me, but that the Chain was made of old Iron.</hi> He that parted with the falſe Diamonds for die Place being at the Goldſmith's ſelling it for leſt than the weights, rejoyced to think how he had bubbled the other with bits of Glaſs. In comes the right Owner, and ſeeing his Plate ſwing in the Scale calls an Alguazil and ſeizes the Cheat for a Thief, and they fell together by the Ears. At the noiſe out runs he with the falſe Diamonds: He that was ſelling die Plate cryed out, <hi>That Rogue ſold it to me;</hi> The other anſwered, <hi>He lyes, he ſtole it from me.</hi> The Goldſmith cryed,
<hi>That Scoundrel would have ſold me pebbles for Diamonds.</hi> The owner of the Plate was for ſeizing them both; The Scribe was for ſecuring all three till the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were decided. The Alguazil ſeized the two Cheats, and the Scribe led the owner of the Plate by the Cloak; after the Rogues had well buffeted one another, and thus well-atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Mob, they were led to Goal, and there put into cuſtody of the Hangman's Maſter of the Wardrobe.</p>
            <p>There is a ſmall Iſland on the Coaſt of <hi>Denmark,</hi> in which there are Five Towns. The Lord of this place was very poor, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becauſe he coveted much, than that he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98488:23"/>wanted for any thing. God had afflicted the Inhabitants with a general inclination in them all to be Projectors, ſo that the Land ſeem'd to be infeſted with as many Monſters as there were Men. All the Neighbouring People ſhunn'd theſe Iſlanders as they would the Plague, for the very Air that came from them was ſo contagious, it conſum'd their Stocks, blaſted their Fields, waſted their Treaſure, and ruin'd their Trade. So prodigious was the natural Proneneſs to Projecting in that Country, that the very ſucking Babes inſtead of <hi>Daddy</hi> and <hi>Mammy,</hi> cryed nothing but <hi>Project.</hi> The whole Iſland was a confuſed Chaos, for Man and Wiſe, Father and Son, Neighbour and Neighbour, were ever jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and bawling about their Projects, and they were as intoxicated with them as if they had been drunk with Wine. The Lord of this place, (Avarice, which is one of the worſt Devils that diſtract the World, having gain'd the aſcendant over him) ordered a general gathering of Projects. Legions of Projectors aſſembled before his Palace, with Skrips and Scroles of Paper ſtuck in their Girdles, run through their Button Holes, and peeping out of their Pockets. The Lord having made known his Wants, demanded their Aſſiſtance, and they all at once laying hold of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, and crowding till they had almoſt ſtifled one another, in an inſtant heaped up four Tables with their Memoirs. The hurry be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomewhat over, he began to look over them. The firſt Paper he opened was En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98488:23"/>to this effect: <hi>A Project for getting an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite quantity of Silver and Gold, without ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or taking it from any body.</hi> A difficult propoſition in my mind, ſays the Lord. The ſecond: <hi>How to gather unmeaſurable Treaſure by taking what they have, from all Men, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching them by taking it away.</hi> The firſt part, quoth the Lord, of taking from all Men, I like; put as to the ſecond, which is to enrich them by taking it from them, I am dubious, yet let them look to that. The third: <hi>An eaſie, pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and juſt Project for amaſſing of many Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, in ſuch manner, that they who are to pay them ſhall not miſs them, but rather ſhall think they are beſtowed on them.</hi> This I approve of, leaving the perſuaſive part to the Projector. The fourth Project undertakes to make what is deficient to ſuperabound without adding any thing, or taking away, and without giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Body cauſe of Complaint. A Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſo inoffenſive can have nothing of truth in it. The fifth, which offers to furniſh all that ſhall be deſired, directs to take by fair and foul Means, and to ask of all Men, and they will give themſelves to the Devil. This Project having to do with the Devil, ſeem'd practicable. The Author encouraged by this Approbation, added: <hi>And I propoſe, that thoſe who levy it, ſhall be a comfort to them that ſuffer by it.</hi> The Devil put it into his Head to let ſlip that Word, Furies poſſeſs the Projectors, who thunder out Reproaches againſt him, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him, <hi>Sot</hi> and <hi>Dog,</hi> and crying,
<hi>Thou Scoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drel, Hell it ſelf could never have propoſed a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98488:24"/>fort in Tax-gatherers, they themſelves being the greateſt of Grievances.</hi> They call'd one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sons of Projectors,</hi> as it had been <hi>Sons of Whores,</hi> condemning one anothers Propoſals, and each approving only of his own. In the height of this Fray, many of the Lords Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants came running, and crying the Palace was a-fire in three ſeveral places, and the Wind blew high. Juſt then began the Hour, the Smoke was great, and the Flame aſcended. The Lord in that Conſternation knew not which way to turn himſelf. The Projectors bid him ſit ſtill, and they would ſet all to rights in a moment; and ruſhing out from his preſence, ſome laid Hands on all they found in the Houſe, caſting the Cabinets, Tables, Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and all that was of value, out at the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows; others with Sledges overthrew a Tower; others ſaying; the Fire would ceaſe as ſoon as it had vent, uncovered a great part of the Houſe, breaking down the Rooſs, and deſtroying all that ſtood in their way. None of them, went about to quench the Fire, but all were employed in pulling down the Houſe, and confounding all that was in it. The Lord ſeeing the Smoke decreaſe, went out, and found, that the Common People with his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Servants had overcome the Fire, yet at the ſame time perceiv'd the Projectors were tearing up the very Foundations, had demoliſh'd his Palace, and ſpoil'd all his Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture: Incenſed and raging at this hideous ſight, he cryed out,
<hi>Dogs, you are worſe than the Fire, and ſuch art all your Projects, it were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98488:24"/>better I had been burnt, than to have given ear to you, ſo deſtructive are all the Remedies you apply. You overturn a whole Heuſe for fear a Corner of it ſhould fall, and throw the beſt Goods into the Street pretending to ſave them. You feed a Prince with his own Limbs, and pretend to maintain him, when at the ſame time he is devouring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. If the Head devours its whole Body, it will remain a Cancer and not a Man. Villains, juſtly did the Fire come to burn me for gathering and ſuffering you to live, but when it perceiv'd me in the power of Projectors it ceaſed, concluding I was already conſumed. Fire is the moſt Merciful of Projectors for Water quenches it, but you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cteaſe in ſpight of all the Elements. Antichriſt will be a Projector, and ſhall burn you all alive, and keep your Aſhes to make Lye to waſh out the Stains of all Commonwealths. Princes may be Poor, but when once they have to do with Projectors, they ceaſe to be Princes to avoid being Poor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Bauds and Jiles.</note>The Bauds and Whores had gathered a wicked Councel, where they railed at the Purſes they could not come at, and ſpoke ill of Money that was out of their reach. The ancienteſt of the Baudes, mumbling her Words betwixt her Gums with a hollow Tone, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from, the want of Teeth, grunted out theſe Words to the Aſſembly; <hi>The World is now at the laſt gaſp, it is a ſtarving Age, things are at the worſt, Fairings and New-years<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifts are long ſince out of date, Love-Offerings are ſearce remembred, Money is come to that paſs no body knows it, and it is vaniſh'd from our ſight, a Grown Piece is ſhewn about as if it were an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98488:25"/>and Guinea's are Stiled of Bleſſed Memory Promiſes have ſucceeded in the place of ready Coin. A Compliment, with, You may rely upon my Word; is the common Stop-gap, and an empty Note paſſes for current Caſh. Your Spruce Beaus with Buſhy Wigs and long Sword-knots, will reduce you to a Morſel of Bread. Our buſineſs is to have and to hold, to ſeize the ready <hi>Rino,</hi> and to be payed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand, I recommend to you certain Men that are half rotten, that live in the ſpace betwixt Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and the Grave, that trim up a walking Ske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton, and lay up for no Heir bat their Luxury; paying well for the weakneſs of their Limbs. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt takes away all ſqueamiſhneſs, ſhut your Eyes, and ſtop your Noſes, as if you were ſwallowing a Purge; a Bitter Draught <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſometimes a whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Medicine. Make account that you burn old Lace for the Silver, or ſuck a Bone to get out the Marrow. I have half a dozen of dry old Dotards. who ſpit Pieces of Eight for every one of you. I do not deſire a third, but ſhall be ſatisfied with ſome ſmall Allowance to keep up that Reputation I have preſerved all my Life.</hi> She ſaid, and cloſing her Chin with the tip of her Noſe, made a Face like a Nutcracker. One of the young Harpies replied; <hi>Thou Antiquated Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triver of Delight, Coupler of Male and Female, Tacker of Nations, Joyner of Giblets; and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiter of Faces, conſider we are too young to be ſold to impotent Curmudgeons, make uſe of your Rhetorick among the decayed Governants, who are but Walking Carcaſſes playing about the Grave, at Butterflies do about a Candle, till they drop into it. Young Blood is more inclined to the Fleſh than to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98488:25"/>Money, and prefers pleaſure before Riches, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let me adviſe you to chooſe ſome other Trade, for Quality bos now taken up that of Bawding, and I hope to ſee rotten Eggs thrown at their Coaches inſtead of the Pillory.</hi> Scarce had the Night-walker ſpoke the laſt Word when the Hour began, and a whole Shoal of Creditors ruſhing in fell upon them. The Landlord ſeized the Beds and Hangings for Houſe Rent, the Upholſterer their Cloaths for the Hire of his Goods, till both with a hideous Noiſe ſell ſoul of each other. At the ſame time a Broker puts in for his Cloaths, The Wenches they Shreiked, calling them, Rude unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly Fellows, threatning what they would do, and ſwearing they would never put up ſuch an Affront. The damn'd old Baud bleſs'd her ſelf with both Hands, and roared as high as the loudeſt. In comes a Bully to one of the Jilts, and without asking Queſtions draws his Sword, and falls upon the Credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, calling them Thieves and Robbers. They drew, and in the Fray overturn'd and broke all the Goods in the Room. The Wenches ran to the Windows, crying, <hi>Help, Help, Murder, Murder.</hi> At this Summons up comes an <hi>Alguazil</hi> with all his Retinue, bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them keep the Kings Peace. The Broil grew hotteſt upon the Stairs, till out they ruſht into the Street, ſome Wounded, others with their Cloaths rent. The Ruffian with a broken Head, but without Hat or Cloak, took ſanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary in a Church. The <hi>Alguazil</hi> entred the Houſe, and ſeeing the old Woman, laid vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98488:26"/>Hands on her, ſaying, <hi>Art thou here ſtill, old</hi> Beelzebub,
<hi>after having been thrice baniſh'd? Thou art the Ringleader of all this Miſchief.</hi> Then ſeizing her with the young Fry, and ſecuring all they had, he drove them away half Naked, with their Hair about their Ears, to Goal, all the Rabble attending and ſhout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Away with the Whores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer.</note>A Councellor at Law whoſe greateſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lay in his grizly Beard, like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Strength in his Hair, ſate in a Room better furniſh'd with Books than he was with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. His whole Study was how to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broil his Clients, not to conſult his Authors, and yet was ſo proud of his Library, that being a meer
<hi>Ignoramus,</hi> it might truly be ſaid, he knew not the value of it. He had gain'd a great Reputation by his Roaring Voice, his moving Geſtures, and a wonderful fluency of Tongue, wherewith he bore down all other Lawyers. His Chamber could ſcarce contain his Clients, every one preſſing for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to lay his Caſe open, and empty his Purſe. All his Anſwers were: <hi>I am fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formd. I have Studied the Caſe. Your Right is undeniable. It agrees with the expreſs Letter of the Law, It is as clear as the day. There is no difficulty in this Suit. It is a Caſe adjuged. The Law is directly on your ſide. It will eaſily be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termin'd. The Judges are for us. Your Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary has nothing to ſay for himſelf. All that has been done is void in it ſelf. That judgment muſt be Reverſed. Be Ruled by me.</hi> Some he order'd to Petition, others to Appeal, others
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98488:26"/>to Demur, others to put in their Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, others to bring their Writ of Error, and others to Suborn freſh Witneſſes. All that immenſe number of Volumes was turn'd over, and nothing reſounded but an unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligible confuſion of Law Gibberiſh. The Councellor demanded his Fee, the Sollicitor His due, the Attorney his Reward, the Clerk his Perquiſites, and the Scrivener his Pay. Whilſt they were in this Debate the Hour began, and the Clients unanimouſly, as if it had been one Man, cried out; <hi>Good, Mr. Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant, in all Suits the Adverſary is the leaſt of Evils, for he Sues at his own Coſt, and you Plead for us at our own, and you, the Sollicitor, the Clerk, and the Attorney, run away with our Money. The Adverſary waits for Judgment, and purſues upon an Appeal, but you and your Adherents give a definitive Sentence in your own behalf. Our Suit may go for and againſt us, but in the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it we muſt of neceſſity be caſt four times a day, ſo that in the end we may obtain our Right, but have loſt our Money. All thoſe Authors can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not perſwade us, but it is a madneſs to ſpend what we have, to get what another Man has, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be at laſt diſappointed. We had rather have one Adverſary than five, for ſuppoſing the Suit ſhould go on our ſide, it will be when it has ruin'd us. Lawyers defend their Clients, as Seamen do their Ships in a Storm; throwing over all they have, that if it be Gods will they may be brought into their Port empty. The beſt Advice is to agree amongſt car ſelves, for by agreeing we ſhall ſave what you take from us. We are all going to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98488:27"/>pound with our Adverſaries. Your beſt Revenues ariſe out of our Obſtinacy, and if we by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding ſhould loſe all we ſued for, at leaſt we ſhall gain all that you loſe. We would adviſe you to put a Bill upon your Door, for we think it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to ſpend our Money upon Whores than Lawyers; and for your part, ſince your only Buſineſs has been to ſet Men together by the Ears, it will be your beſt courſe to turn Soldiers or Stateſmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Vint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note>The Vintners, a perverſe Generation, who raiſe the Price of their Wine, at the ſame rate that they Brew, Water and Debaſe it, ſelling the Rain diſguiſed and diſcoloured with Sloes, and the Dregs of their Hogſheads, for the Juice of the Grape, were met in a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern to the number of 6 or 7, with as many Bullies and Highwaymen, and a <hi>Quorum</hi> of Draggle-Tail Jilts newly whipt out of <hi>Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well,</hi> who Danced themſelves Dry, and Drank to Dance again. The Bumpers flew about like Lightning, to the Tune of Three in a Hand. <hi>Delicate Wine,</hi> quoth one of the Sparks, perceiving the Cheat, and winking upon the Knave that was to Pledge him. The other, who feared it would breed Frogs in his Belly, rather than fend Fumes into his Brain, replied, <hi>This is truly a Rich Wine, and we Poor Rogues, for the Waters belong to the Rich and not to the Poor.</hi> The Vintner hearing their Flouts, call'd them Sots, bidding them Drink and hold their Peace. <hi>Drink and Swim you ſhould have ſaid,</hi> replied one of the good Fellows. This minute began the Hour, and the whole Company growing Mutinous, threw
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:98488:27"/>the Pots and Glaſſes at the Vintner, crying, <hi>Inhuman Water-ſeller, we are more like Drown'd Rats than Drunkards, thou makeſt us pay by the Quart for the River Water thou bringeſt in by the Hogſhead, and would put the Fox upon us when thou haſt made meer Geeſe of us. We ſhould wear Jack-boots to drink in your Houſe, that we might keep the Water from our Legs.</hi> The Vintner having nothing to ſay for himſelf, cryed, <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Water,</hi> as if his Houſe had been a-fire, and rouling his Hogſheads into the Street, knock'd out the Heads of them, letting the Liquor run down the Channel.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pretenders to an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment.</note>A Swarm of 32 Candidates, all aiming at one Employment, were waiting to ſpeak witn the Nobleman in whoſe Gift it was. Each of them fancied himſelf as deſerving, as the reſt unworthy of it. Every one bleſs'd himſelf and admir'd at the Madneſs and Impudence of the reſt, for pretending to what he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd to be due to him alone. They beheld one another with Evil Eyes, and Hearts full of Malice, and Meditated how to Slander and Defame. Their Looks were Sower and Starch't, but their Joints in continual Motion. Every time the Door creak'd they made a thouſand Bows on all Hands, and as many Submiſſive Grimaces. Not ſo much as a Page could paſs by without a Loving Salute and kind Look. The Secretary happening to ruſh through the Room, their Submiſſions were ſo profound, as if they would have kiſs'd the Ground he trod on. He caſting a Glance like a Shame-faced Girl, preſs'd through,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:98488:28"/>ſaying, <hi>Excuſe me, Gentlemen, I am now in haſte.</hi> The Nobleman call'd for his Desk, and ſate to Diſpatch Buſineſs, when upon a falſe alarm thinking themſelves ſummon'd to appear, one of the Candidates cries, <hi>It is I,</hi> another, <hi>I come,</hi> and others, <hi>Here I am,</hi> crouding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to death againſt the Door. The poor Lord underſtanding what a Peal of Petitions attended him, knew not which way to turn himſelf. He ſilently curſed himſelf, ſaying, <hi>It was one of the greateſt Bleſſings in the World to have to give, provided there were none to ask; and that Favours, that they might not be a plague to him that beſtows them, ought to be freely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, and never ſued for.</hi> The Dunners im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of delay, waſted inwardly, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there was but one Employment, and the Candidates were many. They Calculated the Account Arithmetically, dividing one betwixt 32, and then ſays they, <hi>What comes to every Mans ſhare?</hi> Then would they have ſubſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 32 from one, but that could not be, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every Man ſuppoſed himſelf that one, and applied, it cannot be to all the reſt. The Lord conſidered, he could pleaſe but one, and muſt diſoblige 31, however to be rid of them, he reſolved they ſhould be admitted, and in order to it put on a ſtern Countenance, and looked like a Statue, that he might appear with more Majeſty. In they ruſhed in a Croud, and he perceiving they would all Tongue-pad him at once, ſaid; <hi>There is but one Employment, and you are a Number, I would gladly beſtow the place upon one, and ſtisfie you
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98488:28"/>all,</hi> As he had dropt the laſt Word the Hour commenced, and the Lord beſtowing the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment upon one, entailed the Reverſion of it upon them all one after another, World without end. The wretched Preſumptive Heirs, began to wiſh one another dead, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Pluriſies, Aſthma's, Conſumptions, Plagues, Apoplexes, Fluxes, ſudden Deaths, and all manner of Diſaſters. Scarce Were two Minutes paſt ſince the Entail, when every Man thought his Predeceſſor had liv'd to the Age of <hi>Methuſalem;</hi> and though the, Tenth Man computed his turn could not come till 500 years after, yet every Man was pleaſed to wait the death of his Predeceſſor. Only the 31th finding by his reckoning that his turn fell out exactly with the end of the World, and after the coming of Antichriſt, ſaid; <hi>My Poſſeſſion and the general Conflagration hit exactly together, I ſhall make a fine Buſineſs of my Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; when I am burnt the day of Judgment, who will oblige the Dead to pay me my Wages? For my part, I wiſh the 30th Succeſſor a long Life, for when the Employment comes to him, the World will be at the laſt gaſp.</hi> The Lord left them ſtriving to outlive and deſtroy one another, and went himſelf away in a paſſion to ſee them protracting their Ages beyond Doomſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, and even coping with Eternity. He that had carried the Employment ſtood amazed to conſider what a long ſucceſſion of Heirs he had got, and at laſt ſlunk away, reſolving to eat light Suppers, and prevent taking Cold. The reſt looked upon one another as ſo many
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98488:29"/>mutual Plagues, and reciprocally curſing their Lives, each fancied Diſeaſes in the other, and added to the number of his years, every Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor threatning his Forerunner with Death, giving him over as a gone Man, and wiſhing him in the Hands of Phyſicians; which is the ſame as to be delivered up to the Hangman.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Mumpers that bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, never to pay.</note>A ſort of Men that borrow after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the day that is paſt, never to return again, who ſnap at a Purſe as a Spider does at a Fly that's entangled in her Web, lie tumbling in Bed till the Evening for want of Rags to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Nakedneſs. Among them they had laid out Half a Crown they had Mumped, in Wafers, Ink, Pens and Paper, all which they had conſumed in begging Letters all to the ſame effect, expreſſing how urgent the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion was, their Reputation lying at ſtake, and even their Life, with Aſſurances of a ſpeedy Return, and Profeſſions of Eternal Acknowledgment. However in caſe they ſhould not meet with Money, they concluded with the <hi>Ne plus Ultra</hi> of impudent Beggary, deſiring in caſe there was no ready Caſh, they would be pleaſed to ſend them ſomething of value to pawn, which ſhould be moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſecured. By way of Poſtſcript they begged Pardon for the Boldneſs, proteſting they would not be ſo free with any other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. They had drawn about an Hundred of theſe Notes to be diſperſed in all the Corners of the Town, whither they were conveyed by one of the Fraternity, a notable Spunger that had a Tongue well hung, and with his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:98488:29"/>grave Beard and long Cloak not a little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled a well travelled Mountebank. The Herd of Letter Beggars remained computing how much Money the Meſſenger would bring, and a curſed noiſe there was about the Sum. Nor did it ſtop here, for they wrangled about the laying it out, and having given one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Lye, at laſt they leaped out of their Beds, with ſuch Fragments of Shirts that there was no occaſion to take them up to diſcover their Lower Parts. In came their Mumping Poſt with an Air that ſpoke no Relief; both his Hands were at liberty, and his Arms open, which foreboded Emptineſs. All that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared was a great Bundle of Notes. They all ſtood amazed, ſeeing their Contrivance had ended in empty Anſwers, and in a dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Tone ſaid, <hi>What have we got? No Money,</hi> (replied the poor Scoundrel)
<hi>you may divert your ſelves with Reading, ſince you have no occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Telling.</hi> They began to open the Notes. The firſt was to this Effect; <hi>I was never ſo much concerned at any thing in all my Life, as my not being at preſent in a condition to ſerve you in a matter of ſo little value. He might have ſerved me</hi> (quoth the Reader) <hi>and have had more cauſe to be concerned.</hi> The Second Note; <hi>Sir, had I received yours yeſterday, I could have obliged you, and been proud of the Occaſion. A Curſe of yeſterday,</hi> (ſays he)
<hi>that is the daily Plague of all Mumpers.</hi> The Third Note; <hi>It is ſuch a miſerable time. O Damned Almanack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker,</hi> (cries the Shark) <hi>we ask for Money, and you tell us what Weather it is.</hi> The Fourth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98488:30"/>Note; <hi>Sir, your want cannot be ſo grievons to you, as to me it is that I cannot relieve you. Who the Devil told you ſo</hi> (exclaims the poor Wretch) <hi>doſt thou pretend to Divination thou Miſer, and Propheſy when you ought to give. No more read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (they all cried) and making a Helliſh Charm they added; <hi>It is now night, to make up what has been expended let us gnaw the Wafers of the Letters for our Supper, and ſell theſe and two other Parcels of Notes we have by us to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectioner, who will give at leaſt four Royals for them to Paper up Comfits, wrap Sugar, and lay under Biſcuits in the Oven.</hi> Says the Letter-Carrier, <hi>This Trade of Borrowing has been out of the World theſe ten years. A Man had better give what he asks, than endure the Geſtures and Scurvy Looks of thoſe he Accoſts; and if you cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate the whole, the Expence of Paper and Shooes is greater than the Profit, your only way is to look cut ſharp.</hi> In this poſture were the Paper-Mumpers when the Hour began, and the ligh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt of Equipage ſaid; <hi>We are very Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious with other Mens Money, and if we expect it ſhould fly in at our Windows we may die in a Ditch. Rhetorick is no good Picklock, and fine Words reach the Ears, but not the Pockets, to liſten to one that begs is the Devil. It is much eaſier to take than to ask. When all Men board, it is no time to wait their generoſity. Our buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is to ſteal bare-faced, and with conſideration, that is, conſidering we muſt ſteal in ſuch manner, that there may be enough for the Accuſer, for the Glerk; for the Conſtable, for the Attorney, for the Sollicitor, for the Councellor, for the Jaylor, for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98488:30"/>the Judge, and for our ſelves, for when what is ſtolen ends, the Hangman begins. My Friends, if they baniſh us, it is better than that they ſhould bury us; if they Pillory us, it breaks no Bones, and as for the ſhame of it, none of our Spectators have any; if they whip us, we may be content, for Beggars muſt not be Chooſers, and at leaſt we ſhall have the ſatisfaction of hearing our white Skins com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, and as ſoon as the ſhew is over, the Doublet bides the Laſhes. If they put us upon the Rack we are in no danger, for all they endeavour is to make us ſpeak the truth, which we never do, therefore let us be like the Taylors, and we are ſafe enough, To be ſent to the Galleys is only going into the Kings Service with a</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley Slaves have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways their Heads Shav'd.</note> 
               <hi>bald Pate, and Galley Slaves ſerve only to ſupply the want of Sails. If they ſhall Hang us, Which is the utmoſt extremity, that day twelve-month Will be a year, and every Man that is Hanged honours his Parents, for tho he be never ſo mean a Scoundrel, the Blockheads of the Spectators ſay,</hi> He is very well born, and of a good Family. <hi>Nay, if it were only for the pleaſure of chouſing the Doctor and Apothecary at ones death, a Man might be well enough pleaſed to dye of the Hempen Diſeaſe. Gentlemen, mind your Hits.</hi> Scarce were the laſt Words out of his Mouth, when wrapping the Sheets about them, and ſwallawing the Oil that was in a Lamp, they let themſelves out of the Window with a Blanket into the Street, and away they all ſcoured to ſearch Cheſts, Pick Locks, and Dive into Pockets.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ruffians and phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</note>Two Ruffians were brought to the Gallows for half a dozen Murders. One of them had
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98488:31"/>already taken his ſwing, and the other was mounted on the Ladder with the Hangman aſtride over his Shoulders. Among the Croud of Spectators two Phyſicians riding after Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers and Plagues, made a halt, and behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Criminals began to weep like Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with ſuch a Deluge of Tears, that the People about them asked, <hi>Whether thoſe that ſuffered were their Sons.</hi> They anſwered, <hi>They did not know them, but wept to ſee Men dye with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paying any thing to the Faculty.</hi> That mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment began the Hour, and the Criminal ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Doctors ſaid, <hi>Gentlemen of the Faculty, here is room for you if you pleaſe, for you have killed enough to deſerve my place, and your skill in diſpatching Men renders you worthy of the Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's.</hi> Galen <hi>and</hi> Hippocrates <hi>muſt not ſend all to the Grave, Hemp is as effectual as an Aphoriſm. Thoſe Mules that carry you about to commit ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Murders, are no better than Ladders to mount you to the Gallows. This is a time to ſpeak truth, had I uſed the</hi> Recipe <hi>inſtead of the Dagger, I had not come to this end, tho I had maſſacred all the Spect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ors. I beg a dozen Maſſes for my Soul, which you may eaſily foiſt into one of the Wills you forward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A lean ragged Chymiſt,<note place="margin">The Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</note> who looked as if he had extracted the Juice out of his Fleſh, and calcined his Cloaths, had wheedled a Miſer to give Ear to him, as he ſtood at a Fellow's Door that ſold Charcoal, and was telling him, <hi>I am a Natural Philoſopher, and by the Grace of God a Chymiſt. I have found the Philoſophers Stone, which is a Medicine of Life,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:98488:31"/>and produces a tranſcendent Tranſmutation infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely multiplicable; for with the Powder of this Stone by Projection, I turn into the pureſt and moſt refined Gold Quicqſilver, Iron, Lead, Tin, and Silver. I can make Gold of Graſs, Egg-ſhels, Hair, Blood, Piſs, and of the very Dirt. This I can do in a few days, and with ſmall Expence. I dare not diſcover my ſelf to any body, becauſe, if the King ſhould hear of it, he would clap me into Gaol to ſave</hi> India <hi>Voyages, and the trouble of digging in the Mines. I know you to be a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Diſcretion, Quality and Worth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have reſolved to truſt you with a Secret of ſuch importance and ſo admirable, that in a few days it will make you Maſter of many Millions.</hi> The Miſer liſtned to him with a greedy Ear, and ſo wrapt in Contemplation of the Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions, that his Fingers wagged for eagerneſs of telling them. His Avarice could not contain it ſelf within bounds, but guſht out at his Eyes, and he had in his imagination already converted his Frying-Pans, Spits, Kettles, and Candleſticks into Bars of Gold. He asked, what would be the Charge of the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration; The Chymiſt replied, <hi>Little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for</hi> 50
<hi>Crowns was enough to convert all the World into Gold and Silver, becauſe the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Expence would be in Lymbecks and Crucibles, for the Elixir, which is the vivifying Spirit of Gold, would coſt nothing, and might be had gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis every where; neither ſhould a Farthing be ſpent in Charcoal, becauſe he ſublimated, digeſted, ſeparated, rectified, and circulated all with Lime, and Dung.</hi> The Coal man was, liſtning to this
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98488:32"/>Tale of a Tub, fretting to hear him ſay he would uſe no Charcoal, but juſt then began the Hour, and the Coal-man well powder'd with Charcoal Duſt, and ſmelling of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils Perfume, falls upon the Chymiſt, ſaying, <hi>Thou Vagabond, Scoundrel, Raſcal, why doſt thou feed up that honeſt Man with imaginary Gold?</hi> The Chymiſt in a fury gave him the Lye, which the Coalman ſo readily anſwer'd with a Cuff, it was ſcarce diſcernible which was firſt. They both fell to Loggerheads, and in a trice, the Chymiſt's batter'd. Noſe ran like a Lymbeck. The Miſer could not part them, not daring to meddle becauſe of the Duſt and Smoot. They ſtuck ſo cloſe to one another, it was impoſſible to diſcern which was the Coalman, or who had ſmooted the other. At length they were parted by the People that paſſed by, but in ſuch a condition, they look'd as if they had been rowl'd in Lamblack, and trimm'd with Snuffs of Candles. Says the Charcoal-man, <hi>This poor Devil tells thee he'l make Gold of Dirt and old Iron, and at the ſame time his Cloaths are all in tatters, and he looks as if he had been robbing the Rag-woman. I know theſe Fellows, for one of them cheated a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of mine, and made him lay out at my own Houſe at leaſt a thouſand Crowns in Coals only, and that in the ſpace of two months, telling him he would make Gold, and he only made Smoak and Aſhes, but at laſt ran away with all he had. But I</hi> (quoth the Chymiſt) <hi>will perform what I undertake, and ſince you make Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Coals, and of the Stones, Dirt and Rubbiſh
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:98488:32"/>you throw among them, and of the Cheats of your Weight, why may not I with my Art, and the Aſſiſtance of</hi> Rualdus, Geber, Avicen, Morie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Hermes, Vulſtadius, Crolius, Libavius, <hi>and</hi> Hermes<hi>'s</hi> Smaragdine <hi>Table, make Gold as well as you.</hi> The Charcoal-man in a Fume replied, <hi>Becauſe all thoſe Authors make you mad, and you make him that believes you a Beggar. I ſell Coals, and you burn them, which is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon I convert them into Gold and Silver, and you turn them into Soot. The true Philoſopher's Stone is to buy cheap and ſell dear, and a Pox on all your Catalogue of hard Names. I declare, I would with more ſatisfaction freely give my Coals to burn you with all your Papers, than ſell them for ready Money. As for you, Sir, you make account, that this day you became Maſter of your Money, and if you deſire to increaſe it, Trade is the only thing that multiplies Coin, and makes one Piſtol in a month produce another. But if you are weary of your Bags, empty them into a Houſe of Office, and whenſoever you repent you may take them out with more eaſe and cleanneſs, than ever you will recover them from the Bellows and Diſtillations of this miſerable Wretch, who being himſelf a meer Ragamuffian, pretends to out do, the Treaſures of</hi> India, <hi>and defie the Mines of</hi> Potoſi.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The French Pedlars, and Proud Spaniard.</note>Three <hi>Frenchmen</hi> were travelling into <hi>Spain</hi> over the mountains of <hi>Biſcay;</hi> one of them trundled before him a Wheel with the imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for grinding Knives and Sciſſers; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther carried before and behind two great far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of Bellows and Mouſtraps, and the third had a Box of Combs and Pins. A Poor <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:98488:33"/>who was travelling into <hi>France</hi> a Foot with his Cloak on his Shoulder, met them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout half way in the aſcent of a ſcraggy ſteep hill. They ſate down to reſt in the Shade and began to confer notes. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> being asked, <hi>whether he travelled,</hi> Anſwered, <hi>He was going to</hi> France, <hi>being fled from Juſtice for ſome unlucky pranks; that thence he would go into</hi> Flanders <hi>to appeaſe the Judges, and gain Honour in his Kings Service, becauſe a Spaniard out of his own Country could not ſerve any other Maſter.</hi> Being again asked, <hi>how it came he had no Trade or Handicraft to maintain him in that long Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</hi> He replied, <hi>The</hi> Spaniards <hi>had no Trade but War, that thoſe who were poor and honeſt bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed or begged by the way, and thoſe that were not ſo, Robbed, as they did in all other Countries.</hi> Moreover, he ſaid, <hi>He admired they travelled from</hi> France <hi>through ſtrange Countries and deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Mountains with their goods, being always in danger of falling into the hands of Highwaymen. He deſired they would inform him what moved them to leave their Country, and what profit they could propoſe to themſelves in that lumber they were loaded with, which at a diſtance made them look frightful, and put Travellers into a quandary to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine what they were.</hi> The Grinder who ſtammered the beſt
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> of the three, ſaid, <hi>We are Gentlemen diſguſted at the King of</hi> France, <hi>and have loſt our Fortunes by being Malecontents, but I have made three Journeys into</hi> Spain, <hi>where with this Wheel and theſe Stones I have gathered many</hi> Spaniſh
<hi>Pistols, which you call</hi> Doblones. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> with a ſour look
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:98488:33"/>replied, <hi>Much good may do the King of</hi> France <hi>with his faculty of curing the Evil, if he ſuffers Grinders and Pedlars to be Malecontents.</hi> Quoth the Grinder,
<hi>You ought to look upon us Grinders as a Land-Fleet, for with theſe Stones we ſharpers and wear away your bars of Gold more than your Knives and Sciſſers; take notice of this cracked pot that drivels out the Water; this ſerves us to convey home our Plate, without being expoſed to the Troubles of the Sea, and Dangers of Storms; theſe Wheels inſtead of Sails carry us into all parts, and being diſperſed through all Countreys with our Grind-ſtones, Combs and Pins, we gently draw after us the Revenues of your</hi> Indian <hi>Mines; and you may be aſſured it is no ſmall Treaſure that</hi> France <hi>catches in its Mouſe-traps, and ſucks in with its Bellows. Swoons</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Spaniard</hi>) <hi>tho I knew not all this, yet I could eaſily perceive your Bellows blew away our Money, and your Traps increaſed your Stock, but diminiſhed not our Mice; and I have obſerved, that ever ſince you ſell Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, we ſpend more Coals, and our Pots boil ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the better; that ſince you bring us Traps, we are devoured by Traps and Mice; that ſince you grind, all our Tools ruſt, wear, notch, and grow dull; and that in grinding our Knives you ſpoil them, that we may have occaſion to buy more of you. I am now convinced you</hi> Frenchmen <hi>are the Lice that devour all parts of</hi> Spain; <hi>that you bite us with the Teeth of your Combs, and grind us with your Stones; nor do I think that ſcratch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is any remedy againſt this itching, but that it increaſes it, and makes us tear onr ſelves to pieces with our own Fingers. I hope in God I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:98488:34"/>ſhall ſoon return, and then will make it known there is no remedy againſt this itch, but picking you out, and preſſing you to death. What ſhall I ſay of your Combs, but that they have made it faſhion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to be bald, by wearing all the Hair off of our Heads. I will make the <hi>Spaniards</hi> more chearly of their Mice, their Dandruff, and their Ruſt, that you may go to Hell to vend your Combs, Bellows, and Mouſtraps.</hi> At this moment be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the Hour, and the <hi>Spaniard</hi> foaming with Paſſion, ſaid, <hi>The Devil is at my Elbow, tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to Murder you all, and make theſe Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains as famous as formerly</hi> Ronceſvalles, <hi>for the overthrow of</hi> Charlemaign. The Pedlars ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him change Colour, and Rave, roſe up gabling amain, crying, <hi>Mon Dieu,</hi> and calling him <hi>Coquin.</hi> In an ill hour did they name it, for the <hi>Spaniard</hi> drawing his Dagger, and running at the Grinder, made him quit his Wheel, which receiving the Stroak, tumbled down the Rocks, and was beaten to ſhivers. Mean while the Trap Merchant threw a Pair of Bellows at him, but he falling on with his Dagger cut all the reſt, and clove the Traps. The Comb Pedler laying down his Box, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to throw Stones, the other two followed his Example. All three plied the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and he anſwered them all, there being ſuch plenty of that ſort of Ammunition in the place that they ſtumbled upon it. The <hi>Frenchmen</hi> kept their diſtance for fear of the Dagger. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> guarded himſelf with his Cloak, and giving a Kick to the Pin-Box, it tumbled down the Rocks, and flew open, ſtrewing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:98488:34"/>the Mountain with Pins and Combs; he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Merchandize confounded, cryed out; <hi>I have already begun to do my King good ſervice;</hi> and ſeeing ſome Paſſengers on Mules come up and part them, deſired they would give him a Certificate of the Victory he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained over the Vermin that infeſted <hi>Spain.</hi> The Paſſengers laught, underſtanding the cauſe of the Fray, and carrying away the <hi>Spaniard</hi> behind one of them, left the <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> buſie ſtopping the Holes in the Bellows, patching together the Mouſe-traps, mending the Wheel, and picking up the Pins that were ſcattered about the Clifts. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> being at a good diſtance, cryed out to them; <hi>If you were Malecontents in your own Country, ye Scoundrels, thank me for making you ſo in mine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Italy</hi> Dancing on the Rope, <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> watching to catch her if ſhe falls.</note> 
               <hi>Italy</hi> once the Miſtreſs of the World, and now only retaining the Memory of its former Grandeur, ſeeing its vaſt Monarchy cut out into ſo many Parcels, to enlarge the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſeveral Princes, and its Territories rent aſunder to patch up many ſcattered States, was now at length convinced how eaſie it was for others to take from her all that ſhe alone had with wonderful felicity taken from them all. Now therefore finding her ſelf poor, and extreamly light, as being eaſed of the Burden of many Provinces, ſhe reſolved to turn Rope-Dancer; and for want of Ground to walk upon, exerciſed her ſelf upon the Sreight Rope, to the aſtoniſhment of the whole World. She fixt the ends of her Rope, the one at <hi>Rome,</hi> and the other at <hi>Savoy. France</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:98488:35"/>
               <hi>Spain</hi> were the Spectators. The two Kings kept a watchful Eye upon her, obſerving to which ſide ſhe inclined as ſhe Danced, each ſtriving to be ready to catch her if ſhe fell. <hi>Italy</hi> perceiving what they aimed at, laid hold of the Republick of
<hi>Venice,</hi> and graſping it with both Hands as a Pole to poiſe her, leap'd and skipp'd at a wonderful rate; ſometimes making as if ſhe would fall to one ſide, and ſometimes to the other, diverting her ſelf with the eagerneſs of both Parties ſtretching out their Arms to catch her, and ſurprizing others with her Skill in recovering her ſelf, and deceiving them both. As they ſtood thus upon the catch, the Hour began, and the King of <hi>France</hi> ſeeing no probability of laying hold on her, began to looſen the end of the Rope which was ſix't in
<hi>Savoy,</hi> that ſhe might come tumbling towards him. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Monarch perceiving it, clapt in the State of <hi>Milan</hi> and Kingdoms of <hi>Naples</hi> and
<hi>Sicily</hi> as Supporters. <hi>Italy</hi> skipping in the Air, diſcovered that
<hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> which ſhe uſed as a Pole to poiſe, at the ſame time, crucified her, and therefore caſting it from her, and laying hold of the Rope, ſhe ſaid; <hi>So much for Rope-Dancing, for it is not for me to riſe high, when the Lookers on wiſh I may fall, and the Pole that ſhould poiſe crucifies me.</hi> Then ſuſpecting the ſupport of <hi>Savoy,</hi> ſhe betook her ſelf to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Since all are for ſeizing me, I'le take ſanctuary in the Church, where; if I chance to fall, I ſhall not want ſome body to abſolve me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:98488:35"/>
               <note place="margin">The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Naples,</hi> and Duke of
<hi>Oſuna</hi>
               </note>The <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Courſer, from whom ſome have ſtolen his Oats, and others drawn away his Hay, while ſome ſtrove to make of him a Geld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, others a Mare, and others a Poſt-Horſe, perceiving, that whilſt he was in the keeping of that incomparable Viceroy and invincible Captain General the Duke of <hi>Oſuna,</hi> he could cope with
<hi>Bucephalus,</hi> his Furniture, being compoſed of the Treaſures of <hi>Venice</hi> and
<hi>Brindiſi.</hi> That he had made him a Sea Horſe by his many glorious Naval Victories; that he had turned him to Graſs in <hi>Cyprus,</hi> and Water'd him at <hi>Tenedos,</hi> when he dragg'd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him the mighty Ship <hi>Sultana</hi> from <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonica,</hi> for which Action <hi>Neptune</hi> own'd him for his firſt begotten Son, brought forth in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to
<hi>Minerva.</hi> He remembred that Great Duke had ſhod him with the Turkiſh Half Moons, and that kicking up his Heels he had daſhed out the Teeth of the <hi>Venetian</hi> Lion at the prodigious Battle near <hi>Raguſa,</hi> where with only 15 Sail he defeated 80, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliging them ſhamefully to retire with the loſs of many Galleys and Galleaſſes, and of the beſt of their Men. Calling to mind theſe Triumphs, and conſidering he had not now ſo much as a Horſe-Cloth, but was gaul'd, and Snuffled becauſe they had thrown Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers into his Manger; and that he was now put to draw a Coach, having been once ſo Mettleſome, that die
<hi>Frenchmen,</hi> tho good Jockeys, could never ſit him; The Miſerable Condition he ſaw himſelf reduced to, drove him into a deſperate Melancholy, and that
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:98488:36"/>into raving Madneſs, ſo that Neighing fiercely, and Breathing Fire, he thought to have imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated the <hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe, and kicking and plunging to have overthrown the City. At the Noiſe, in came the Magiſtrates of <hi>Naples,</hi> who throwing one of their Gowns over his Head blinded him, then ſtroaking and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him fair, they put on his Collar and Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; but as they were tying him to a Ring in the Stable, the Hour began. Two of them that were fartheſt off ſaid; <hi>It was more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient and cheaper to give the Courſer at once to the Pope, than every year to ſend him a Nag with a Purſe, for by their Malicious Eyes it might be judged the Popes Nephews would ſome time over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look him.</hi> The others ſurprized at this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, anſwered; <hi>That the King of</hi> Spain <hi>had ſecured him againſt that Diſtemper, by placing three Caſtles on his Forehead as a Spell, and that they would ſooner cut off his Legs, than ſee him ſerve like a Mule under long black Trappings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling a Pall.</hi> The two firſt replied, <hi>They talked like Hereticks in refuſing to be Papiſts, and that no Saddle would fit the Courſer like that of St.</hi> Peter. The others in a Paſſion ſaid; <hi>That to prevent the Hereticks making the Pope looſe his Stirrups in that Saddle, it was convenient only the King of</hi> Spain <hi>ſhould mount the Horſe.</hi> Some were for the Mitre, others for the Crown, and Words paſſing, at laſt they came to Blows, ſo that a terrible Havock had been among them, but that the Elect of the People came in in the Godſpeed, and underſtanding the cauſe of the Quarrel ſaid; <hi>This Horſe, tho
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:98488:36"/>hard Mouthed, has had many Maſters, and for the moſt part has gone to them of his own accord, and not ſuffered himſelf to be led. It is requiſite he be carefully looked after, for there are in</hi> Italy <hi>many a-foot that look for Baggage Horſes, and Jockeys ready Booted and Spurred, and the old Horſe-ſtealer who catched him ſometimes before, and has now got a back Door to the Stable. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it convenient any</hi> French <hi>Groom ſhould Curry him, for they tickle and do not make him ſlick, and pray look to the Monſieurs who wear the Canonical Robes that they may have the better op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to throw their Leg over him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Czar of <hi>Moſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> conſults about raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Taxes.</note>The Great Czar of <hi>Moſcovy</hi> being exhauſted by the continual Inroads of the Tartars, and frequent Incroachments of the Turks, found himſelf neceſſitated to impoſe new Taxes upon his Subjects. To this effect he ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Favourites, Servants, Miniſters, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, and the Commons of his Court, and ſpoke to them to this effect; <hi>That they could not but be ſenſible of the great Expence he was at in maintaining an Army to protect them againſt the Malice of their Neighbouring Enemies; That no State could ſubſiſt without Taxes; That thoſe which were impoſed in preſſing Neceſſities were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways juſt, and muſt be accounted no burden, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing employed in the defence of thoſe that pay them, who purchaſe their Security, Lives, and Eſtates, with that ſmall Pittance, which in a moderate and well regulated Tax falls to every Mans ſhare to be disburſt; That he had aſſembled them to conſult their own conveniency, and therefore expected their Anſwer would be ſuitable to their Common Intereſt.</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:98488:37"/>The firſt that ſpoke were his Creatures and Miniſters, ſaying; <hi>The Propoſition was ſo good and juſt, it carried along with it its anſwer and conceſſion; That all was due to the ſupport of the Prince and Defence of the Country, and therefore he might contrive according to his pleaſure, to lay whatever Taxes he thought fit upon his Subjects, becauſe all that they payed was for their own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and Security; and conſequently the greater the Burdens he laid upon them, the more he would convince them of the confidence he repoſed in their Loyalty, and the greater would be their Honour.</hi> The Czar heard them with ſatisfaction, but not without ſome miſtruſt, and therefore or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Commons to anſwer for themſelves. They, whilſt the Courtiers Harangued, had privately whiſpered about, and pitched upon one to be their Speaker, and deliver their Sentiments. He haying taken a convenient place, ſaid; <hi>Great Sir, your Dutiful Subjects, whoſe Mouth I am, render you their moſt humble Thanks for your Care in Protecting and Defending them; They yield a blind Obedience to your Will, and wholly ſubmit themſelves to your Pleaſure, as becomes a People born under your Juriſdiction, who have ingrafted in them an hereditary Love and Reverence for you, and they beg Leave to put you in mind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is their Glory, they have made this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear during your whole Reign, which God long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue over us; They are ſenſible you make their Protection your Care, and that it is that which makes yon deſcend from being a Sovereign over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and their Fortunes to become a Father to every one, a Teſtimony of your Goodneſs which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:98488:37"/>they infinitely value; They are not ignorant of the many preſſing and unexpected Aceidents which bring upon you unavoidable Expences, not to be ſpared with Honour to you or Safety to them, and they are convinced you are too far exhauſted to defray them. I, in the Name of all your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, do freely offer all they poſſeſs without reſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing, but muſt alſo offer two things to your Conſideration. The one is, That if you now take all your Subjects have, you will drein that Source which is always to ſupply you and your Heirs; and if you undo them, you do that which you fear your Enemies ſhould do, and the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is ſo much the more fatal to you, by how much their being ruined by the Enemy is dubious, and by you certain; and they who adviſe you to deſtroy your ſelf, to prevent being deſtroyed, are rather Penſioners to the Enemy, than faithful Councellors to you. Remember the Countreyman</hi> (<hi>in</hi> Aeſop) <hi>to whom</hi> Jove <hi>gave a Hen that every day laid an Egg of Gold for his maintenance; He ſuffering himſelf to be deluded by avarice, fancied, that a Fowl that laid every day a Golden Egg muſt have rich Mines of that Metal within her, and therefore thought it better to ſeize all at once, than receive it by little and little. The Gods ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo ordered it, he killed the Hen, and was left without the Treaſure or the Egg. Do not you, Great Sir, verifie this Fable of the Philoſopher, for if you do, you will become a Fable to your People. A Prince of a poor People, is rather a Poor Man, or Poverty it ſelf, than a Prince. He who enriches his Subjects has as many Treaſures as he has Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, He who empoveriſhes them has ſo many
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:98488:38"/>Hoſpitals, he has as many Terrors as Men, and fewer Men than Enemies. Riches may be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken at any time, but Poverty cannot. We ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom endeavour to quit the former, but always the latter. The other thing I offer to your Conſideration is, That your preſent Wants proceed from two Cauſes. One, the immenſe Frauds and Depredations of thoſe about you. The other, the preſent extraordinary Emergencies. There is no doubt but the firſt named is the foremoſt as to time, and whether it be not the greateſt, belongs to you to examine. Divide therefore the Supply you require as you ſhall think fit, laying one part on thoſe who have made a property of your Revenues, and the other as a Tax upon your Subjects, and then none but a Traytor can complain.</hi> Thus had he ſpoke when, the Hour began, and the Czar riſing up ſaid;
<hi>Let them that have taken it from me reſtore what is wanting of what I had, and what is wanting after that let my People pay; and that this may not be delayed, all you and your Friends, who at a diſtance like Spunges have ſucked my Revenue, ſhall be left as you were when you came to my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, only allowing your Salaries.</hi> So great and univerſal was the Joy of the Commons hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this juſt Decree of the Czar; that they unanimouſly gave him the Title of
<hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and kneeling before him ſaid; <hi>As an Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment we agree to pay whatſoever you ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon us, and that done will of our own accord double the Sum, and ordain, that this Free Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may remain as a perpetual Duty payable every time you ſhall reſume what has been taken from you, whereby it will come to paſs that Covetous
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:98488:38"/>Men will be afraid to receive what you freely give them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Dutch</hi> their Riſe and Growth.</note>The <hi>Hollanders,</hi> who are beholding to the Sea for the Ground they live on, which is only ſome ſcraps of Land they have ſtolen from it, under the ſhelter of heaps of Clay they call Dykes; having quelled their inteſtine Broils by an univerſal Trade, after they had ſurrep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titiouſly erected themſelves into a Free State, and extended their Territories by Treachery, pretending to be the firſt-begotten of the Ocean, and conceiting, that the Sea, which gave them the Land it once covered for their Habitation, would not refuſe them that which compaſſes it, having covered it with Ships and Peopled it with Pyrates, reſolved at once in ſeveral places to encroach upon the Eaſt and Weſt. They go to our Fleets for Gold and Silver, as our Fleets go for it to the
<hi>Indies.</hi> They look upon it as the cheaper and ſhorter way to take it from thoſe that bring it, than from the Earth that produces it. The negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of an Admiral, or the favour of a Storm, furniſh them, with Plate at an eaſier rate than the Mines could do. In theſe Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings they have been forwarded, fauour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and aſſiſted by all the Princes of
<hi>Europe,</hi> who behold the Grandeur of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy with envious Eyes. Encouraged by theſe powerful Supports, they have eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Trade in <hi>India,</hi> ſettled Commerce in <hi>Japan,</hi> and ſtill perſiſting after many Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointments, have at length poſſeſt themſelves
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:98488:39"/>of the beſt part of <hi>Brazil,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">This was writ before the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> when the
<hi>Dutch</hi> ſtood poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of a great part of <hi>Brazil,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the
<hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueſe</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in <hi>India.</hi>
               </note> where they have not only the power of Government, but the Profit of the Sugar and Tobacco, which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riches them and beggars us. In this place, which is the in-let to the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> they reſide like Cormorants, ready to ſwallow Ships and whole Fleets, alarming <hi>Peru</hi> and
<hi>Potoſi;</hi> for that it appears by Geography, that they may gradually, without wetting their Feet, ſteal to thoſe Mountains, if weary of the Sea, they ſhould think much to creep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long the Coaſt down to <hi>Rio de la Plata,</hi> and <hi>Buenos Ayres,</hi> and to ſecure to themſelves the Streights of <hi>Magellan.</hi> That World Devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Aſſembly ſate conſulting over a Terreſtial Globe, and Sea Chart, with a pair of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, leaping over Climes and Countreys, and making choice of Provinces that were none of their own, and among them the Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioner with a Pair of Sciſſers in his Hand. ready to cut out the World according to his fancy. In this poſture they were when the Hour began, and a decrepid Old Fellow ſnatching the Sciſſers out of his Hand, ſaid; <hi>Gluttons, who are greedy of Provinces always dye for want of Digeſtion, no Surfeit ſo dangerous as that of Dominion. The</hi> Romans, <hi>from a narrow ſpot of Ground too little to Sow half a Buſhel of Corn, ſwallowed up all their Neighbours, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending their Avarice brought the whole World under the Yoke of their firſt Plough; and it being certain, that whoſoever pours himſelf out, waſtes as much as he extends, ſo they no ſooner had much to loſe but they began to loſe much; for Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:98488:39"/>gathers more than Force can preſerve. Whilſt they were poor they conquered the rich, who mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them rich and being left poor, took to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Cuſtoms inherent to Poverty, infeſting them with thoſe of Riches and Luxury, and by that means deſtroyed them, revenging themſelves on them with the very Riches they gave them. The</hi> Aſſyrians, Greeks,
<hi>and</hi> Romans <hi>are ſo many Skeletons to inſtruct us; it is fitter for us to take warning by, than to imitate thoſe ruined Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies. The more we raiſe our ſmall Weight, and the nearer we bring it in the<note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>Stil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard,</hi> which weighs great or ſmall things by putting forward or drawing back the weight up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Beam.</note> Roman
<hi>Ballance of Power to the great Maſs we would outweigh, the leſs we ſhall appear; but the more we draw it back, the better our ſmall Portion will turn the vaſt weight that ſtands againſt it; and if we draw back to the laſt Notch, one Pound of ours will poiſe a thouſand of theirs.</hi> Traiano Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calini <hi>hinted at this Secret in the Weight of his</hi> Politick Touchſtone, <hi>and it is verified in the Monarchy of</hi> Spain, <hi>from which we aim to draw away Weight, which added to ours will diminiſh it by the addition. Of Subjects to become a Free State was prodigious; to keep our ſelves ſo, is a Work that requires all our application.</hi> France <hi>and</hi> England, <hi>which aſſiſted us to cut off from</hi> Spain <hi>that part of its Dominion which was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable to them, will not for the ſame reaſon per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit us to ſwell to that greatneſs they may have cauſe to fear us. The Ax which joins to it ſelf all it cuts off from the Tree, will not be eſteemed a uſeful Inſtrument, but rather an Encumbrance. They will bear with us as long as they think we ſtand in need of them, but if once they imagine
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:98488:40"/>they can have occaſion for us, they will meditate our Ruine and Deſtruction. He who ſees a Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar on whom he has beſtowed Alms grown rich, either asks him to refund, or lend. We can gain nothing, but what the Princes who look on will covet for themſelves. As they deſpiſe the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour that is upon the loſing, ſo they fear him that is upon the getting hand. We by diſperſing act for the King of <hi>Spain</hi> againſt our ſelves, for ſhould be to divide and weaken us, wilfully loſe the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys we take from him, it were in him a Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem and no Loſs, and he will never be ſo able to take what we have, as when he has ſuffered us to take what he has ſo far from him and us.</hi> Brazil <hi>rather ſucks and unpeoples</hi> Holland <hi>than ſtrengthens it. It is enough for Thieves not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore what they have ſtolen, without continuing their Thefts for ever, which ſooner prefers them to the Gallows than to the Throne.</hi> The Penſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſnatching back the Scizars in a Pet, ſaid;</hi> Tho <hi>Rome</hi> loſt it ſelf, yet <hi>Venice</hi> holds out, and was at firſt but a Town-ſtealer as we are. The Gallows you ſpeak of is oftner the Lot of the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate than of Robbers, and all the World over the great Thief hangs the little one. He that Picks a Pocket is ever a Thief, he that ſtole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and Kingdoms was always a King, the Right of Monarchs is in the longeſt Sword. It is natural for one to be engendred out of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of another, he that is Corrupted is the Cauſe of him that is Engendred. A Carcaſs complains not of the Worms that eat it, becauſe it breeds them. Let every Man look to himſelf that he does not putrifie, otherwiſe he will be Father to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:98488:40"/>
               <hi>his own Worms. All things conſume, but the ſmall ſooner than the greater. When it ſhall come to paſs that they fear who pitied us, we will pity them we feared, which is a good exchange. If we can, let us be what they are, who were what we are. All the hints you have given are good, let not the Kings of</hi> France <hi>and</hi> England <hi>hear of them, but do you put us in mind hereafter, for that is an Obſtacle in the beginning, which proves good Advice when well advanced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Tuſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite's Advice.</note>The Great Duke of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> who by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding five Letters, which compoſe the Word <hi>Great,</hi> to his Title, has gained the ill will of all other Princes, was private in his Cloſet with a Servant whom he intruſted with his greateſt Secrets. They diſcourſed of the Beauty of his Cities, the greatneſs of his Territories, the Trade of <hi>Leghorne,</hi> and the Victories ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by his Galleys. From this they changed Subject, and fell upon the great Honour his Family had attained to, being Allied to moſt Monarchs and Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> by its Matches with
<hi>France,</hi> whereby the Kings of <hi>France, Spain,</hi> and <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> were by the Mothers ſide deſcended from it. Thus were they diſcourſing when the Hour began, and the Servant, as it were in a Prophetick Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſaid; <hi>Sir, Your Highneſs of a Private Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizen was made a Prince:</hi> Memento, Homo: <hi>Whilſt you were content to be a Prince, you was the richeſt among them, and now you look upon your ſelf as Father in Law of Kings, and Son in Law of Emperours,</hi> Pulvis es: <hi>and if you hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be Father in Law to</hi> France,
<hi>and the Cures
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:98488:41"/>of Match-making fall upon you,</hi> In pulverem reverteris. <hi>Your Country is Fruitful, your Cities Wealthy, your Ports full of Trade, your Galleys ſucceſsful, your Alliances great, and on all theſe accounts your State is truely Regal; but this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute I have diſcovered in it ſuch Stains as ſully and leſſen the value of it, which are theſe; The Remembrance the Subjects retain that once they were Equals; The Repubick of</hi> Luca <hi>which ſtarted up in the midſt of us; The Gariſons the King of</hi> Spain <hi>has in</hi> Tuſcany;
<hi>And the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Title</hi> Great <hi>to that of</hi> Duke, <hi>which all your Neighbours envy.</hi> The Duke, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had not reflected upon any of theſe things, ſaid;
<hi>What Method ſhall I uſe to take out theſe Stains?</hi> The Servant anſwered, <hi>They are ſo grounded in, it is impoſſible to take them out without cutting off the Piece, which is a Remedy worſe than the Diſeaſe, becauſe it is better to be Stained than Ragged. If the Stains I ſpeak of be taken out with the Piece, your Highneſs will ſcarce have a Rag left, but will be rent to tatters. The nature of theſe Stains is, they are cleanſed by ſinking in deeper, and not by being taken out. Your Highneſs muſt make uſe of Faſting Spittle, and ſuck in by little and little, and what you now ſpend in Portions for Queens, lay it out in ſtopping the Eyes and Ears of thoſe who obſerve you, that they way not perceive you ſuck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The State of <hi>Venice</hi> its Policy.</note>The moſt Serene Republick of
<hi>Venice,</hi> which in regard of its great Wiſdom and Prudence, is as it were the Brain of
<hi>Europe</hi> where the Judgment reſides, was aſſembled in full Senate. That Aſſembly was Compoſed of ſeveral
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:98488:41"/>Sounds, ſome more ſolid, others more quick, the common difference betwixt old and young, yet all Skilfull, ſome by Experience, and others by Information, making together ſuch a Harmony, that all the Princes in the World dance to their Muſick. The Doge Crowned Head of that powerful Free Nation ſate on a high Throne with three Counſellors on each ſide; on his Right was one Chief of the <hi>Quarantie,</hi> and on the left two; next theſe were the Secretaries who count the Balls, and in their places ſtood two Officers whoſe bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs it is to gather them The Silence was ſtupendious in ſo numerous an Aſſembly, and ſo far exceeded that of a Deſert, it was hard to perſwade the Eyes, but that the Audience was made up of Statues and not of Men, ſo very mute were the very Diſeaſes in the old, and ſo bridled the fierceneſs of the young. At length the Doge broke the Silence with theſe Words; <hi>Malice brings Diſcord into the World, Double-Dealing continues it, and Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation makes him that ſows it beloved even by him that ſuffers by it. The Wars we have occaſioned among our Friends, not thoſe we have made with our Enemies, have given us Peace and Victory. We ſhall be free ſo long as we employ others in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing one another. Our Light ſprings from Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſention, we are like the Spark that is produced from the colliſion of the Flint and Steel. The more Monarchs batter one another, the more we ſhine.</hi> Italy, <hi>ſince the decay of the Empire, is like to a Rich and Beautiful Heireſs, who, her Parents dying, was left to the Care of Guardians
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:98488:42"/>and Truſtees, and deſires to be Married. But the Truſtees having divided her Fortune between themſelves, and being loth to reſtore, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous to keep what they have, ſome of them miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents her to the King of</hi> Spain <hi>who courts her, and the others to the King of</hi> France <hi>who asks her in Marriage, at the ſame time finding thoſe Faults in the Suitors which they ſee in themſelves. Theſe falſe Truſtees are the Princes of</hi> Italy, <hi>and among them it is not to be denied but that we alſo have ſeized a great part of her Fortune. The two Suitors now preſs hard to carry their Miſtreſs. We have made uſe of the King of</hi> France <hi>to put by the Catholick King, who being ſo near a Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in</hi> Naples <hi>and</hi> Milan, <hi>makes ſigns to her, and from his own Windows overlooks her. The moſt Chriſtian King, who being at a diſtance could not gallant, nor ſo much as ſee her, and therefore made Love by Letter; now by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of</hi> Savoy, Mantua,
<hi>and</hi> Parma, <hi>and his approach to</hi> Pignerol, <hi>he Ogles and Courts her, and this obliges us to cheat him of her. This is eaſie to do, becauſe there is leſs trouble in caſting out the</hi> French, <hi>than in bringing them in; they expel others with their Fury, and themſelves with their Haughtineſs. However this Snare muſt be ſo laid, that at the ſame time we break the Match, we may receive Thanks for promoting it. The Moſt Chriſtian King has bent his thoughts upon</hi> Lorrain, <hi>his Succeſs in</hi> Germany <hi>is dubious, and Subjects poor, which things diſcourage his Partiſans in</hi> Italy, <hi>ſo that we ſhall not find any great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in attaining our ends, for his own Motions will diſguiſe ours, and we need not raiſe Jealouſies in
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:98488:42"/>thoſe that have confided in him, ſince their repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſaves us that labour. It is my Opinion we ſhall ſubdue the King of</hi> France <hi>by encouraging him to go on in his great Undertakings, and by heightning his credulity. Our utmoſt endeavours muſt be uſed to raiſe the Eſteem he has of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, for this Man who takes from him all that he adds to himſelf, leſſens him as he grows great. As long as the Subject has the aſcendent over his King, and the King is ſubject to his Servant, the Subject will be hated as a Traytor, and the King undervalued as of a mean Spirit. The way to deſtroy a King publickly with ſafety is to ſtand up for his Favourite. I know not whether</hi> Ravilliac <hi>was more fatal to his Father than</hi> Richlieu <hi>has been to him. This I know, that betwixt them they have robbed him of both Parents, the firſt of his Father, the ſecond of his Mother. May</hi> Richlieu
<hi>continue, for he is like a Diſeaſe which by continuance either conſumes it ſelf, or him that endures it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lewis</hi> the 13th had at that time no Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it was ſuppoſed the Crown would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volve to his Brother, the Duke of
<hi>Orelans<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It is requiſite we caſt an Eye upon the Succeſſion of the Crown of</hi> France, <hi>which is like to fall to the Kings Brother, whoſe generous Nature we have reaſon to hope we may impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He is like a Fire that may be blown away, yet kindles it ſelf. He is diſobliged at the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours he receives, whereby he has offended the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>and ſowen the Seeds of Diſſention, which we may improve to our benefit.</hi> France <hi>is diſſatisfied at the Prime Miniſter's, pretending to be of the Blood Royal, which he claims by forged Genealogies, and is diſguſted to ſee all Places of Profit and Truſt in the Hands of his Kindred and Friends They remember the Beheading of</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:98488:43"/>Montmorency, <hi>and the Baniſhing ſo many great Men and they ſuſpect that Violence and not Right will take place in the Succeſſion to the Crown. The Affairs of</hi> Germany <hi>are paſt compoſing, the</hi> Palatin <hi>being diſpoſſeſſed, the Duke of</hi> Lorrain <hi>outed, and the Duke of</hi> Saxony <hi>and other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants of the Empire conſpiring againſt the Houſe of</hi> Auſtria. Italy <hi>ſeems to deſpair of Peace by reaſon of the Gariſons the</hi> French <hi>have within it. The King of</hi> Spain <hi>has his hands full with the</hi> Dutch, <hi>who have taken what he had in</hi> Holland, <hi>and aim to rob him of what he has, being already poſſeſſed of the beſt part of</hi> Braſil, <hi>which furniſhes their Fleets with the Trade of Sugar, Tobacco, and Braſil Wood, and having fortified themſelves in one of the Leeward Iſlands. Beſides all this he is engaged to ſupport the Emperor and maintain the State of</hi> Milan <hi>againſt the</hi> French. <hi>We, like the Spring in a Striking Watch, muſt move theſe Hands every hour and every moment without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perceived, continually ſounding abroad with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever turning back. Our Politicks work like the Glaſs-makers, who blow things into form, and we ſow Fire to produce Ice.</hi> Hither was he come when the Hour began, the wonderful influence whereof inſpiring the Politick Brain of a Republican of the <hi>Capi-Duchi,</hi> made him Diſcourſe to this effect. Venice <hi>is the very Figure and Reſemblance of</hi> Pontius Pilate <hi>Probo.</hi> Pilate <hi>out of meer Policy condemned the Juſt and waſhed his Hands:</hi> Ergo. Pilate <hi>diſmiſſed</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabbas,
<hi>who was Sedition it ſelf, and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended Jeſus that was Peace it ſelf.</hi> Igitur. Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>positively ſaid,</hi> What I have written, I
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:98488:43"/>have written. Tenet conſequentia. Pilate <hi>delivered the Peace and Safety of the World to Mutiniers, to be crucified.</hi> Non poteſt negari. All the Aſſembly lifted a Cry, and fell into Confuſion, the Doge ordered the Republican, <hi>Nemine contradicente,</hi> to be put into Irons, and that his Genealogy ſhould be enquired into, for that it was viſible he was ſome way defended from ſome body that depended on another, who was a Friend to ſome one that was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with ſome Perſon that came from another that had ſomething of a
<hi>Spaniard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans, <hi>and</hi> Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts.</note>The Heretical <hi>Germans,</hi> among whom there are as many Hereſies as Men, who conſume themſelves in ſupporting the Tyranny of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and the Treachery of the Electors of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and the Landtgrave of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> perceiving themſelves infected with the <hi>French</hi> Diſeaſe, reſolved to cure themſelves at once. Conſidering that the Salivation of ſo many paſt Calamities, nor the Flux they were put into at <hi>Norlinguen,</hi> nor the many Bleedings, <hi>Uſque ad animi deliquium,</hi> of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny overthrows, had availed nothing, they gathered all the Phyſicians, Chymiſts and Mountebanks they could find, and having made known to them their Diſtemper, asked their Advice thereupon. Some were of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the only Remedy was to Purge out the French Humours that were crept into their Bones. Others affirming the Diſtemper lay altogether in their Heads, preſcribed Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines to carry off the Humour, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge them of dull Notions, by the Help of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:98488:44"/>
               <hi>Hypocrates</hi> his <hi>Tetragonum</hi> ſo much applauded by
<hi>Galen,</hi> to which the ſmoak of Tobacco exactly anſwers. Others more Superſtitious, and Magically inclined, affirmed it was no Natural Diſeaſe they were troubled with, but were exagitated by Evil Spirits, and that as Perſons poſſeſſed they ſtood in need of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orciſms. In the midſt of the Learned Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the Hour began, and a Phyſician of
<hi>Prague</hi> with an Audible Voice ſaid; <hi>There is no Cure for this Diſeaſe of the</hi> Germans, <hi>becauſe all their Maladies and Diſtempers are only to be Cured with a Regular Diet, and as long as</hi> Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>and</hi> Calvin <hi>keep their Taverns open, and they have thirſtty Throats, and as long as they do not abſtain from</hi> French <hi>Cooks Shops and Bawdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, they will never be ſo temperate as they ought to be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Grand S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gnior, the Advice given him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſco,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d by <hi>Sinon</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a.</note>The Grand Signior or Emperor of the
<hi>Turks,</hi> a Monarch raiſed by the Forgeries and Deceit of <hi>Mahomet</hi> to a vaſt Dominion, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned together all his Viſſers, Baſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, Begler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>begs, Generals, and other Eminent Men of his Mighty Port, all or moſt of them being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negadoes, as alſo the Chriſtian Captives, who lying in perpetual Slavery, ſuffer a lingring Death in the Seven Towers of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> without hope of Redemption by reaſon of the Pride of that Haughty Monarch, who looks upon it as a Diminution of his Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur to Ranſom Slaves, and deems that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Vertue of Mercy as proper only to the the Vulgar. The Concourſe was therefore extraordinary, and greater the Expectation of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:98488:44"/>all Men, becauſe there had been no Precedent of ſuch an Aſſembly in the Memory of Man. The Grand Signior looking on it as too great a condeſcenſion that his Voice ſhould be heard, or his Perſon ſeen by his Subjects, being feat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a lofty Throne behind a Curtain which allowed only ſome ſcant paſſage to the ſight, made a ſign to the Aſſembly to give Ear to what things one of the<note n="*" place="margin">The
<hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſcoes</hi> were the Race of the <hi>Moores</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> moſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were counterfeit Chriſtians, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired to bring in the <hi>Moors</hi> again, for which rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they were all expelled by King <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip III.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Moriſcoes,</hi> who had been expelled <hi>Spain,</hi> offered to him by way of advice. The <hi>Moriſco,</hi> after proſtrating himſelf at the Emperor's Feet, ſacrilegiouſly adoring, aroſe again and ſaid: <hi>We the true and conſtant</hi> Mahometants, <hi>who through the courſe of a tedious Captivity in</hi> Spain, <hi>have for many years privately entertained in our Hearts the Law of the Prophet deſcended from</hi> Agar, <hi>hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly acknowledging the unparallelled goodneſs of the Almighty Monarch of the World, the Great Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror of the</hi> Turks, <hi>in receiving us the miſerable Relicks of that Expulſioh, have reſolved among our ſelves to do his moſt Potent Majeſty ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Service, which muſt be grounded on our Knowledge and Experience, having no Fortunes to offer, as being a Multitude ſtripped of all we po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſſed. To this effect, the firſt thing we propoſe is, That for the Honour of our Nation, and as a Reward to our invincible Generals and Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, in continuing the Memory of their Exploits, it is convenient, that after the manner of</hi> Greece, Rome, <hi>and</hi> Spain, <hi>Colledges and Univerſities be erected, aad Rewards be aſſigned to Learning, for by it, after the Death of the Monarchs, and Extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation of the Monarchies, the</hi> Greek <hi>and</hi> Latin
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:98488:45"/>
               <hi>Languages ſtill gloriouſly ſurvive, and in them in ſpight of Death, do ſtill flouriſh their Heroick Actions, Virtues and Names, being reſcued from the Oblivion of the Grave by thoſe Studies which enriched their Minds, and made their Nations ceaſe to be Barbarous. The ſecond Propoſition is, That the Laws and Cuſtoms of the</hi> Romans <hi>be received, ſo far forth as they are not directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to our Law; to the end that Policy may be advanced, Diſorders ſuppreſſed, Virtue Rewarded, Vice puniſhed, and the Diſtribution of Juſtice may be ſo eſtabliſhed, that neither Affection, Malice, nor Bribery may have place, but a ſure and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Method be ſettled in all parts. The third is, That for our greater Benefit in Fight our crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Cimiters be changed for</hi> Spaniſh
<hi>Tucks, becauſe they are more handy either to defend or offend, the great circular motion of cutting being ſaved by thruſting, by which means whenever we have come to Handy-blows with the</hi> Spaniards, <hi>we have ſuſtained unspeakable Loſs, that Nation exceeding all others in handling their Rapier and beſides the Swords are lighter of carriage, and eaſier to weild. The fourth, That to preſerve Health, and recover it when impaired, the uſe of Wine be by all means allowed, becauſe moderately taken it is the beſt Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle of Nutriment, and moſt Efficacious Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine. It is alſo a rich Fund to increaſe the Grand Signior's and his Subjects Revenues, there being ſeveral Liquors produced by the Grape which create a conſiderable Trade. Nay, it is more powerful and effectual than Opium to raiſe the Spirits and excite the Blood to bold Undertakings. Neither ought the prohibition in our Law which has been
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:98488:45"/>already partly diſpenſed with, to be any hindrance, for a proper interpretation to our purpoſe may be found. For the putting all we have propoſed in execution, we offer to furniſh Schemes and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectors, who ſhall carry it on without any Charge or Trouble to the Publick; and are aſſured it will add much to the grandeur and glory of all the Great Emperor of</hi> Conſtantinople<hi>'s Dominions.</hi> Scarce had he uttered the laſt Word, when
<hi>Sinan</hi> Baſſa, a Renegado, ſtarted up, foaming with rage, and ſaid; <hi>If all the Devils in Hell had conſpired againſt the</hi> Turkiſh <hi>Monarchy, they could not have invented four ſuch curſed Plagues as have been propoſed by this</hi> Moriſco <hi>Dog, who among Chriſtians was an ill</hi> Mahometan, <hi>and would be an ill Chriſtian among the</hi> Turks. <hi>Theſe Fellows would have rebelled in</hi> Spain, <hi>and here they would deſtroy us. The reaſon for expelling them there was not greater than this, it will be convenient we revenge our ſelves on thoſe who ſent them among us by returning them back. Don</hi> John <hi>of</hi> Auſtria <hi>had not more deſtructive Deſigns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Power, when at</hi> Lepanto
<hi>opening the Veins of ſo many Janiſaries, he cauſed the Fiſh to ſwim in Blood, and made a new Red Sea not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior to the old. The</hi> Perſian Green Turbant <hi>doth not more maliciouſly aim at the overthrow of our Empire; Nor did D.</hi> Peter Giron <hi>Duke of</hi> Oſſuna, <hi>and Viceroy of</hi> Naples <hi>and</hi> Sicily, <hi>with his Fleets and Land Forces, and Terrour of his Name more fiercely endeavour to obliterate the Memory of our Half Moons, whoſe light he often ſullied, when our Veſſels ſcarce thought themſelves ſecure of him at</hi> Pera <hi>and</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>than
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:98488:46"/>thou infernal Dog with thoſe four Proportions haſt laboured to do. Helhound, Monarchies are upheld by the ſame Arts that erect them. They have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways been raiſed by Souldiers, and always corrupted by Pendants. Kings hold their Dominions by the Sword, not by their Books. Armies gain and defend them, not Univerſities. Victories make them great and formidable, not Arguments. Battles beſtow Kingdoms and Crowns, Learning Caps and Degrees. Whenever a State begins to aſſign Rewards for Learning, Dignities are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on Drones, Craft is honoured, Subtlely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, and Favour Rewarded, and then the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror depends on the Doctor, the Soldier on the Scholar, and the Sword on the Pen. The igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the People is the greateſt ſecurity of Princes, Learning which inſtructs makes them mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinous. Learned Subjects rather conſpire than obey, rather examine their Soveraign than reſpect him. No ſooner they underſtand, but they deſpiſe him. No ſooner can they know what liberty is, than they deſire it. They can judge whether he that Reigns is worthy to Rule, and then begin to Reign over the Prince. Learning is the cauſe that Peace is ſought after, becauſe it ſtands in need of it, and Peace that is ſought after draws on the moſt dangerous War. No War is ſo deſtructive as that he endures who ſeems to covet Peace; The latter ſues with Words and Embaſſies, and the former makes its advantage of the fear that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the Intreaties. When a Nation affects Scholars and Writers, Gooſo Quils place of Swords and Muskets; Ink in writing is more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious than Blood ſpilt; a Sheet of Paper ſigned
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:98488:46"/>is of more force than Armour proof againſt Shot; and the Hand of a Coward by virtue of the Pen extracts from the Inkhorn Honours, Revenues, Titles, and Grandeur. Many Vile Wretches wear the Black Robe. Many raiſe Eſtates by their Writings, and many great Men are deſended from Scriblers.</hi> Rome, <hi>when beginning in a ſmall circumference, ſcarce big enough to ſow two Buſhels of Corn, it grew to a vaſt Commonwealth, uſed neither Doctors nor Books, but Souldiers and Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons. All there was Violence and no Study, they raviſh't the Women they wanted, ſubdued what was near, and aimed at what was farther off. No ſooner did</hi> Cicero, Brutus, Hortenſius, <hi>and</hi> Caeſar <hi>introduce Harangues and Declarations, than they began Seditions, and conſpiring deſtroyed one another, and others themſelves, and even the Commonwealth. The Emperors and the Empire were deſtroyed, and overthrow by the ambition of the Orators. Even among Birds only thoſe ſuffer impriſonment in Cages which talk and ſing, and the more perfectly they do it the cloſer they are kept. Then the Schools were made the Magazines againſt Arms, Orations ſanctified Crimes and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Virtue, and whilſt the Tongue reigned Triumphs were ſubject to the power of Words. The <hi>Greeks</hi> ſuffered by the ſame itch of Learning, they were proud of their Academies which vied with their Armies, and their Philoſophers were a plague to their Generals. Wit became the Judger of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and they grew rich in Books and poor in Triumphs. You ſay their Heroes ſtill live in their famous Authors, and their Language ſtill ſurvives tho their Monarchy be extinct. The ſame happens
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:98488:47"/>to a Dagger which wounds a Man, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues when the Man is gone, and yet that is no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to the dead Man. It were better the Monarchy ſurvived, tho dumb and without a Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, than that the Language ſhould laſt without a Monarchy. <hi>Greece</hi> and
<hi>Rome</hi> are become Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choes, forming in the hollow emptineſs of their Majeſty, not whole ſounds, but the very extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of abſent Words. Thoſe very Authors that extolled them could allot themſelves but ſo ſhort a Life at the pleaſure of the Reader, that in ſome it reaches only the Underſtanding, in others goes not beyond Curioſity. <hi>Spain,</hi> whoſe People in danger were always prodigal of Life, covetous of Death, and impatient of Age, when with unparallelled Reſolution it raiſed its Head out of ruin, grew to a mighty Flame from ſcattered Embers, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a prodigy from a Skeleton, rather attended to furniſh Matter for Writing, than to Write, and to deſerve Praiſes than to Compoſe them. Their Drums and Trumpets ſpoke for them, and all their Speeches were repeated Huzza's before Battle. They furniſhed the World with Subject of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration under</hi> Viriatus <hi>and</hi> Sertorious; <hi>they gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed glorious Victories for</hi> Hannibal; <hi>they obliged</hi> Caeſar, <hi>who till then every where fought for Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, to fight for his Life, and they exceeded Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Reſolution it ſelf at</hi> Numantia. <hi>Yet of theſe and many other their Brave Actions they writ nothing, all was Recorded by the</hi> Romans. <hi>Their Valour made uſe of Foreign Pens, they thought it enough for them to Act, and for the</hi> Latines <hi>to Write. As long as they knew not how to be Hiſtorians, they deſerved t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. Artillery
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:98488:47"/>was not long ſince invented to take off Lives before ſecured by diſtance, to overthrow the ſtrongeſt Walls, and to beſtow Victories by aim, not by true Courage; but preſently after was Printing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented in oppoſition to Cannon, it is, Metal againſt Metal, Ink againſt Powder, and Letters againſt Bullets. Wet Powder takes no effect, there is no doubt but it is moiſtned by the Ink that ſends down Orders to provide and diſpoſe it. There is no doubt but there is a ſcarcity of Lead to make Bullets, ever ſince it is conſumed in caſting of Letters. But it was Battles that gave us Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, Souldiers gained the Victories, and the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the Rewards, which ought always to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on thoſe who always made us Triumph. They who called Letters and Arms Siſters, knew nothing of their Pedegree, for no Families are leſs of Kin than Saying and Doing. The Steel is never joined to the Quill but to cut it, but the Quill with thoſe very Wounds it receives from the Steel revenges it ſelf. Moſt contemptible</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſco, <hi>it is our deſire that among our Adverſaries there be many Learned, and among us many Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious, for it is Victory over our Enemies that we covet, and not their Practices. The ſecond thing you propoſe, is to receive the Laws of the</hi> Romans,
<hi>which if once you had compaſſed you had ruined all. Our whole Empire would run into confuſion betwixt Plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffs and Defendants, and Inferior and Superior Judges, and the People would be all taken up in the Employments of Councellors, Sollicitors, Atturneys, Clerks, Apparitors, Serjeants, and other Pepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants of Courts. Thus War which now makes choice of Men will be forced to take up with the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:98488:48"/>Refuſe of the Embroilers of the Nation, and there will be more Suits, not becauſe there will be more occaſion, but becauſe there will be more Laws. Following out own Methods, we enjoy as much Peace as we ſtand in need of, and as much War as we pleaſe to Make with our Neighbours. The Laws in themſelves are juſt and good, but where there are Lawyers they are dull and ſenſeleſs. This cannot be denied; ſince the Lawyers themſelves own it as often as they impoſe what ſenſe they pleaſe upon the Law, ſuppoſing of it ſelf it has none. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Judge affirms he is an interpreter of the Law, and by giving a meaning to it, ſuppoſes it has none. I for my part am a Renegado, and was a Chriſtian, and do avouch as an Eye Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, there is no Law eitheir Civil or Rational but what has as many meanings as there are Lawyers, Commentators, or Judges, who give it ſo many that it proves at laſt to have none at all. When then there is no reaſon to diſpoſſeſs a Man of his Eſtate, there never wants a Law, which being either ſtrained, or ill interpreted, is ground enough for a Suit, and both the Plaintiff and Defendant are in the end Sufferers. Conſider now what Two wholeſome Propoſitions have been made by this thankful</hi> Moriſco. <hi>The third thing is, that we ſhould change our Cimiters for long Swords. In this particular, as there is no conſiderable ill co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence to obſtruct, ſo I can find no great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to encouraging us to put it in execution. The Half Moon is our diſtinctive Character, and that we always brandiſh in our Cimiters. To take up the Faſhions and Cuſtoms of Enemies is a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony proper to Slaves, and a Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for Conquer'd People or at leaſt it is an men or forerunner of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:98488:48"/>both. If we are to be permanent, let us ſtick to the old Proverb, which, ſays,</hi> Let that ever be done, which was always done; <hi>for by keeping to it we ſhall be free from Novelties. Let the Chriſtian thruſt and the Turk hew, and let this</hi> Moriſco
<hi>expelled by the former be impaled by the latter. As to the fourth and laſt point, which relates to the uſe of Vineyards and Wine, let thirſty Souls agree about it with the</hi> Alcoran. <hi>No ſmall toleration has been given in this caſe long ago. But I muſt obſerve, that if there be an univerſal Toleration of Wine and Taverns, it will only ſerve to enhance the price of Water, and to make us buy Rain by the Quart. My Opinion is therefore, weighing what has been propoſed, that this Cur is a greater Enemy to thoſe that harbour, than to thoſe that expelled him. All the Aſſembly heard this Diſcourſe with profound ſilence. The</hi> Moriſco <hi>looked pitiouſly, a cold ſweat running down his Forehead.</hi> Then
<hi>Hali,</hi> the Prime Viſier, who ſtood next to the Curtain that was before the Grand Signior, after conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Looks, ſaid; <hi>Chriſtian Slaves, what ſay you to what you have heard?</hi> They ſeeing the blindneſs of that deluded Nation, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving they loved their own barbarity, and placed their Security in Tyranny and Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, abhorring the light of Learning, and the Juſtice of Laws, cauſed a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man who had been 30 years in ſlavery, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for them all, which he did in theſe Words. <hi>We</hi> Spaniards
<hi>ſhall not adviſe you to any thing that is for your good, becauſe it would be a piece of Treachery againſt our Monarch, and an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt our Religion; neither will we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:98488:49"/>you, becauſe we do not ſtand in need of frauds to defend our ſelves againſt you; therefore we Chriſtians have reſolved thus ſilently to wait our doom.</hi> The Grand Signior influenced by the Hour, and drawing the Curtains before his Throne, (a thing never before ſeen) with an angry Voice, ſaid; <hi>Let thoſe Chriſtians be ſet free, their generous goodneſs ſhall be their Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, Cloath and furniſh them plentifully for their Voyage out of the Eſtates of the</hi> Moriſcoes. <hi>And let that Dog be burnt alive for propoſing of Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and all that ſhall follow his Example ſhall ſuffer the like pain. It is my choice to be called Barbarous Conqueror, rather than be Learned and overthrown. All our knowledge muſt be to know how to overcome, for an ignorant People is the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Tyrant. I command all here preſent to forget what they heard from this</hi> Moriſco, <hi>the powers of the Soul ſhall obey my Orders, as well as the Corporal Senſes, therefore let your Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries dread my Anger.</hi> Thus the Hour gave to every one what they deſerved, the Barbarous Infidels were hardened in their Ignorance, the Chriſtians obtained their Liberty, and the
<hi>Moriſco</hi> was puniſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Dutch</hi> Propoſals to the <hi>Indians</hi> of <hi>Chile,</hi> and their An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</note>A <hi>Dutch</hi> Ship by ſtreſs of Weather was forced into one of the Ports of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chile</hi> is the Coaſt of <hi>America</hi> on the South of
<hi>Peru.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chile.</hi> The <hi>Indians,</hi> guarded that Harbour, being a People who in that Harbour, being a People who in that Conquered World Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully defended their Liberty, to the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Souls in their Idolatry, with Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons in their Souls in their Hands attack'd the Ships Crew, thinking they were <hi>Spaniards,</hi> whoſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions encloſed them, and from whoſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:98488:49"/>they have ſtill exempted themſelves. The Captain pacified them, ſaying, They were <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and came as Ambaſſadors from that Commonwealth with a Meſſage of importance to the Caciques and Chief Men. Then ſweetning theſe Words with rich Wine brewed after the manner of the North, and mollifying them with Butter and other Rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they were admitted and careſſed. The <hi>Indian</hi> who commanded gave an account to the Magiſtrates of the new People that was arrived, and of their Intentions. All the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Men and a great number of People aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled with their Weapons in their Hands. This Nation is ſo provident againſt Poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſo jealous of Appearances, that they receive Ambaſſadors with the ſame precaution as they meet an Enemies Army. The Captain of the Ship came before them, attended by 4 of his Men, and a Slave ſerving as an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter; They asked of him, Who he was? Whence he came? To what purpoſe? And, From whom? He anſwered, not without ſome dread of the Warlike Audience. <hi>I am a</hi> Dutch <hi>Captain, and come from</hi> Holland, <hi>a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth in the Weſt, to offer you our Friendſhip and Trade. We live in a Land which the Sea from above looks down upon with indignation to ſee it dry below its billows. We were not long ſince Subjects, and part of the Dominion of the Great Monarch of</hi> Spain
<hi>and the New World, where only your Valour has exempted it ſelf from his Crown, which like, the Sun extends its compaſs round the Earth. We gained our Liberty with
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:98488:50"/>immenſe labour, becauſe the Severity of Ring</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip <hi>the Second preferred the Bloody Execution of</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">The Two Counts, <hi>Horn</hi> and
<hi>Egmont.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>two Noblemen, before the Sovereignty of ſo many Provinces. Revenge inflamed our Courage, and carrying on a War which laſted above</hi> 60 <hi>years without interruption, we have ſacrificed Two Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of Men to thoſe two Lives, and made the Fields of the</hi> Low-Countreys <hi>an univerſal Burial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place to all</hi> Europe. <hi>Our Succeſs has made us abſolute Maſters of half thoſe Countreys, and not ſo ſatisfied we have taken many ſtrong Holds in the other Provinces, have gained large Dominions in the Eaſt, and in</hi> Brazil <hi>have Conquered</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nambuco <hi>and</hi> Paraiba, <hi>enriching our ſelves with Brazil Wood, Tobacco, and Sugar; And to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, of Subjects that we were to the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>are become his moſt implacable Enemies. We have taken it into our Conſideration, that the</hi> Spaniards <hi>have not only ſubdued theſe Provinces, but that in few years they have deſtroyed in them many Towns, peopling them again with Strangers, ſo that there ſcarce remains the Memory of the Natives in their Tombs, and that the mighty Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Kings, Caziques, and other Princes, are ſo wholly extinct and buried in Oblivion as if they had never been. We perceive that you alone (either that you are Wiſer, or warned by the Fate of others) main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain an Hereditary Liberty, and by your Valour the</hi> American <hi>Race is preſerved from ſlavery. It is natural for every Creature to love its likeneſs, and ſince you and our Commonwealth ſo much reſemble one another, it was decreed to ſend me through ſuch vaſt Seas, and ſuch dangerous diſtance, to tender you their ſincere Amity and Friendſhip, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:98488:50"/>to offer not only for your Defence, but to promote your further Deſigns to furniſh you with Ships, Cannon, Officers and Souldiers, who are ſuch as are praiſed and admired by all by whom they are not feared. By way of Trade they offer you free Commerce in their Dominions, with a Brotherly and perpetual Alliance, deſiring for themſelves the freedom of your Ports, and the ſettlement of a League Offenſive and Defenſive upon equal Terms on both ſides. And the more to expreſs their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, by their great Intereſt they will ſecure you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Friendſhip of many Kings, Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths their Confederates.</hi> The
<hi>Indians</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned a courteous Anſwer, telling him, That to receive his Propoſals it was enough to hear him, but in order to give their Anſwer they muſt conſult in Counsel, and the next day at the ſame time would give him their Reſolution. It was ſo agreed, and the
<hi>Dutchman,</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Indians</hi> are naturally inclined to Toys and Curioſities, the better to gain their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections he preſented them with Barrels of Butter, Cheeſe, Casks of Wine, Swords, Hats, and Looking-glaſſes, and laſtly a Tele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope, highly extolling the uſe of it, ſaying, By the help of it they might ſee Ships at Ten or Twelve Leagues diſtance, and diſcover by their Colours whether they belonged to Friends or Enemies, that the ſame they might do by Land. He added, that with it they might find Stars in Heaven which they had never ſeen before, nor could not be diſcerned without it; That through it they might plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpots in the Face of the Moon,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:98488:51"/>which look like Eyes, and Mouth, and might perceive a black ſpot in the Circle of the Sun. That it wrought theſe Wonders by drawing with thoſe two Glaſſes cloſe to the Eyes things that were at a vaſt diſtance. The Principal Man among the <hi>Indians</hi> asked for it, and the <hi>Dutchman</hi> having opened it to the due diſtance, and inſtructed him how to uſe it, delivered it to him. He clapt his Right Eye to it, and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling it towards the Mountains, ſet up a Cry that teſtified his Admiration to the reſt, telling them, He had at four Leagues diſtance plainly ſeen Men, Beaſts and Birds, and the Rocks and Shrubs, ſo near at hand that they ſeemed bigger than natural cloſe, to the fartheſt Glaſs. Here the influence of the Hour affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and they having gabled in their Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſome Diſcourſes in appearances paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, he that took the Glaſs holding it in his Left Hand directed his Diſcourſe to the <hi>Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> in theſe Words. <hi>An Inſtrument that finds a Spot in the Sun, proves the Moon a Lyar, and diſcovers what Heaven hides, is a miſchievous In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, a Glaſs Pickthank, and cannot be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Heaven. Its attracting things at a great diſtance, is a ſufficient cauſe to raiſe a Jealouſie in us who are far removed from you. With this doubtleſs it was you diſcovered us ſo remote, and through it we have deſcryed the deſign you labour to hide under your Specious Offers. By this Artifice you pry into the Elements, and thruſt your ſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Sovereignty. You, as you ſay, live dry below the Water, and wreſt your Land wrongfully from the Sea. We ſhall not be ſuch Fools to take thoſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:98488:51"/>for our Friends who could not be good Subjects, nor ſhall we truſt them with our Habitations who have ſtolen theirs from the Fiſhes. You were Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the Kings of</hi> Spain, <hi>and having uſurped his Dominion, value your ſelves upon being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, and would have us through a fond credulity become a Prey to your Treachery. Neither is it true that we reſemble you, for in maintaining that Native Country which Nature gave us, we only defend what is our own, we preſerve our Liberty, but do not ſteal it. You offer to aſſiſt us againſt the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>yet confeſs at the ſame time you have taken</hi> Brazil <hi>from him, which was his; if you take the</hi> Indies <hi>from him who took them from us, how much more reaſon have we to be afraid of you than of him. You muſt obſerve that</hi> America <hi>is a rich Beautiful Harlot, and ſince ſhe was falſe to her Husbands, ſhe will never be true to her Bullies. Chriſtians ſay Heaven pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the</hi> Indies <hi>becauſe they adored Idols, and we</hi> Indians <hi>ſay, Heaven will puniſh the Chriſtians becauſe they adore the</hi> Indies. <hi>You think you carry Gold and Silver, and you only carry well coloured Envy and precious Miſery. You take from us, that you may have for others to take from you. That which makes you our Enemies, makes you Enemies to one another. Be gone then within two hours out of this Port, and let us know if you want for any thing. If you have a mind to gain our good will, ſince you are ſo good at Invention, invent an Inſtrument to remove what is by us at a great diſtance, for we promiſe you we will never look upon your Country nor</hi> Spain <hi>with this that attracts things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat are far off. Carry away this
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:98488:52"/>Glaſs Spy, this Diſcoverer of the Firmament, for we have no need of it, being able with the help of our Eyes only to diſcover more in you than we like; and let me tell you, the Sun is beholding to it for ſhewing you the black ſpot in his Circle, or elſe for the colour ſake you would have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to cut out and ſtamp him into Money.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Blacks conſult how to deliver themſelves from Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very.</note>The Blacks aſſembled in mighty numbers to conſult about obtaining their Liberty, a thing they have often earneſtly ſollicited. The nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous Concourſe being ſeated and ſilent, one of the chiefeſt among them, who in that ſwarthy Audience appeared blacker than the reſt, and had propoſed this Affair in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſpoke to this purpoſe. <hi>There is no cauſe for our ſlavery but our colour, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour is an accident, not a crime. Yet certain it is, thoſe who Lord it over us have no colour for their Tyranny, but our colour, which is produced by the preſence and nearneſs of the greateſt Beauty, to wit, the Sun. Flocky Heads, and clotted Hair, ſquab N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes, and Blubber Lips, are no better grounds for our Captivity. Many Whites might be Slaves if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe three things carried is, and it were more reaſonable they ſhould be ſo who are hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous with their mighty N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſes like Rudders in their Faces, and ſnivle through Elephants Trunks, than we who have nothing to looſe by the Pox, and are the very Oppoſites to the Snouts. Why do not the Whites conſider, that if we look like Blots among them, one of them looks like a Stain among its. Did they make Slaves of the Mulattoes, it were more excuſable, for they are a Rabble with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a King, a Compound betwixt Light and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:98488:52"/>Darkneſs, Wainſcot Paces compared with White Men, Foils to the Brown, the next degree to the Blacks, and the very Picture of Soot. In all Ages there have been Men of our Complexion Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Martial Exploits, Learning, Virtue, and Sanctity, it is needleſs for me to repeat a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of them, for they are ſufficiently known. Nor can it be denied, that we are preferable to the Whites for not endeavouring to diſguiſe the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour Nature gave to our Skins. Among them the Women that are ſwarthy or brown, plaſter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like Walls to become White, and they that are White never ſatisfied with Whiteneſs waſh to encreaſe it. Only our Women contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their Natural Complexion, are beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in the dark, and the whiteneſs of their Teeth ſhining the brighter through their blackneſs, when they ſmile they ſparkle like the Stars in the night. Neither do we bely our Age, dye our Hair, or wear falſe Locks. Why then are we contemned and chaſtiſed. This is it I offer to your Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that you may conſult what Means may be uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d for obtaining our due liberty and reſt.</hi> The Hour prevailed, and a Black whoſe Head through Age was become grey, contrary to the received Opinion, that Black takes no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, roſe up and ſaid. <hi>Let Ambaſſadors be immediately ſent to all the Kingdoms in</hi> Europe, <hi>with Two Propoſals. The firſt, That if Colour be the cauſe of Slavery, they will take notice of the Red Beards for the ſake of</hi> Judas, <hi>and paſs by the Blacks on account of one of the three Kings that came to</hi> Bethlem. <hi>And ſince Cats and Dogs of that colour ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hateful, it will be but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:98488:53"/>there be no Men nor Women of it, and let him in our Name propoſe means for the ſpeedy deſtruction of all Fox heads with their Appurtenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The ſecond Propoſal is, that they mix their Breed with ours, and blending their Brightneſs with our Sootineſs, produce a mungril Race, that ſo Swarthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs may become Faſhionable; being ſufficiently war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the clearneſs of the</hi> Garmans <hi>and</hi> Flem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings, <hi>who have Embroiled and Distracted the World, ſtained ſo many Fields with Blood, and filled ſo many Nations with Rebellions and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies; but particularly let them remember the</hi> French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens <hi>yellow Beards.</hi>
               <note place="margin">It is a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom in <hi>Spain</hi> to Sneeze at the Blacks by way of contempt.
<hi>England</hi> in the year <hi>1640.</hi> This was ſpoke in the Perſon of K. <hi>Ch.</hi> the
<hi>I.</hi> in whoſe time it was writ.</note> 
               <hi>As for our Ambaſſadors, let them take this Advice along with them, that if the</hi> * <hi>People Sneeze at them they may take Snuff for their comfort and ſhall anſwer, God Bleſs us; beſtowing the Prayer upon themſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The mighty Monarch of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe Iſland is the moſt Beautiful Mole upon the face of the Ocean, having Aſſembled his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſpoke to them as follows.
<q>My Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions are encompaſſed by the raging Sea, hemmed in and defended by the Waves; my Kingdomes, as to the Publick Worſhip are of the Reform'd Religion, but in their hearts they are Catholicks. I have engraft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Papal power upon the Regal, wear at once the Crown and Miter, and have two Heads, the Spiritual and the Temporal. I ſuſpect, tho it is not viſible, as Spiritual Schiſm among my Subjects, and that the City which holds St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Keys influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the private Councels in <hi>London.</hi> This is of ſo much the more dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:98488:53"/>by how much it is the more Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate. It is a great Eye-ſore to me to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Rebellious <hi>Hollanders</hi> grown up in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> I confeſs, mine and my Anceſtors jealouſie of the greatneſs of <hi>Spain,</hi> has raiſed them from a contemptible Spawn to a Bulk that exceeds the <hi>Britiſh</hi> Whale. I ſee them daily encroaching upon the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and am devoured by the Lice I bred. I know, moſt years they have rich Fleets from their ſtolen Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and ſometimes they ſnap all, or a conſiderable part of thoſe that belong to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> which brings them in ineſtimable Treaſure. By Land ſo many years continual exerciſe has made them Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, with the reputation of innumerable Victories; and their experience in obeying has rendered them fit to Command. By Sea their Ships are not to be counted, their Fortune is matchleſs, their Conduct not to be Paralelled, and their Reputation above their Neighbours. On the other ſide, I ſee my Neighbour the King of <hi>France</hi> (whom I hate upon antient grudges) aſpire to the Empire of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already got footing in <hi>Italy,</hi> being poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of Towns, favoured by ſome Princes, and in all appearance countenanced by the Pope. He is a Youth born and grown up amidſt Armes, and gain'd Triumphs with them when he was fitter to have played with Toyes. I now look upon his Subjects to be wholly united, ſince he has demoliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:98488:54"/>all the ſtrong holds of the <hi>Huguenots, Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans,</hi> and
<hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and veſted the power of the Government in the <hi>Catholicks</hi> alone: Neither do I on this account eſteem him the better Catholick, but believe him a crafty Polititian, and am perſwaded, he is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Time-ſerver, that he only aimes at his Intereſt, and believes in what he would have, not in that he adores; a Religion many fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low under the name of another, yet he diſſembles, becauſe his deſign being to work himſelf into the poſſeſſion of <hi>Naples</hi> and <hi>Milan,</hi> he thought it convenient to favour the Catholicks, as being infinitely the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger party; They are beholding to their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, not to their Doctrine. He pretends a Catholick zeal becauſe it is the beſt colour to diſguiſe his ambition of enlarging his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions in <hi>Italy,</hi> and he is a much behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Hypocriſie as to his Valor for his Conqueſts. In <hi>Germany</hi> by calling in the <hi>Sweeds,</hi> and ſtirring up the Electors of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony</hi> and
<hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and the Landtgrave of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> he has ſworn <hi>In verba Lutheri</hi> He laid hold of <hi>Calvins</hi> Conſcience to ſeize the Duke of
<hi>Lorrain</hi>'s Dominions; and thus he is a <hi>Janus</hi> in Religion, looking upon the
<hi>Turk</hi> with one Face, and upon the <hi>Pope</hi> with the other; Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> being made his inſtrument to wind him into that Court. This cauſes my Noſe to ſwell at him, becauſe I conſider, that for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing his ends he has made no account of
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> power, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> taken <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> up with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:98488:54"/>of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> deſpiſing <hi>England</hi> as if he were furniſhed with another wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Joan</hi> of <hi>Are,</hi> or Maid of <hi>Orleans.</hi> I have ſo ill a reliſh of all theſe actions that they ſet my Teeth on Edge, and the very air I breath is nauſeous; to which, adding the ſucceſs of the Iſle of <hi>Rhe,</hi> it cauſes a loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in my Memory. It occurs not to me with whom I can join in Confederacy to clip the Wings of theſe two Neighbours, unleſs with the<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> the 4th then young.</note> King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who is a Great, Rich, and Mighty Monarch, being Lord of the moſt Warlike Nations in the World, and in the prime of his Age; yet I cannot but take notice, that my Honour and Reputation are ingaged in reſtoring the <hi>Palatine;</hi> and I cannot expect it from the <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and conſequently muſt not hope it from the
<hi>Imperialiſts</hi> and <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by reaſon of the difference of Religion, and that the Proteſtants are already ſick of the <hi>Houſe of Austria.</hi> Beſides, I gueſs the King of <hi>Spain</hi> has not forgot my Journey to his Court, ſince I have not forgot my return to my own, the memory whereof is renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the attempt of my Ships upon <hi>Cadiz.</hi> I would willingly reduce the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> to his former bounds, for like a Flood, he is ſwollen above his Banks, and has ſpread himſelf over all <hi>Europe;</hi> and at the ſame time would pull back the <hi>Dutch</hi> to what they were. It is your parts to adviſe what methods will be moſt proper for this under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking; but at the ſame time you are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:98488:55"/>that I am not only reſolved, but eager to go my ſelf in Perſon, becauſe I am of opinion, that a Prince who being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in a neceſſary War, does not himſelf lead his People, rather condemns his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to carry Armes, than makes Soldiers of them, and they being thus drove like Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minals, ſuffer more then they Act; whence it comes, they expect their Liberty, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge no leſs by being overcome than by overcoming. There is as much difference betwixt leading and ſending of Armies, as betwixt jeſt and earneſt, as appears by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Anſwer in relation to the Public without medling with my ſafety; and let me hear nothing in your opinions that looks like Self-Intereſt. Inform my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, do not perplex it.</q> This ſaid, they all looked upon one another with an awful ſilence, and after conſulting together in private, the Speaker returned this Anſwer.
<q>Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, Great Sir, has contrived ſo to place your Queſtion, that you have taught us how to Anſwer; an Art highly to be valued by Kings, becauſe it creates perſpicuity and a good underſtanding. Truth is but one, it is plain and clear, few words expreſs it, multiplicity confounds it; it breaks little ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, falſhood leaves none unbroken. The Reflections you have made on the King of <hi>France</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> are worthy your Royal conſideration. The imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger requires a manly and ſpeedy reſolution. The King of
<hi>Spain</hi> is at this time the only
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:98488:55"/>Confederate can promote your deſigns, and will be the more effectual if you joyn with him in Perſon to cruſh theſe two troubleſome Neighbours. And your Majeſty may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, there is as great diſtance betwixt Acting and Commanding, as is betwixt Words and Deeds. I confeſs your Heirs are too tender to be forſaken. But it is a leſs evil to leave them young, then Childiſhly to bear them company being a Father.</q> Scarce had he uttered theſe Words, when an old decrepit Senator, whoſe griſle clotted Beard covered all his Breaſt, his head hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down, and the hunch of his back through Age riſing above it, lifting himſelf up by the help of his ſtaff ſaid.
<q>There is no doubt but it is a great raſhneſs to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> adviſe his Kingdoms ſwarm with concealed Catholicks, whoſe number is known to be great, but ſuſpected to be much greater. Your Majeſty has Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects fit to be entruſted with ſuch an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, let an Army of our own Religion be ſent under the Command of the Chief Men who are ſuſpected to be Catholicks: Thus their Allegiance will be ſecured abroad, and fewer Enemies will remain at home. Do not venture your Perſon in which we venture our all, and which alone ſecures all; for, from the Speakers opinion I gather he Plots like a Papiſt, and does not adviſe like a Councellor.</q> The whole Aſſembly fell into confuſion, and in this diſorder the Hour began, and the King changing colour
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:98488:56"/>ſaid:
<q>You two inſtead of Adviſing have Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted me. One ſays, if I go not abroad in Perſon my Enemies will deprive me of my Kingdom. The other, that if I go it will be taken away by my Subjects, ſo that you will have me ſtand more in awe of my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects than of my Enemies. The Condition I am reduced to is Deplorable. It remains, that every one of you within 24 hours, lay before me by whoſe and by what means I am reduced to this paſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> naming Perſons and Cauſes without ſparing one another; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I ſhall ſuſpect you all, for the blame lies only among you that adviſe me; for I am now reſolved to attend my Affairs both at home and abroad. The King of <hi>France</hi> goes abroad without having Iſſues or hopes of it, and leaves a Kingdom divided on ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral accounts, the Nobility ſtained with the Blood of
<hi>Montmorency,</hi> the <hi>Huguenots</hi> ſuppreſt, but not without thoughts of revenge, the Country eaten up with Taxes, and the whole Kingdom groaning under the Oppreſſion of the Prime Miniſter; and you would have me who have Iſſue, and leſs Obſtacles to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct me, ſtay to rock and play with my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> are become formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable becauſe I have lived at home at my eaſe, if I appear not abroad they will be my ruin. If I ſtay for fear of my Subjects, I encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage them to contemn me. If once my Enemies are aſſured I cannot go abroad, I ſhall not be able to ſecure my ſelf againſt them, and if I go abroad and periſh, at
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:98488:56"/>leaſt I ſhall gain the Honour of the Attempt, and prevent the Scandal of Cowardice. That King who acts not himſelf in defence of his Crown, furniſhes them with an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe who do not aſſiſt him. It will be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt to puniſh thoſe that follow his Example, for he cannot be Judge of the Crime he taught, nor condemn what was learnt of him by thoſe who imitate him in forſaking the Defence of their Country. Be gone all of you immediately, and conſult accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to your Duty what is beſt for my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, preferring it before your own Lives, and my Quiet, for I promiſe the more ſharp the truth you deliver ſhall be, the better I will look upon it; and do not perplex me with the pretence of carrying all the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity along with me, for Experience demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, that no Man ever aſſembled them in an Army, but he loſt them and himſelf. The Rings meaſured by the Buſhel at <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> teſtifie it to the unſpeakable ſorrow of <hi>Rome.</hi> So the Wood of <hi>Pavia</hi> made the Sepulcher of all the <hi>French</hi> Nobility, and of their Kings Liberty. So the
<hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armada under the Duke of <hi>Medina Sidonia,</hi> which coming to invade this Kingdom, enriched the Shoars with its Wreck. And ſo King <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> who loſt his Nobility, his Crown, and his Life in <hi>Africk.</hi> The Nobility united cauſes Confuſion, and occaſions Ruin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know not how to Command, and will not Obey, and conſequently their Pride breaks an Military Diſcipline. I will take
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:98488:57"/>with me a few that have gained Experience, the reſt ſhall ſtay to be a Check to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs of the Multitude, and a Curb to Mutiniers. I have Occaſion for ſuch Men as think they cheat me in expoſing their Lives for Six-pence a day, not for thoſe who having exhauſted my Treaſure that they might go, claim a Title to my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue becauſe they went. It were good that all the Nobility were Trained, yet it were not ſafe. Private Perſons muſt not Arm Madmen, nor Kings the Nobility. Take this along with you by way of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and there will be the leſs to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract your Conſultations, and my Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion will the ſooner take effect.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopanti</hi> in Councel for embroil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom,</hi> and drain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its Wealth.</note>At <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> a City of
<hi>Macedonia,</hi> ſeated at the bottom of the Gulph to which it gives its Name, and ſubject to the Emperor of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> by the appointment of Rabbi <hi>Saadias,</hi> Rabbi
<hi>Racabarbaniel,</hi> Rabbi <hi>Salomon,</hi> and Rabbi <hi>Niſin,</hi> was held a general Aſſembly of the Deputies of all the <hi>Jews</hi> in <hi>Europe.</hi> Thither reſorted for the Synagogue at <hi>Venice</hi> Rabbi <hi>Samuel</hi> and Rabbi <hi>Maimon,</hi> for that of
<hi>Raguſa</hi> Rabbi <hi>Abenezra,</hi> for that of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> Rabbi
<hi>Jacob,</hi> for that of <hi>Rome</hi> Rabbi <hi>Chaminiel,</hi> for that of <hi>Leghorn</hi> Rabbi <hi>Cerſonni,</hi> for that of <hi>Roan</hi> Rabbi <hi>Gavirol,</hi> for that of
<hi>Prague</hi> Rabbi <hi>Moſche,</hi> for that of <hi>Vienna</hi> Rabbi <hi>Berchai,</hi> for that of <hi>Amſterdam</hi> Rabbi <hi>Mier Armaac,</hi> for that of <hi>Oran</hi> Rabbi
<hi>Aſepha,</hi> for the <hi>Jews</hi> in Maſquerade, who Trade under
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:98488:57"/>the diſguiſe of the Chriſtian Habit and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, Rabbi <hi>David Bar Nachman.</hi> With theſe joined the <hi>Monopanti,</hi> a Republican People inhabiting certain Iſlands, who lying in the <hi>Black Sea,</hi> betwixt <hi>Moſcovy</hi> and <hi>Tartary,</hi> are politickly maintained againſt their fierce Neighbours, rather by Cunning than force of Arms or ſtrength of Fortifications. The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives are Men of inextricable Subtlety, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough-paced in Hypocriſie, abſolute Maſters of Diſſimulation, and of ſo deceitful a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, that all Religions and Nations take them for their own. Trade gives them mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of Faces, and charges their Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and Intereſt ſhifts their Souls. They are Governed by a Prince called <hi>Pragas Chin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collos.</hi> By his Order there came to this San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim Six of the moſt Learned Men in the Doctrine of Raking and Griping, the firſt was called <hi>Philorgiros,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Erictotheos,</hi> the third <hi>Danipe,</hi> the fourth <hi>Arpi Trotono,</hi> the fifth <hi>Pacaſmazo,</hi> and the ſixth <hi>Daper Bazalas.</hi> The Aſſembly ſeated themſelves orderly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Preheminence of each Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue, giving the Firſt Seat to the <hi>Monopanti</hi> in Courteſie as they were Strangers. After Silence was made, Rabbi
<hi>Saadias</hi> having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated the Pſalm, <hi>In exitu Iſrael de Egypto,</hi> made the following Speech. <hi>We the firſt Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the World, who are become the Offcaſt of all Ages, and diſperſed Multitude, living in Captivity and miſerable Contempt, perceiving the whole World entangled in the inextricable Snares of Diſcord, have aſſembled our ſelves together to
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:98488:58"/>conſult our Intereſt amidſt the preſent Tumults, that we may raiſe our ſelves upon the Ruines of all others. I conf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Captivity, Plagues, and Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy are our Inheritance. Fears and Jealouſies are the firſt begotton of our Underſtandings, and we were ever Malecontents againſt God, ever valuing the Diety we made, before that which made us. From the firſt beginning his government was irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to us, and we followed the interpretation of the Devil in oppoſition to his Law. When his Omnipotency governed us, we rebelled, when he gave us Governours we diſobeyed.</hi> Samuel <hi>who governed in his Name was thought burdenſom, and we gathering an ungrateful Aſſembly, though God was our King, asked of God another King. He gave us</hi> Saul, <hi>and him a Tyrannical Right over us, declaring he would make Slaves of our Children, and take away our Eſtates to give to his Servants; and he aggravated this puniſhment, ſaying, he would not take him from us tho we ſhould beg it of him. He ſaid to</hi> Samuel, <hi>that it was him they deſpiſed, not the Prophet, or his Sons. To fulfil his Curſe, that</hi> Saul
<hi>continues among us at all times, in all Places, and under ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Names. Since then he oppreſſes us with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous and miſerable Thraldom in all Kingdoms and Commonwealths, and God permits every King ſhould be a</hi> Saul <hi>to us who left God for</hi> Saul; <hi>Our Nation remained Criminal in the ſight of all Men, all caſt it from themſelves, all retain, and all are aſhamed of retaining it. We reſide not in any place, but whether we came expelled from another. We reſt no where, but where they are deſirous to caſt us out, and all dread we ſhould be drove
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:98488:58"/>upon them. We cannot but own there is no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity between our Words and our Actions, and that our Mouth and our Heart never were united in adoring the ſame God; our Mouth always cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon the God of Heaven, our Heart ever gave Idolatrous Adoration to God and Uſury. Being under the conduct of</hi> Moſes, <hi>when he went up to the Mount for the Law, we made it appear, that the Religion of our Souls was Gold, and any Creature framed thereof. There we adored our own Jewels in the Calf, and our Avarice took for its Deity the reſemblance of the ſucking Cattle. We admit not of God in any other Metal, and in this we receive any Inſect for a God. He well underſtood the Diſeaſe that cauſed our inſatiable Thirſt, who made us drink up our Idol reduced to Powder. A mighty Vengeance followed this Crime; yet tho it ſlew many thouſands, it was a warning to few, for whereas God afterwards did for us all that we could ask, ſtill he did nothing but what we grew weary of. He ſtretched out the Clouds like a Canopy to cover us in the Deſert from the ſcorching heat of the day. He ſtrengthned with the fiery Pillar the weak light of the Moon and Stars, that they aſſiſted with its glittering motion might overcome the darkneſs of the night, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Sun in its abſence. He commanded the Wind to ſhower down our Harveſt, and diſpoſed the Regions of the Air into wonderful Barns, powring thence our Suſtenance ready dreſſed in the Manna with all the ſeaſoning every Pallat could deſire. He cauſed the Quails deſcending like Rain to become Game and Nets for our Entertainment. He diſſolved the immovable Rocks into running
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:98488:59"/>Streams, and cauſed Springs to guſh from the Stones to recreate our Thirſt. He dried up the bottom of the Sea into an eaſie Road for our Feet, and raiſed the Waters perpendicular, heaping up their ſmoothneſs into Liquid Walls, detaining in a ſecure Structure the Waves and Billows, which became a ſtreight way for our Forefathers, and a Sepulchre to</hi> Pharaoh <hi>and his Army. His Word raiſed a Vermin, and liſted Frogs, Flies and Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſts in his Army for our ſervice. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo weak, whereof God doth not make up invincible Hoſts againſt Tyrants. With ſuch ſmall Souldiers he vanquiſhed the formidable Enemies Squadrons, glittering in their Steel Armour, vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious in the bearings of their Shields, and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in the Feathers of their Creſts. Theſe wonderful Mercies which our King and Prophet</hi> David <hi>celebrated in the</hi> 105th Pſalm, <hi>which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins</hi> Horula Adonai, <hi>were requited by our Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy and Ingr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>titude with a loathing and diſlike of our Food, and with Oblivion of the Way open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed through the Waves of the Sea. Many times God chaſtiſes with what he gives, and rewards with what he refuſes. Such Forefathers are a ſcandalous Genealogy of our Perverſneſs. We are generally looked upon as obſtinate in endleſs hopes, whereas in reality we are the moſt deſperate People in Nature: We are the</hi> Ne plus ultra <hi>of Incredulity; and hopes nor is any thing to be hoped of us. Becauſe</hi> Moſes <hi>ſtayed a little on the Mount, we deſpaired of him, and asked a God of</hi> Aaron. <hi>The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why it is ſaid we are obſtinate in everlaſting hope is, becauſe we have ſo many Ages expected
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:98488:59"/>the Meſſiah; but neither did we receive him in Chriſt, nor do we expect him in any other. The cauſe of our ſaying always, that he is to come, is not that we deſire him, or believe it, but by theſe delays to diſguiſe our being the Fool that begins the</hi>
13th Pſalm, <hi>ſaying in his Heart, There is no God. The ſame ſays he, who denies him that came, and waits for him that is not to come. This is the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of our Heart, and rightly conſidered it is the</hi> Quare <hi>of the</hi> 2d Pſalm, Fremuerunt gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; populi meditati ſunt inania adverſus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum, &amp; adverſus Chriſtum ejus. <hi>So that we ſay we always hope, to conceal our always de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpairing. Of the Law of</hi> Moſes <hi>we retain only the Name, giving it to the Exceptions the</hi> Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mudiſts, <hi>have forged to belye the Scripture, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guize the Prophecies, invalidate the Precepts, and diſpoſe Conſciences to Worldly ends, inſtructing our Atheiſtical Inclinations with Seditious Politicks for the conveniency of a Civil Life, and adopting us of Sons of</hi> Iſrael <hi>Sons of Mammon. When we had a Law we kept it not. Now we keep it, it is no Law, farther than in the very ſound of the three Letters. It was neceſſary to declare what we were, to excuſe what we are, and to promote what we aim to be, advancing our ſelves upon the wild Extravagancies, which like a Frenzy poſſeſs all the Earth; for now not only the Hereticks riſe in Arms againſt their Enemies the Catholicks, but the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks themſelves in hoſtile manner invade one another. The Proteſtants of</hi> Germany <hi>for many years paſt have ſtrugled for a H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>retick Emperor, and in this they are favoured by the moſt Chriſtian King, who acts as if he were not ſo, and connives
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:98488:60"/>at</hi> Calvin <hi>and</hi> Luther. <hi>The Catholick King op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes them all, to keep in the Houſe of</hi> Auſtria <hi>the Supream Dignity of the Roman Eagles. The</hi> Hollanders <hi>encouraged by being ſucceſsful Traitors, aſpire to raiſe their Treaſon into a Monarchy, and of Rebellious Subjects to the King of</hi> Spain, <hi>dare preſume to become his Competitors. They wreſted from him what he bad in them, and they proceed rob him of what is ſo far from them, as</hi> Brazil <hi>and</hi> India, <hi>deſigning to extend their Conqueſts over his Crown. We have been no ſmall Inſtruments in promoting theſe Uſurpations, by means of the Sham Chriſtians, whom under diſguiſe of the</hi> Portugueſe <hi>Language we have applied to undermine him, upon pretence of being his Subjects. All or moſt of the Princes of</hi> Italy <hi>have harboured the</hi> French <hi>in their Dominions, pretending they read the Popes inclinations in his Looks, and interpreting his ſilent Toleration for a poſitive Command,</hi> Ex motu pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prio. <hi>The King of</hi> France <hi>has practiſed an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beard or Stratagem againſt the Monarch of</hi> Spain,<note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> and Queen Mother of <hi>France,</hi> upon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt went into <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> where they had Penſions from the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> who entertained them to breed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions in
<hi>France.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>diſcharging upon him all his Family under the Title of Malecontents, that he might conſume the Pay of his Army in Penſions and Proſents. When was it ever known that a King made Ammunition of his Mothers and Brothers Teeth againſt another, that they might eat him up by morſels. It is a beggerly invention, and yet moſt pernicious. To wage War by Mumping, looks more like jeſt than earneſt. We have Synagogues in the Dominions of all theſe Princes, where we are the principal Element in compoſing of this Confuſion. At</hi> Roan <hi>we are the Purſe of</hi> France <hi>againſt</hi> Spain, <hi>and of</hi> Spain <hi>againſt</hi> France. <hi>In</hi> Spain, <hi>diſguiſing our Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion by our Habit, we ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that Monarch with
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:98488:60"/>the Stock we have at</hi> Amſterdam <hi>amidſt his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who make a greater advantage by ordering us to delay the payment of the Bills, than he does by receiving them. This is indeed an extra ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Riddle, to wit, to ſerve and ruin Friends and Enemies with the ſame Money, and to cauſe him that pays it to make his advantage over him that receives it. The ſame we do in</hi> Germany, Italy, <hi>and</hi> Conſtantinople, <hi>and we have knit this indiſſoluble knot by placing the ſupply every one expects in the hands of his greateſt Enemy. For we furniſh Money, as he that lends upon Intereſt to one that plays and looſes, that he may looſe the more. I do not deny but the</hi> Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panti <hi>are the Boxkeepers of</hi> Europe, <hi>who furniſh Cards, Dice and Candles, and at length the Box runs away with all the Gold and Silver, leaving the Gameſters nothing but Noiſe, Ruine, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Revenge, which they encourage, that their Gaming Houſe, which is the end of all Men, may never have an end. Thus far they are the true Copies of our Original. True it is they have much the advantage of us in the manner of worming themſelves in, becauſe they are the</hi> Jews <hi>of the</hi> New Teſtament, <hi>as we are of the</hi> Old, <hi>for as we did not believe that</hi> Jeſus <hi>was the Meſſiah that came, ſo they believing that</hi> Jeſus <hi>was the Meſſiah already come, they let him ſlip through their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences in ſuch a manner it ſeems he never came to, or for them. The</hi> Monopanti <hi>believe him, as a grave Author ſays we expect him:</hi> Auream, &amp; Gemmatam Hieruſalem expectabant. <hi>A Hieruſalem of Gold and Precious Stones. Both we and the through differing Principles and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Means tend to the ſame end, which is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:98488:61"/>Chriſtianity which we would not receive, and they after receiving have rejected. And this is he reaſon we have met to join a Confederacy of Malice and Deceit. This Synagogue has taken it into conſideration, that Gold and Silver are the true Sons of the Earth which make War againſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, not only with an hundred hands, but with as many as dig, caſt, coin, gather, tell, receive, and ſteal them. They are two Subterranean De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, yet beloved of all Mortals. Two ſuch Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, that the greater Body they have, they have alſo the more Spirit. No Eſtate or Condition de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſes them, and if any Law condemn, the Lawyers and Interpreters of it bring them off. He that thinks it an undervaluing to dig them, values him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon gathering them. He who is too great to ask of him that keeps, courteouſly receives them of him that offers. And he who thinks it too great a labour to earn them, eſteems it an art to ſteal them. He that ſays, I will not have them, at the ſame time means, Give me them. And he who cries, I receive nothing, ſpeaks truth, becauſe he ſnatches all. As it were a falſhood ſhould the Sea pretend it does not ſwallow up the Springs and Brooks, ſince drinking up the Rivers which ſuck them up, it alſo licks up Brooks and Springs; ſo great Men prevaricate when they ſay they do not receive from the Poor and Beggars, whereas they devour the Rich, who ſwallow up the Poor and Beggars. The Premiſes being granted, it will be moſt proper to level the Stroaks of our Intereſt at Kings, Commonwealths, and Prime Miniſters, in whoſe Stomachs all the reſt cauſe a Surfeit, which being by us ſtirred up will prove a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:98488:61"/>Lethargy, or Apoplexy in their Heads. Let the</hi> Monopanti <hi>have the preheminence of giving their Opinion firſt, what method they judge moſt proper for our advantage.</hi> They having buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed about their ſly thoughts from one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, agreed that
<hi>Pacaſmazo,</hi> as the moſt fluent of Tongue, and abounding in Words, ſhould ſpeak for them all, which he did in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. <hi>The Goods of the World belong to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious, and Fortune follows the Diſſemblers and the Bold. Crowns and Scepters are ſooner uſurped and ſnatched, than inherited or deſerved. He who in Temporal Preferments is the worſt among the Wicked, is the moſt deſerving without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and grows till he ſuffers himſelf to be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done in Villany, for in all Ambitious Attempts, Juſtice and Honeſty make Tyrants Criminals. No ſooner theſe begin to uſe moderation, but they depoſe themſelves. If they will continue their Tyranny, they muſt not ſuffer any ſigns to appear abroad that may prove them ſo. The Fire that burns a Houſe, caſting out the Smoak, calls People to quench it with Water. Let every one take as much of this Diſcourſe to himſelf as ſuits with his purpoſe. Money is the true Circe, which changes into ſundry forms all that come near or fall in love with it. We our ſelves are the Example. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney is a diſguiſed Deity, which in no place has any publick Altar, but is privately adored in all parts. It has no particular Temple, becauſe it ſlides into all Churches. Riches is an univerſal Sect, in which moſt Souls agree; and Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is an Arch Heretick beloved by all Politicians, and the Reconciler of all Differences in Opinion
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:98488:62"/>and Humour. We therefore perceiving he is the moſt wonderful Magician and Negromancer, have choſen him for our North Star, and make him our Loadſtone to point to that Pole that we may not ſtray from our Courſe. This we perform ſo artificially, that we leave him to the end we may have him, and deſpiſe him that we may gather him. This we learned of the deceitful Pump, which by being empty fills it ſelf, with what it has not; attracts what others have, and eaſily ſucks and dreins the full with its own emptineſs. We are the very reſemblance of Gunpowder, which being ſmall, black, and cloſe rammed, gathers vaſt ſtrength and ſwiftneſs from its cloſe impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment. We do the miſchief before the noiſe can be heard, and as we open one Eye and ſhut the other to take aim, we carry all before us in the twinkling of an Eye. Our Houſes are like the Barrels of Guns, they are diſcharged at the Keys, and charged at the Mouth. Yet though we are ſuch, we have Countenances and Manners that ſuit with all Men, and therefore we ſeem not Strangers to any Sect or Nation. The Turk takes our Hair for a Turbant, the Chriſtian for a Hat, the Moore for a Cap, and you for a Veil. We admit not of the Name of a Kingdom, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, or any other, but only that of</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopanti.
<hi>We yield all Titles to Kings and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths, we take from them the power ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from the Vanity of thoſe noiſy Words. We lay our Deſign that they may be Lords over the World, and we over them. To attain ſo glorious an end, we have not found any to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with in Confederacy on equal Terms, like you,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:98488:62"/>who are at preſent the ſharpers of</hi> Europe; <hi>you only want our quality to compleat the ſubverting of all, which we offer you entire, by way of Conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion or Infection, to be tranſmitted by means of an infernal device found out againſt Chriſtians by us here preſent; which is, that as Treacle is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the ſharp poiſon of the Viper, becauſe it is the moiſture that goes the quickeſt and moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly to the Heart; for which reaſon being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with many Simples of Efficacious Virtue, it conveys them to the Heart to defend it againſt Poiſon, which is the deſign of the Medicine; ſo we have invented a counter-Treacle to convey Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to the Heart, by falling upon the Vertues and good works that go to it, and to carry to the Soul the Vices, Abominations and Errors, which on theſe Vehicles will ſlip into it. If you reſolve upon this Alliance, we will give you the Receipt, with the weight and number of Ingredients, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Apothecaries well verſed in the compoſition, in the contriving whereof,</hi> Danipe, Alkemiaſtos, <hi>and I, have taken great pains, and our labour is nothing inferior to the</hi> Trochisks <hi>of the Viper. Be ruled by our Pragas, for you need not ceaſe to be</hi> Jews, <hi>and at the ſame time will learn to be</hi> Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panti. At the very uttering of theſe words the Hour had its effect, and Rabbi
<hi>Maimon</hi> one of thoſe that came from the Synagogue of <hi>Venice</hi> riſing up, and putting aſide with his hand a Fathom and a half of Snout, that he might come the cloſer to the Ear of Rabbi <hi>Saadias,</hi> whiſpered theſe words <hi>Rabbi, I ſmell a Rat in that word, be govern'd, we muſt keep a ſharp Eye upon theſe Fellows, for
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:98488:63"/>to me they look like famely</hi> Pharaos <hi>and ſubtile en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachers. Saadias</hi> replied, <hi>Now at length I am convinced they are the very Manna of inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, for they taſt as every one would have them. The beſt way is to ſay little, and give them a bait in the Trap as to Republican Mice. Chriſtotheus</hi> ſeeing the numbling Dialogue, ſaid to <hi>Philar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giros</hi> and <hi>Danipe. I ſmoke the Jealouſie of the wicked</hi> Jews: <hi>Let every Man of the</hi> Monopanti <hi>give himſelf a lick of the Golden Calf, and they will all fall upon their Knees.</hi> They all run up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Snares and Contrivances againſt one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Rabbi <hi>Saadias,</hi> to amuſe the <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panti,</hi> ſaid, <hi>We look upon you as diſcoverers of the</hi> Land of promiſe, <hi>and the true baſis of our deſigns, that we may be united in a miſchievous body, it will be requiſite we conſult the methods, and conclude and ſign Articles at our next meeting, which we appoint three days hence. Pacaſmazo</hi> covering his Snake Skin with Doves Feathers, ſaid, <hi>The time was ſufficient, and the reſolution diſcreet; but that it was requiſite, exact ſecrecy ſhould be obſerved.</hi> Then taking out a Book bound in Sheeps skin with the Wooll on, which was curiouſly interwoven and wrought with Gold Thread, he gave it to <hi>Saadias,</hi> ſaying, <hi>This Jewel we give you as a Pledge.</hi> He took it, and asked, <hi>Whoſe works are theſe? Pacaſmazo</hi> anſwered,
<hi>The works of our words. The Author is</hi> Nicolas Matchiavel, <hi>who compoſed the thorough Baſe to our Trebel.</hi> The <hi>Jews</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively looking upon them, and particularly obſerving the binding in Sheeps skin; Rabbi <hi>Aſapha,</hi> who was Deputy for <hi>Oran</hi> ſaid, <hi>This
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:98488:63"/>is ſome of the Wooll the</hi> Spaniards <hi>tell us in their Proverb, which ſays, they that go to fetch it are fleeced before they return.</hi> Thus they parted, both parties contriving to meet again like the Steel and Flint for to batter, bruize, and beat one another to pieces, till they ſtruck fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all the World, for founding the new Sect of
<hi>Monetiſm,</hi> changing the name of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts,</hi> into that of Moneymongers, or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The general Aſſembly of all Nations for redreſs of grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note>The Subjects of Princes, Common-wealths, Kings and Emperors aſſembled together at <hi>Liege,</hi> a Neuter Country, to conſult about their Affairs, redreſs their Grievances, vent their Spleen, and breath out their thoughts before ſtifled under the fear of Sovereign Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. There were people of all Nations, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and Qualities. The number was ſo great it looked more like an Army than an Aſſembly, for which reaſon they made choice of the open Fields to meet in. On the one hand it was ſurpriſing to behold the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful variety of Garbs and Countenances; on the other the Ears were Confounded, and Attention it ſelf deceived by the ſtrange diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Languages. The voices ſeemed to rend the Air, and reſounded in the ſame manner, as when in the heat of harveſt time, the Fields ring with the indefatigable noiſe of Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. The moſt piercing cry was, that raiſed by the Women tearing their Throats with Actions altogether diſtracted. All was full of tumultuous Madneſs, and raging Diſcord. The Republicans would be govern'd by Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:98488:64"/>and the Subjects of Princes were for ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting themſelves into Common-wealths. This controverſie ſet a Noble <hi>Savoyard</hi> and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner of
<hi>Genoua</hi> together by the Eares. The <hi>Savoyard</hi> complained, <hi>That his Duke was the perpetual motion, and conſumed his Subjects with continual Wars, to hear up his Dominions which are ever ready to ſink betwixt</hi> France <hi>and</hi> Spain. <hi>That his ſafety conſiſted in embroiling the two Kings at the Expence of his Subjects; to the end, that they two being employed againſt one another, neither of them might ſwallow him, ſince both thoſe Princes alternatively, firſt one and then the other Conquer and Defend him; all which the Subjects pay for, being never allowed any reſpite to breath. When</hi> France <hi>attacks,</hi> Spain <hi>ſupports him; and when</hi> Spain <hi>invades,</hi> France <hi>defends him; and whereas, neither protects him for his ſake, but to obſtruct the others enlarging his Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion by that acceſſion, and becoming a nearer and more formidable Neighbour, the Defence is often as fatal, if not more to the Subjects, than the Invaſion. The Duke retains a ſecret ambition to be thought the Founder of the Liberty of</hi> Itatly; <hi>bearing before him, the better to draw to his party the See of</hi> Rome. <hi>The Hiſtory of</hi> Amadee, <hi>ſurnamed the</hi> Pacifick,
<hi>becauſe ſome Perſons impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Malicious, have ſuſpected he deſigns to reduce the Pope to his bare ſtock of Pardons in indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. The Duke is Diſceaſed of the Diſtemper of King of</hi> Cyprus, <hi>is perplexed with the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of having been Lord of</hi> Geneva, <hi>and grows ſick with the deſire of being Supream among the</hi> Italian
<hi>Princes. All theſe motives are ſpurs
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:98488:64"/>to his Ambition, which rather ſtands in need of a Curb; and for theſe Reaſons, I come to propoſe, that</hi> Savoy <hi>and</hi> Piemont <hi>may be formed into a</hi> Common wealth, <hi>where Juſtice and Wiſdom Govern, and Liberty Reigns. What Liberty Reigns?</hi> Quoth the <hi>Genoeſe,</hi> Damming himſelf to the pit of Hell. <hi>Thou art certainly mad, and having never lived in a</hi> Common-wealth, <hi>doſt not know the miſery and ſlavery that attends it. All the Politicks in the World will never make us ſet our Horſes together. I who am a</hi> Genoeſe, <hi>Born under that</hi> Common-wealth, <hi>which by its nearneſs and the great contentions betwixt us is well acquainted with you, am come to perſwade your Duke, with the aſſiſtance of us the Commons, to make himſelf King of</hi> Genoua;
<hi>and if he accepts not of it, I will go make the ſame offer to the King of</hi> Spain; <hi>and from him to the King of</hi> France, <hi>and ſo from one to another till I find one that will take pitty on us. Tell me, thou un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful wretch, to the goodneſs of God towards you, in making you the Subjects of a Prince: Have you ever conſidered how much eaſier it is to obey one, than many met together in one room, but as divided in Manners, Inclinations, Opinions and deſigns. Doſt not thou obſerve, Monſter, that in</hi> Common-wealths, <hi>the Government being An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual and Succeſſive through ſeveral Families, it is conſequently under an awe, and Juſtice is not free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtributed, for fear leaſt thoſe who ſhall Govern the next twelve Months or three Years ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge themſelves on him that governed before? If a Republican Senate conſiſt of many it is all confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; if of few, it only ſerves to corrupt the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:98488:65"/>and excellency of Unity. Nor is this remedied by the Duke, who either has no abſolute Power, or laſts but for a time appointed. If the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be equally divided betwixt the Nobility and Commons, they make up an Aſſembly of Dogs and Cats; For the one part propoſes Snaping and Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the other anſwers, Scratching and Claw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. If they be Rich and Poor, the Rich contemn the Poor, and the Poor envy the Rich. Conſider now what will be the iſſue of Envy and Contempt. If the Power reſt in the Commons, neither will the Nobles be able to endure them, nor they bear not being ſuch. Now if only the Nobility rules, I can compare the Subjects to nothing but the Damned in Hell, and ſuch are we the Commons of</hi> Genoa: <hi>Nay, could I ſay worſe of our condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I ſhould think this too little.</hi> Genoa <hi>has as many Common-wealths as Nobles, and as many Slaves as Commons; and all theſe Common-wealths meet in one Pallace, only to reckon up our ſtock, that they may ſqueeze us either by enhancing or abaſing the value of money, and as if they were informers againſt our eſtates, their continual ſtudy is to depreſs us into Poverty. They make uſe of us like Sponges, ſending us abroad into the World, that plunging in Trade, we may ſuck Riches, and when they perceive us ſwollen with caſh, they ſqueeze us out for their own uſe. Tell me then, thou Curſed abominable</hi> Savoyard, <hi>what it is you aim at by your Treachery, what can be your infernal deſign? Do not you perceive that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Commonalty tranſmit their Power to Kings and Princes, in whom being removed from the Prince of the former, and lowneſs of the latter
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:98488:65"/>it compoſes a ſupream head, authorized by a Peaceful and diſintereſſed Majeſty, over which the Nobility dares not inſult, and under which the Commonalty does not groan.</hi> They had fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len ſoul of one another, had not they been prevented by the muttering of a drove of Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlators, driven by a Rabble of Women, who with open mouths confounded them, Shreik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and threatned to fall on with their Teeth. One of them of ſuch Tranſcendent beauty that it was increaſed by the hideouſneſs of paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is an Affection that adds Deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty even to the fierceneſs of Lions, delivered her ſelf in theſe words. <hi>Tyrants, for what reaſon have you alone made Laws againſt Women without their conſent, according to your own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, whereas they are an equal part of the two wherein Human Government conſiſts. You ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude us the Schools meerly through Envy, becauſe we ſhall exceed you; and deny us the uſe of Arms for fear you ſhould be Conquer'd by our Anger, as you are already by our Smiles. You have conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our ſelves the Supream Judges of Peace and War, and we ſuffer under your extravagancies. Adultery in us is a crime puniſhable with Death, and among you it is a meer Jeſt. You will have us be good, that you may be wicked, and require us Chaſt, that you may be Lewd. We have not a ſenſe but what you keep under hatches; you tye up our Feet, and Hoodwink our Eyes. If we look, you ſay we are impudent; if others look on us we are dangerous. And thus under colour of Modeſty you Condemn us to forfeit our Reaſon and Senſes. It is your Jealouſie, you Scoundrels, not
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:98488:66"/>our own weakneſs, that often perſwades us to act that againſt you, for which you are moſt watchful over us. More are made wicked by you, than would be ſo of themſelves. If you ſenſeleſs Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cals make your ſelves the forbidden fruit to us, it follows of neceſſity, we ſhall all become ſo many</hi> Eves <hi>againſt you. Very many are good when they are put into your hands, and you force them to be wicked; and you receive none ſo wicked, but moſt of you oblige them to be worſe. All your Gravity conſiſts in the wild hairineſs of your Faces; and he who thinks his Beard will make the bigeſt bruſh, thinks himſelf the ableſt Man; as if the ſtrength of the Brain lay in long Briſtles, which rather look like a Tail than a Head. This is the day theſe grievances muſt be redreſſed, either by allowing us a ſhare in Learning and Government, or by giving us a hearing, and doing us right a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Laws Eſtabliſhed; Enacting ſome more favourable for us, and repealing others that are prejudicial to us.</hi> A Doctor whoſe beard hung in daglocks down to his Heels, ſeeing the Women in a croud and bent upon miſchief, relying on his Eloquence, attempted to appeaſe them with theſe Words, <hi>It is not without much dread I undertake to oppoſe your ſentiments, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Reaſon it ſelf is oft overcome by Beauty, and Rhetorick is of no force compared with your Charmes. However, tell me, what law can you be entruſted with, ſince the firſt Woman proved her ſelf ſuch, by breaking the Law of God. With what ſafety can weapons be put into your Hands, ſince with an Apple, you ſtruck to the ground all the generation of</hi> Adam, <hi>not ſo much as thoſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:98488:66"/>that were hid in the diſtance of futurity eſcaping? You ſay all Laws are againſt you, this were truth, had you ſaid, you were againſt all Laws. What Power is there to compare to yours, for tho you do not judge according to the Laws ſtudying them, you judge the Laws by means of the Judges cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting them. If we make Laws, it is you that break them. If Judges govern the World, and Women the Judges; it is the Women that govern the World, and debauch them that govern it; for the Women they love are more prevalent with many than the Laws they read. What the Devil ſaid to the Woman took place with</hi> Adam, <hi>of that God ſaid to him. The influence of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil is great over Human Hearts, if he ſpeaks through the Mouth of one of you. Woman is a Rarity that ought to be feared and loved, and it is very hard to fear and love the ſame thing. He who loves only her, hates himſelf; and he who hates only her, hates Nature. What Law is there which your Tears will not blot out, and what Equity is of force againſt your Smiles? If we have Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments and Preferments, it is you that ſpend the Profits in your Dreſſes. You have but one Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent to quote, which is your Beauty; When did you ever urge it that it did not take place? Or, Whoever ſaw it that did not ſubmit? If we ſuffer our ſelves to be bribed, it is that we may bribe you. If we ſtrain the Laws, and incline Juſtice, it is for the moſt part becauſe we adviſe with your Charms; you run away with the Prize of the Villanies you command us to act, and we are left with the Scandal of Corrupt Judges. You envy us our Military Employments, whereas you are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:98488:67"/>to War for the happineſs of being left Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and we for being buried in Oblivion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Dead. You complain that Adultery is a Capital Crime in you, and not in us. Why you Charming White Devils, if one ſlip of yours Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honours Parents and Children, and ſtains a whole Generation, how can you fancy Death too ſervere a Puniſhment? whereas the Honour of many inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Perſons is infinitely valuable above the Life of a Criminal. But let us judge by your Works how you value the Penalty. You cannot count the Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries you are guilty of, becauſe they are innumer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and among us they are ſo rare we have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to count. Death is a Puniſhment that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters others from falling into the ſame Crime, but where does this appear by you? To complain of our guarding you, is to complain that we value you, for no Man takes pains to ſecure what he deſpiſes. By what I have ſaid it appears you are abſolute Ladies of all things, all things are ſubject to you; you enjoy Peace, and are the occaſion of War. If you would aks that which many of you want, ask for Moderation and Brains.</hi> Scarce was the Word Brains out of his Lips, when all the Women together diſcharged their Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry upon the Wretched Doctor in the Storm of Blows, Scatches, and Pinches, and ſo out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageouſly did they pull his Beard and Hair, that they left him as ſmooth as if he had been new Shaved, and looked more like an old Woman, than the Reverend Interpreter of the Law. They ahd quite ſtifled him, but that a multitude of People came in hearing he Noiſe and Outcries. Among them a
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:98488:67"/>French Monſieur, and an Italian Monſeignor, had already made known to one another their Diſpleaſure by ſome good Bangs, and ſaluted their Countenances with Cuffs, followed by Kicks and ſuch like Familiarities. The <hi>French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> fretted with Rage, and the
<hi>Italian</hi> foamed with Anger. <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Frenchmen</hi> flocked to them on all hands, the <hi>Germans</hi> interpoſed, and having with much difficulty appeaſed them, asked the cauſed of their Strife. The <hi>Frenchman</hi> gathering up with both Hands his Breeches, which in the Scruffle were fallen over his Legs, anſwered: <hi>All Nations are met here this day, to redreſs their Grievances, and I among the reſt was diſcourſing with others of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymen concerning the miſerable condition</hi> France <hi>is in at preſent, and how the</hi> French <hi>are oppreſt under the Tyranny of Cardinal</hi> Richlieu. <hi>I was laying open with what art he pretends the Kings Service, at the ſame time he degrades him. How he covers the Fox under the Purple Robe. How by Embroiling all Chriſtendom, he diverts all from looking into his Practices. How his Subtlety makes a Property of his Princes Favour. And how he had put the Power of Sea and Land, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Preferments, Armies and Fleets, into the hands of his Kindred and Confederates, defaming the Nobility, and raiſing the Unworthy. I was putting my Countrymen in mind how the Mareſchal</hi> D'Ancre <hi>was hacked and hewed in pieces, and called to their remembrance Monſieur</hi> de Luiſnes, <hi>and how yet our King cannot rid himſelf of Prime Miniſters, ſhewing how this laſt was the only Friend to the other two, whoſe Reputation he eſtabliſhed
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:98488:68"/>by blackning his own. I was diſcovering to them, how of late years, Traitors have hit upon the moſt pernicious Art that ever Hell invented, for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that to uſurp Kingdoms is become Treaſon, and that he who attempts it is puniſhed as a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the better of ſecure themſelves in their wicked Practices, they uſurp the Kings, calling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Favourites, and thus inſtead of being pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed as Traitors, they are adored as Kings of Kings. I was propoſing, do now propoſe, and will again propoſe in the general meeting, that for the perpetuating the Succeeſſion, eſtabliſhing of Kingdoms, and extirpating this Sect of Traitors, an inviolable and indiſpenſible Law ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, ordaining, That whatſoever King of</hi> France <hi>ſhall ſubject himſelf to a Favourite, he and his Heirs ſhall</hi> Ipſo facto, <hi>forfeit their Title to the Crown, and their Subjects be abſolved from their Oath of Allegiance, for the</hi> Salique <hi>Law, which excludes Femanes, does not prevent ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt a danger as this that cuts off Favourites. I added, that at the ſame time it ſhould be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, That whatſoever Subject under the Title preſumed to uſurp his King, ſhould ſuffer an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Death, and forfeit all the Eſtate and Honours be ſtood poſſeſſed of, his Name for ever remaining ſcandalous and execrable. Now that diſtracted</hi> Bergamaſco <hi>never conſidering what was ſaid by me, who never ſo much as once thought of the</hi> Nepotes <hi>of</hi> Rome, <hi>called me He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick, ſaying, that in deteſting</hi> Favourites <hi>I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted the</hi> Nepotes, <hi>for that</hi> Favourite
<hi>and</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re two Names, yet but one and the ſame thing; and tho I had not ſpoke a Word tending
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:98488:68"/>to that mad Notion, he attacked me as you all beheld. The</hi> Germans
<hi>with the reſt of the Spectators were ſurprized and amazed. With much difficulty the directed each to his Poſt, and diſpoſe the Multitude into a ſilent Auditory to hear the Propoſitions which were to be made in the Name of them all by a ruddy Lawer who had ſet them all a madding, and put into their Heads ſuch wild and extravagant Demands.</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Two Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets gave the ſignal for ſilence, when he ſtanding upon an eminent place in the midſt of the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, which ſwarmed about, delivered himſelf in this manner.</hi>
               </q> The thing we all aim at is the general Liberty of all, to be purchaſed by contriving how we may be ſubject to Juſtice not to Violence; That Reaſon may govern us, and not the abſolute Power of the Will; That we may belong to thoſe who Inherit, not to them that Raviſh us; That we may be the Care of Princes, not their Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize; and in Commonwealths, Companions not Slaves, Limbs not Lumber, Bodies and not Shadows. That the Rich Man hinder not the Poor from growing Rich, nor the Poor grow Rich by plundering the Wealthy. That the Nobleman deſpiſe not the Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, nor the Commoner hate the Nobleman. And that the whole Care of the Government be employed in encouraging the Poor to grow Rich, and Honouring the Vertuous, and in preventing the contrary. Care muſt be taken that no one Man become greater and more powerful than all the reſt, for he who excels all others deſtroys equality, and they that
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:98488:69"/>ſuffer him to exceed encourage him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire. Equality is the Harmony in which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the Muſick of the Commonwealths Peace, for when diſturbed by any Exceſs it becomes Diſcord, and that before was Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort becomes Noiſe. Commonwealths are to be ſo united with Kings, as the Earth (which repreſents the former) is with the Sea (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting the latter;) Theſe always em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace one another, yet ſo as the Earth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways defends it ſelf againſt the encroachment of the Sea by its Banks, the Sea always threatens the Earth, wears and endeavours to overflow and ſwallow it up, and the Earth ever fixed and unmoved oppoſes the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual motion and inconſtancy of the Sea. The Sea ſwells with every Wind, every Blaſt makes the Earth fruitful. The Sea grows rich with what the Earth commits to it, and the Earth with Hooks and Nets drains and depopulates the Sea. Even as all the Security and Shelter againſt the Sea is in the Land, which fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhes Harbours, ſo Commonwealths are a Refuge againſt the Revolutions and Storms of Kingdoms. Commonwealths ought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to make War with their Heads, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with their Hands, they muſt have Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Fleets ready in the greatneſs of their Stock, which is the Celerity that lays hold of all Opportunities. They are to make War upon Kings by ſetting them one againſt another, for Monarchs, tho they be Fathers, Sons, Brothers, and Relations, are like Steel and the File, which tho not only near Allied,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:98488:69"/>but the ſame Subſtance and Mettal, yet the File always cuts and wears away the Iron. Commonwealths are to aſſiſt raſh Princes ſo far as may ſerve to overthrow them, and the more cautious far enough to make them raſh. It is their beſt Policy to Honour Trade, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it enriches and carries Men throughout the World, gaining them Practical Experience, by which they diſcover the Ports, Cuſtoms, Government, Strength and Deſigns of their Neighbours. The Study of Politick and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks ought to be encouraged as advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to the Publick, and nothing ought to be ſo much contemned as Idleneſs, tho un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der never ſo ſpecious a Title, or Riches de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to Luxury. All Publick Sports ſhall conſiſt of the Exerciſe of Fire-armes, and handling of other Weapons, as is uſed in Battle, that they may be at once Uſeful and Diverting; at the ſame time Sports and Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, and then will it be decent to frequent the Theaters, when they are Academies. All Formality of Garb is to be abſolutely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and all the diſtinction betwixt the Rich Man and the Poor muſt be, that the former extend Relief, and the latter receive it; and Virtue and Valour ſhall make the difference betwixt the Nobleman and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner, for thoſe Virtues were the foundation of all ancient Nobility. I will here drop a few words out of <hi>Plato,</hi> let him that has need of them gather them up, for I don't know to what purpoſe I bring them, but ſome body or other perhaps may know to what purpoſe he
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:98488:70"/>ſpoke them in the 3d Dialogue, <hi>De repub. vel de Juſto.</hi> They are theſe. <hi>Igitur rempublicam adminiſtrantibus praecipue, ſi quibus aliis mentiri licet, vel hoſtium, vel civium cauſa in communem civitatis utilitatem, reliquis autem a mendacio ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinendum eſt.</hi> If it be lawful to any to Lye, it is chiefly allowable to them who govern the Commonwealth, either on account of the Enemies, or Citizens for the common advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the City, all others are to abſtain from Lying. I cannot but reflect, that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the Catholick Church condemns this Doctrine of <hi>Plato</hi>'s Commonwealth, yet there are many that value themſelves upon being his Commonwealth. Let us now come to what is propoſed by the Subjects of Kings. Theſe complain, that they are all become E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lective, becauſe thoſe who are and continue Hereditary, elect Favourites, who become Kings by their Election. This is that enrages them, becauſe the <hi>French</hi> tell us that Princes, who for the better government of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms wholly give themſelves up to their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourites, are like Galley Slaves who travel by force, turning their Backs to the Port they go to; and that the Favourites are like Juglers, who the more they deceive the more they ent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtain, and the better they conceal their ſlight from the Eyes, and baffle the Senſes and Underſtanding, the more they are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued and praiſed by him that pays for their Tricks to divert himſelf. Their chief Art conſiſts in making him believe that is full which is empty, that there is ſomething where
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:98488:70"/>there is nothing, that thoſe are Wounds in others which are but Bruiſes in his Armour, and that they throw away what they hide with their Hand. They ſay they give him Money, and when he looks upon it he finds Dirt or Rubbiſh. Theſe Companions are vile, but theſe Men make uſe of them for want of better, and ſo they affirm thoſe Kings are equally to blame who will not be what the great God made them, and thoſe who would be what he made them not. They preſume to ſay, that an abſolute Favourite brings upon Kings the ſame that Death does upon Man, <hi>(i. e.) Novam formam cadaveris.</hi> A new Form of a Carcaſs, to which follows Worms and Corruption, according to the Opinion of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> in his <hi>Prince. Fit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutio uſque ad materiam primam,</hi> that is, there remains nothing of what was, but the bare reſemblance. So much for this Point. Next let us go upon the Complaints againſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, and the reaſon there is for them. For my own part I know not who I ſpeak of, or who I ſpeak not of, whoever underſtands me may explain me. <hi>Ariſtole</hi> ſays, He is a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant who has more regard to his private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt than to the Publick. Whoſoever can tell Tale or Tidings of any who are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended under this definition, may give an account of them, and they ſhall be well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. They complain more grievouſly againſt Tyrants who receive benefits of them, than they that are oppreſt by them; for the Benefits of Tyrants make Men Criminals and
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:98488:71"/>Accomplices, and their Severity proves them Virtuous and Deſerving. They are of ſuch a Nature, that Innocence in their Dominions muſt he miſerable that it may be happy. A Tyrant in reſpect of his Covetouſneſs and Avarice is a Wild Beaſt, in reſpect of his Pride a Devil, and in reſpect of his Riotouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Luxury all manner of Wild Beaſts and Devils. No body conſpires againſt a Tyrant ſooner than himſelf; whence it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, 'tis eaſier to kill a Tyrant than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure him. The favour of a Tyrant is ever fatal, the greateſt good he does him he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours moſt, is to delay doing him harm. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyphemus</hi> in
<hi>Homer</hi> is the Emblem of Tyrants. He favoured <hi>Ulyſſes,</hi> diſcourſing with him, and enquiring into his Merits, he heard his Intreaties, ſaw his Diſtreſs, and all the Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he offered him was, that after eating all his Companions he would devour him laſt. Let no Man hope more favour from a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that devours thoſe under his power, than to be the laſt eaten; and it is to be obſerved, that tho the Tyrant grants it as a favour, he that is to be eaten takes the delay for an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Cruelty. He that is to devour you after all the reſt, begins to eat you in all thoſe he eats before you. The longer he delays feeding on you, the longer you have to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you ſhall become his Food. <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> was preſerved by the Gyant as Suſtenance, not as a Gueſt. To keep him in his Den in order to transfer him to his Stomach, was more like burying him alive than entertaining him.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:98488:71"/>
               <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> put him to ſleep with exceſs of Wine. The Bane of Tyrants is ſleep. You that are ſubject to them caſt them into a ſleep, harden your Spikes at the Fire, put out their Eyes, for that done it was no body did what every one deſired ſhould be done. The Tyrant <hi>Polyphemus</hi> cryed, <hi>Nobody</hi> had blinded him, becauſe
<hi>Ulyſſes</hi> with wonderful ſagacity had told him his Name was <hi>Nobody.</hi> He named him with deſire of revenge, and defended him by the double meaning of the Word. Tyrants themſelves excuſe thoſe that kill them, or put out their Eyes. <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> made his eſcape diſguiſed with a Sheeps Skin among the Sheep he kept. That which a Tyrant moſt care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully preſerves, preſerves his deſtroyer againſt him. Having premiſed thus much, it remains to tell you, that we Subjects are met here this day to conſult how we may defend our ſelves againſt the Arbitrary Power of thoſe who either mediate, or immediately govern king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Commonwealths<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The chief Heads I have to offer to this purpoſe are theſe. That all Councellors be fixed for ever in their Poſts, without hoping to riſe a ſtep higher, becauſe there is no room for Application or Juſtice, where a Man has one Charge and aims at another, and the Ambition of aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to another more eminent Employment makes him look upon himſelf as a Paſſenger not a Reſident, ſo that his Charge ſerves only to purchaſe, that he aſpires to, and being thus, diſtracted he attends neither, not that he has, becauſe he deſigns to leave it, nor that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:98488:72"/>he deſires becauſe as yet he has it not. Every Man is uſeful in that Poſt where he has gained Experience; and troubleſome where he learns the firſt Rudiments, becauſe they remove from Buſineſs they were verſed in, to that they do not underſtand. What Honours are confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on them muſt ſtill be ſuch as are proper to their Profeſſion, not mixing Civil and Military, leſt the Sword and the Gown ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Habit diſagreeable, for the Gown is cumberſom to the Sword, and the Sword diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dains to be hid under the Gown. The next thing is, that Rewards be indiſpenſable, that is, not only that they be not beſtowed on the unworthy, but that they be not permitted to pretend to them, for if the Reward of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue be exhauſted on Vice, the Prince or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth will be robbed of their greateſt Treaſure, and the Metal of which the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence conſiſts will become baſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible. Neither the Deſerving nor Unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving muſt expect it, the former becauſe it muſt be immediately given him, the latter becauſe he muſt never have it. Gold and Diamonds were better employed in making Fetters to ſecure Criminals, than in Military and Honourable Enſigns beſtowed on Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds and Vicious Perſons. This Doctrine was well received among the <hi>Romans,</hi> who with a Branch of Lawrel or Oak rewarded more Wounds, and Victories over Cities, Provinces and Kingdoms, than it bore Leaves. Let only the Brave and Experienced be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Counsels of State and War; let the
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:98488:72"/>Blood they have ſpilt and their Qualifications, not the Pride of long Genealogies, be their Recommendation. The Brave and Fortunate are to be preferred to Military Employments. To be Fortunate as well as Valiant is a great addition. <hi>Lucan</hi> gives this advice,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Fatis accede, Deiſque,</l>
               <l>Et cole felices, miſeros fuge.</l>
            </q>
            <p>I have always read theſe Words with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and this admirable Poet (let who will deny it) with attention as preferable to all but <hi>Homer</hi> for Politicks and Military Sence. The Courts of Juſtice are to be filled with Learned and Diſintereſted Perſons. He who is not Covetous, is ſubſervient to no Vice, becauſe Vices induce the Intereſt for which they are ſold. Let them know the Laws, but not more than the Laws. Let them cauſe them to be obeyed, not make them obedient to their Wills. This is the very Touchſtone of Judgment. I have ſaid, you may now ſay what occurs, and propoſe the moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and practicable Redreſs againſt your Grievances. He ceaſed, and the Auditors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a multitude of ſeveral Nations and Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, there enſued ſuch a confuſed buzzing of unintelligible Jargons, that it ſounded as if the whole Clack of the Tower of <hi>Babel</hi> had been turned looſe in that place. They underſtood not themſelves, nor one another. All was filled with Contention and Diſcord, and by their Looks and Actions they appeared
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:98488:73"/>like an Aſſembly of People Diſtracted, or Poſſeſt. Then the Congregation of Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, to whom the Sheepskins bound about with Slings are rather a reproach than a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt the Weather, ſaid. They muſt be heard immediately before any others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Sheep had rebelled, ſaying, that they had kept them from the Wolves who eat them by one at a time, to the end they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves might ſhear, flea, kill, and ſell them all at at once. And that ſince the Wolves at moſt devoured, one, two, ten, or twenty, their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign was, that the Wolves ſhould guard them againſt the Shepherds, not the Shepherds againſt the Wolves. That they looked upon the Hunger of their Enemies as leſs prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial to them, than the Avarice of their Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, and had brought the Shepherds Dogs as Evidence againſt them. There was not one Soul but ſaid, <hi>We gueſs what they would be at, the Sheep are no Fools if they bring this to paſs.</hi> At this ſtand they were when the Hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected them, and being all enraged, ſome cryed, <hi>We are for the Wolves;</hi> Others, <hi>They are all Wolves;</hi> Others, <hi>It is all the ſame thing;</hi> Others, <hi>They are all bad;</hi> and many others contradicted them. The Lawyers perceiving them ready to fall to Loggerheads, in order to appeaſe them ſaid. <hi>It was a Caſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired mature Deliberation, therefore adviſed to defer it till the next day, and to have recourſe to the Churches to implore a Bleſſing on their Debates.</hi> The <hi>Frenchmen</hi> hearing that Word, cryed out, <hi>If there muſt be recourſe to the Churches we are
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:98488:73"/>undone, and we fear the ſame ſhould befall us as did the Owl when ſhe was ſick. She adviſing about her Diſtemper with the Fox, whom ſhe judged the moſt skilful among the Beaſts, and alſo with the Rook whom ſhe took for a Phyſician becauſe ſhe often ſaw him upon Carrion Mules, they told her there was no remedy for her but to repair to the Temples, The Owl hearing their Opinion an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Then my Caſe is deſperate if the remedy is only to be found in thoſe Holy Places, for I have left them all in the dark, ſucking the Oyl out of the Lamps, and there is not an Idol that I have not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrayed.</hi> The <hi>Italian</hi> hearing this Diſcourſe, with all his might cryed out. <hi>The Compariſon is allowed you, and we make bold to put you and all ſuch as feed upon the Church in mind of what</hi> Homer
<hi>relates of the Mice, when they fought with the Frogs, for then they having recourſe to the Gods for their aſſiſtance, all the Deities excuſed themſelves, ſome ſaying they had gnawed their Hands, others their Feet, others their Garments, others their Crowns, and others the Tips of their Noſes, ſo that there was none but miſſed ſome part of his Image, and bore the marks of their Teeth. Apply this Fable you</hi> Calviniſt, Lutheran, <hi>and</hi> Huguenot
<hi>Mice, and then conſider who is there in Heaven to relieve you.</hi> Good God, what a hideous Tumult and Hurlibury the Monſieurs raiſed againſt the poor <hi>Italian,</hi> the Confuſion of Hell is nothing compared to it. The whole Multitude ran great danger in endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to pacifie them. At length with held but no ſilence, they all parted, all complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what they endured, and every one
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:98488:74"/>raving, that he might change his Condition with another.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Hour expires, <hi>Jove</hi> ſtops further Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</note>As theſe things were in agitation upon Earth, and the Gods attentively looking on, the <hi>Sun</hi> ſaid. <hi>The Hour is now at the laſt gaſp, and the Shade of the Gnomon will in a trice touch the Number Five. Great Father of all, do thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine whether</hi> Fortune <hi>ſhall proceed before the Hour expire, or elſe wheel and rowl back as ſhe uſed to do. Jove</hi> anſwered,
<hi>I have obſerved, that during this Hour which gave to every Man what he deſerved, thoſe who becauſe they were poor and deſpicable, were alſo humble, are become proud and intolerable; and thoſe who being rich and reſpected were conſequently vicious, perverſe, arrogant, and wicked, ſeeing themſelves poor and abject, are become penitent, baſhful, and pious, ſo that the conſequence is, that thoſe who were good Men are become Knaves, and the Knaves good Men. This little time may ſuffice to ſatisfie the Complaints of Mortals, who ſeldom know what they ask of us, for ſuch is their frailty, that he who does ill when he can, forbears when he can do it no longer, and this is not repentance, but a forced refraining from wickedneſs. Oppreſſion and Miſery curb, but do not correct them. Honour and Proſperity make them act, that which if they had ſooner attained them they would always have acted. Let</hi> Fortune <hi>direct her Wheel and Globe in their former courſe, and cauſe Merits in the Wiſe, and Puniſhment to the Senſeleſs, wherein our infallible Providence and Divine Preſence ſhall always be aſſiſting to her. Let all Men receive what ſhe diſtributes, that is, either Frowns or
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:98488:74"/>Smiles, ſince neither are bad in themſelves, for patiently enduring the former, and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly contemning the latter, they both become e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually advantageous. And let him that receives and makes his misfortune of what he takes to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, complain of himſelf, and not of</hi> Fortune, <hi>who gives to all indifferently and without favour or affection. We permit</hi> Fortune <hi>to complain a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Men, who making a wrong uſe of their Proſperity or Adverſity, defame and curſe her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fortune</hi> reſtores her Wheel to its former mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>At this time it ſtruck Five, And the Hour of all Men was at an end. Then <hi>Fortune</hi> well pleaſed with what <hi>Jove</hi> had ſaid, chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hands, began again to ravel up the Cares of the World, and unwind what was wound backwards, which done fixing her Globe on the Regions of the Air, ſhe ſlid down as if it had been upon Ice, till ſhe found her ſelf upon Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Gods take leave, and break up the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</note>
               <hi>Vulcan,</hi> that Blackſmith God who keeps time with his Hammer, cryed, <hi>It is hungry Weather, and I being in haſte to obey, left two Ropes of Garlick a roaſting at my Forge, to break my faſt with the Cyclops.</hi> All-ruling <hi>Jove</hi> ordered Meat to be brought, and immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there appeared
<hi>Iris</hi> (Chambermaid to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi>) with Nectar, and <hi>Ganimede</hi> with a Plat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Ambroſia. <hi>Juno,</hi> who ſpyed him by her Husbands ſide, and had more mind to ſuck his Blood than to ſwill the Heavenly Liquor, ſpitting Fire, and hiſſing like an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der when his Tail had been trod, ſaid, <hi>Either this Bardaſh or I muſt reign in</hi> Olympus, <hi>or elſe I will ſue for a Divorce in</hi> Hymen's <hi>Court.</hi>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:98488:75"/>Had not the Eagle the Rogue beſtrided ſlunk away with him, ſhe had made Hawks Meat of him with her Nails. <hi>Jove</hi> began to blow his Thunderbolt, and ſhe ſaid,
<hi>I will ſnatch it from you, to deſtroy that Sodomite Page. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva,</hi> the Product of
<hi>Jupiters</hi> Noddle, who, had he been a Blockhead, could ne're have been born, with fair Words ſoothed <hi>Juno</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged with the ſight of her Husbands Vile Cup bearer. But
<hi>Venus</hi> in a ſume heightned her Jealouſie, ſcolding like a Butter-whore, and rated
<hi>Jove</hi> as if he had been a Chimney-ſweeper. Then <hi>Mercury</hi> letting looſe his Clack, ſaid, All would do well, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired them not to diſturb the Heavenly Banquet. <hi>Mars</hi> ſeeing the Ambroſia handed about in China Diſhes, like a roaring Bully Deity cried out; <hi>Dam your Coffee-Diſhes, let the Moon and other Petty Goddeſſes drink out of them.</hi> Then mixing <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Neptune,</hi> he ſwallowed down both the Gods at two or three pulls, and laying hold of <hi>Pan</hi> he ſliced him out, and cutting up his Flocks of Sheep, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured them by Wholeſale. <hi>Saturn</hi> ſtayed his Stomach with half a dozen Children. <hi>Mercury,</hi> like a true Spunger, ſtuck cloſe to <hi>Venus,</hi> who was cramming her Chops with Biſcuits and Sugar Plums. <hi>Pluto</hi> drew out of his Snapſack ſome Griskins, <hi>Proſerpine</hi> had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for his Journey; <hi>Vulcan,</hi> who ſtood gaping, perceiving it, came limping towards him, and courteouſly intruding himſelf with much Ceremony, began to lay on and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. The <hi>Sun,</hi> who is the Father of Jollity,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:98488:75"/>pulling out his Lute, ſung a Hymn in praiſe of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> running diviſion without end. <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> being offended at the gravity of the Tune, and ſeriouſneſs of the Words, he to the harmony of a pair of Tongs roared out a Bawdy Song, and ſhe rattling a pair of overgrown Caſtinets, danced a Jig as if ſhe would have skipp'd over the Heavens, and ſhaken her ſelf to Attoms, tickling with her wanton motions the Hearts of all the Gods. Her Dance ſet them all into ſuch an itching, that they could not hold their Hands or Feet ſtill. <hi>Jove,</hi> whoſe Mouth watered at the lend Motions of the Goddeſs, ſaid;
<hi>This is a Farewell to</hi> Ganimede, <hi>and no Quarrel.</hi> He gave them Leave, and they being all full and ſatisfied, ſlunk away, crying, <hi>The Devil take the hindmoſt;</hi> and the lot fell to the <hi>Eagle-ſtriding Cup-bearer.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
